Inside this lecture,
let's try to create that DTO classes representing each of the entity classes that we have inside our
accounts microservice.
Before I try to do that, I just wanted to reiterate one more time.
If you are clear about all these basic concepts that we typically follow whenever we're trying to create
REST APIs, please try to watch the video at a higher speed so that you won't get bored.
I'm trying to cover all these basics so that these concepts will help the students
or junior developers who are not aware about all these basic concepts.
But I promise you there is a lot of interesting and exciting stuff ahead.
Once we build all these microservices like accounts, cards and loans, we are going to explore a lot
of interesting topics.
So brace yourself.
Now coming to our DTO pattern, I'm going to create a new package here and the package name
I'm going to keep it as dto and inside this dto package
first, I'm going to create an DTO class with the name AccountsDto. It is always advisable to end your
DTO classes with the name DTO.
That way you can always know the difference between a DTO class and a normal spring data JPA entity
class.
So inside this DTO class, what I'm going to do is, I'll go to Accounts, I will take all the fields that
I want to send to my client application.
So I don't want to send the customerId to my client application.
Why do they want the Id, which is specific to my internal database?
So these kind of data filtering also we can do with the help of DTO pattern.
That's why I'm ignoring these customerId into my DTO class.
So what I can do is I can take this account number, account type and branch address and I can mention
them inside my DTO class.
I'm removing all the code related to the JPA.
So these are the three fields that I have created inside my DTO class.
As a next step, we need to create the getters and setters for these class also.
So instead,
so I'm going to use a lombok here instead of mentioning @Getter, @Setter.
Separately, I can mention an annotation which is @Data.
So if you open this Data annotation, you can see this is a combination of Getter, Setter, RequiredArgsConstructor,
ToString, EqualsAndHashCode and value.
So whenever I'm using this annotation behind the scenes it is going to generate all the Getters, Setters
equals(), hashCode(), toString() everything it is going to generate.
The reason why I have not used this @Data inside our entity classes is I don't want to generate
the hashcode or equals code method for our entity classes because sometimes it is going to create issues
with the Spring data JPA framework.
With that reason, I have not used the @Data on top of our entity classes.
Now, as a next step, I'm going to create a next dto, so let me copy this class and paste it again
and I'm going to rename it to CustomerDto.
So here inside the CustomerDto, I want to use @Data annotation, but I want to maintain the fields
related to customer.
Like I don't want to send the CustomerId, I just wanted to send name, email and mobile number to
my client applications.
That's why I'm going to take these fields and mention them here and I'm removing the JPA specific annotations
here.
So with this we have the CustomerDto also ready, and I'm not creating any DTO class which is a combination
of Customer and Accounts, entity class, because for now I'm not going to have that scenario inside
our Rest API.
But definitely when we progress in the coming sections, we are going to have a different, different
DTOs which will aggregate the data and send the same to the client application. After this CustomerDto
and AccountsDto,
I want to create two more DTOs that will help me to send the response to the client application
in certain scenarios. Think like my client application gave a request to save the data into the database.
My rest API or my microservice will accept that data, will store the data inside database.
So as a response, I may want to send a successful response or an error response.
So in such scenarios I can't use this DTOs because they don't have any fields representing the status
code and status message inside my response.
So for the same, I'm going to create a first a new DTO class and the class is going to be
ResponseDto.  So let me create this class. Inside this class
also, I'm going to mention @Data annotation, apart from @Data annotation, I'm
also going to mention @AllArgsConstructor annotation.
The reason why I'm mentioning these AllArgsConstructor is by default.
The @Data annotation will not generate a constructor which accepts all arguments present inside my DTO class.
That's why I'm creating this. In future
I need the constructor that accepts
all arguments as an input parameter.
That's why I have mentioned this annotation.
Now I want to mention two different fields here.
The very first one is private string statusCode.
So this is going to send the what is the status code to my client applications, like I can send 200 if
it is successful or
similarly, I can also send other status code like 500, which represents there is an error.
Very similarly, I'm going to mention private string instead of statusCode, I'm going to mention statusMsg,
which is status message.
With these two fields we are going to send what is the status code and status message inside the response
using which my client can easily understand whether the given operation is successful or not.
Now, just like normal ResponseDto, I also want to build a error response DTO which we can use whenever
there is an error or exception happened inside the microservice.
So the class name is going to be ErrorResponseDto and inside this DTO class I'm going to mention the
same annotation which is @Data and @AllArgsConstructor.
And we are going to create four fields here.
The very first one is private string apiPath.
So this represents what is the API path that my client application trying to invoke.
I want to send inside the error response also that you invoke this path and it failed due to so and
so error code and the error message and so &
so error time.
That's why let me try to create other three fields that we need private HttpStatus.
What is the errorCode.
So I'm going to send the error code which is of type HttpStatus to the client applications sharing
what is the reason that the API invocation failed?
Now, after errorCode, I'm going to create a new field with the name errorMsg and at last I'm
going to create a new field with the name errorTime.
So this is going to return LocalDateTime.
So with these four fields, my clients will have all the information like which API they tried to invoke.
What is the error code that they received, what is the error message and at what time the error happened.
This will also help the developers and the client side to debug the logs inside their system and accordingly
they can try to debug the issue. With this,
we have created all the required DTOs for our accounts
microservice.
We can build the mapper logic or aggregation logic based upon the needs in the coming sections, but
for now we have not implemented DTO pattern completely inside our microservice.
We just created DTOs, we created entities, so there should be some mapper logic that we need to build
and we are going to build that as we are making progress inside this course.
Before I try to close this lecture, I want to highlight that this DTO pattern is initially recommended
by Martin Fowler inside his blog.
So like you can see, he gave a description why we should follow this data transfer object pattern.
And he also gave a logic. Suppose inside a database,
there is an album table and artist table which holds a title and name.
And if one of the client they want the both title and the name of the artist inside the response, then
definitely we will have an AlbumDto, which will hold both title and artist.
All the data inside the entities will be mapped to dto with the help of this assembler logic or mapper
logic in between and if needed, we can also write some serialization specific logic inside our DTO
classes and in some project or in some organizations,
they call this DTO objects as Value object or Transfer object.
So regardless, the name that they are using, if they are using different pojo classes instead of database
entity Pojo classes to transfer the data between multiple layers of the application, then they are
following the DTO pattern.
I'm going to mention this URL inside the GitHub repo page and at the same time I'm also going to attach
this URL link to this lecture.
If you are interested to read this page, feel free to do the same. With this,
we have successfully created DTO classes inside our Accounts
Microservice.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.