Welcome back
As of now, we have created a mapping logic.
Now, as a next step, let's go to the AccountServiceImpl.
Here,
First, I need to convert the input received customer DTO to Customer entity object.
For the same,
I'm going to write a piece of logic here.
First, I'm going to create a field with the name customer.
Post that with the help of customer mapper that we have created, I'm going to invoke the method, which
is map to customer and to this method we need to pass what is the DTO and post that we need to pass
a new object of Customer.
So with this line, all the data that I have inside this CustomerDto will be transferred to this Customer
object and the same will be stored with the help of this customer field.
Now I want to save these customer information into the customer table.
For the same,
I need to use the CustomerRepository interface and using this interface we can call a method called
save().
You can see there are multiple save(), but since we want to save a single entity, we need to
invoke the save method.
And to this method we need to pass the Customer object that we have.
So with this code, the Spring Data JPA framework will take care of taking the input object, preparing
an SQL statement, creating a connection with the database, executing the statement, committing the
transaction, closing the connection.
So all those boilerplate code which developers use to write now will be taken care by the spring data
JPA.
So the save method I have not written inside the CustomerRepository.
It is coming from the spring data JPA since we extended this JpaRepository class.
So now we successfully save the customer details into the database.
When this customer details is saved into the database.
Very first time the customerId will be generated automatically by the spring Data JPA framework.
So in order to know what is the customerId, we need to store the return type of the save() method into
another variable called savedCustomers.
Now, with the help of this customer details, I want to create a new bank account for this customer.
The customer is only going to give what is his name, email and mobileNumber with his customer details.
I want to create a new bank account. For the same,
we need to use the AccountsRepository and invoke the save method. To this method, We need to pass the
object of Accounts entity populated with the values like customerId, accountNumber.
What is the account type?
What is the branch address?
All those details.
So to populate a new accounts object, let me create a new private method inside this service class
to save some time.
I'm pasting this private method.
You can see this is the private method which is create new account.
It is going to accept the customer entity and inside this customer entity there will be a customerId
which is populated by the previous operation we have done here.
So I'm taking the customerId from the customer and the same I'm populating into the accounts object
which I have created inside this method.
And now coming to the accountNumber previously I was telling it is the responsibility of the developer
to generate the account number which is a primary key and send the same to the spring data JPA using
the same account number, it is going to insert a new record.
So here I have written a logic that will give me a ten digit random account number. Post that I'm setting
the same random account number into the Account entity object followed by what is the account type and
branch address.
So this account type is coming from the accounts constraints we have created previously.
The savings means it is a savings account and the branch address.
I'm just putting it as
123 Main Street, New York.
So this is a simple method which will take Customer entity class and will return a Accounts entity class.
So to this save() method,
Since I need to pass the Accounts entity pojo class, what I'm going to do is I'm going to invoke the
new account method and pass the saved customer object that we have.
So behind the scenes, a new account will be created with the customerId that we have passed to this
method, and that way we are establishing a link between a customer and new account that is created
with this everything looking good, but we are not handling the exceptions properly.
Think like someone is trying to use the same mobile number again and again.
We don't want that to happen.
We want only one customer to use a single mobile number, but multiple customers can have same email
or same name, but we don't want the mobile number to be used by multiple customers.
That's why we need to have some logic to handle these kind of scenarios.
For the same, let me create a new package where I can store all the classes related to exception handling.
So the package name is going to be exception.
Inside this exception package, I'm going to create a
new custom exception.
And the name of this new custom exception is CustomerAlreadyExistsException.
.
So this is the class name that I want to keep.
And since I want to write my own custom exception, I need to make sure I'm extending the RuntimeException.
So any custom exception that you want to create, it should extend the RuntimeException.
Now, I also want to create a constructor for this class which is going to accept the exception message
post that once this constructor is invoked with this message
details.
Since we are trying to extend another class, we need to make sure we are invoking the parent constructor
also, for the same
I'm using super(message).
So with this what I'm trying to do is whenever someone is trying to create an object of this custom
exception by passing this message, value the same
I'm passing to this RuntimeException because I'm extending this as a superclass.
Now, on top of this custom exception, I'm going to mention an annotation which is ResponseStatus
to this ResponseStatus
I'm going to send the value as HttpStatus.BAD_REQUEST.
Whenever I'm trying to throw this exception in the response, my client is going to receive a status
saying that 400 which represents bad requests.
So this is the custom exception I have created.
Now, as a next step, I can go to my Service class.
Here first
I need to make sure I'm validating if there is any existing customer with a given mobileNumber, which
means I need to execute a query on my database by passing a mobileNumber and to identify if there is
any existing record.
Can we do that with the help of this CustomerRepository?
Think about it.
We declared customerId as an primary key field inside our entity, so this CustomerRepository will
have a find()  with the help of Id, which is customerId.
My framework can only provide a find() based upon my primary key values, which is customerId.
That's why if you go and check the ServiceImpl class using this CustomerRepository, I can invoke find
by method which will accept the customerId as a input because customerId is a primary key that we
have defined.
But are we receiving the customerId inside the request when they're trying to create the account very
first time?
Off course we won't receive that.
That's why we need to write a different method that will help us to query the database based upon a
mobileNumber.
For the same, let's go to the CustomerRepository.
Inside this interface, we need to define an abstract method by following some naming convention and
the Spring Data JPA framework is going to write the logic of fetching the record based upon the column
that we have mentioned.
So let's try to understand how to do that.
So here I'm going to create a method that is going to return optional of customer, because for a given
mobileNumber there can be a customer or they cannot be any customer.
That's why I need to make sure I'm using optional of customer.
So now I need to write a method with the name findByMobileNumber().
To this method I need to pass the input which is mobile number itself.
So whenever I write this method inside my repository interface, my spring data JPA framework will take
care of fetching the record based upon a mobileNumber.
So here you may have a question like how your spring data JPA know that you are trying to query based
upon a single column which is mobileNumber, but at the same you can see if you see the naming convention
findBy whenever we are using findBy we're telling to the spring data JPA framework.
We are trying to run a select query using the column mobileNumber.
So this field name mobileNumber has to match with what you have mentioned inside your pojo entity class.
Don't worry about this small letter that we have.
It is not case sensitive, but please make sure the spelling is correct
like mobileNumber is matching with what you have mentioned here.
This way we are telling to spring data JPA framework to fetch the records from this column.
What if you have multiple columns inside your requirements?
In that case, you need to write and followed by what is the second parameter and the second parameter
also you need to pass as a method parameter to this method.
I talked extensively about this concept inside my spring course.
We call this concept as derived named method because based upon the method names, my spring data JPA
framework is going to prepare the SQL queries and run the same onto the database.
So now let's go and use these fineByMobileNumber inside our ServiceImpl class.
So I'm just trying to invoke fineByMobileNumber and to this method we need to pass the mobileNumber
that we received inside the CustomerDto.
So I'm trying to invoke CustomerDto.getMobileNumber().
So whatever returned by my spring data JPA framework, I'm going to
catch that into an object with the name optional customer.
So now using this optional customer object, I need to validate if there is an existing customer available
inside the database or not.
For the same, I'm going to write an If check here like you can see with the help of this
OptionalCustumer.isPresent(), which means this is present is going to return a boolean value true
.
If there is a record inside this optional object.
If there is a record, then I want to throw a CustomerAlreadyExistingException with a message customer
already registered with a given mobile number.
So this is what I'm doing inside this if block with this now I'm doing the validation and I'm throwing
the custom validation exception.
But where is the logic to handle this exception?
I'll throw this CustomerAlreadyExistingException to my parent method, which is inside my controller
and inside my controller.
I can handle the exception using catch block and I can send an error response to my client application.
But in future, if there is some other place where you're trying to throw the same exception, you're
going to throw again.
A different controller method has to catch that.
So there is a lot of exception
handling logic is going to be duplicated inside your application.
To overcome this challenge.
The best standard is you need to write a GlobalExceptionHandlingLogic.
So for the same under these exception package, I'm going to create a new class, and the class name
that I want to do here is GlobalExceptionHandler.
So this is the class where I want to write all the Global exception logic.
So whenever you want to write some global exception logic, we need to make sure you are mentioning
the annotation @ControllerAdvice.
Using this annotation, we are telling to the Springboard framework whenever an exception happens in
any of my control not only accounts controller in future I may write different controller in all such
controllers.
If any exception happens, please invoke a method that I'm going to write inside this class.
So here, inside this class I'm going to create a new method.
Let me paste the method to save some time.
You can also get this method from the GitHub repo so you can see the method name is handleCustomer
handleCustomerAlreadyExistingException().
You can write any method name.
This method is going to handle the exception which is CustomerAlreadyExistException.
And we should also pass this web request parameter to this method because inside our ErrorResponseDto
we decided to send the what is the path that my client application is trying to invoke?
So you can see using this web request, I'm trying to get the get description. When I pass this false
value to this get description, I'll only get the API information.
Whereas if I try to pass the true value, I'll get many other information like what is the IP address
of my client?
All those details.
But for now I just wanted to send the only API path.
So using ErrorResponseDto constructor I'm trying to pass what is the path that my client is trying to
invoke and the HttpStatus as BAD_REQUEST and the message that we receive from the customer already
CustomerAlreadyExistingException which we are trying to throw from the AccountService.
So we will receive this message. And at last, what is our date and time right now when this exception
happened?
That's why we have created a error response and we have annotated @AllArgsConstructor because
we need a constructor that accept all these four parameters.
So right now, with the help of this constructor, I have created a DTO object and the same I'm trying
to send as inside the ResponseEntity as a body.
So you can see here this ResponseEntity object.
It is accepting the body as a very first parameter and the second parameter what is the HttpStatusCode
.
So I'm trying to send the bad request as a HttpStatusCode, which will throw 400 to the client application
saying that you are sending some bad data.
For more details, check the body of the Response.
So now here I have written a method and in future I may return more methods which will handle more custom
exception logics.
How my spring boot framework will know that this method has to be invoked whenever there is an exception.
CustomerAlreadyExist.
Exception is being thrown. For the same,
what we need to do is we need to mention an annotation which is ExceptionHandler.
This annotation we need to pass what is the exception name that this method is supposed to handle.
So this method is supposed to handle CustomerAlreadyExistsExcepiton.
That's why I have mentioned this .class here.
So now with these changes we should be good.
Let's go to the AccountServiceImpl, here
everything is looking good.
We need to go to the controller class. Here first
I need to do the autowiring of my service class to these AccountsController
For the same,
I'm going to mention private
AccountService and accountService is the field name.
Now I can mention @Autowired on top of these field which will take care of autowiring.
But I don't want to go with the field autowiring.
Instead I want to go with the constructor autowiring, which is the recommended approach.
For the same, I need to mention an annotation which is AllArgsConstructor and with this Lombok annotation
AccountsController is going to have a constructor that accepts the IAccountService as the input parameter.
Like I said before, whenever you have only single constructor then you don't need to mention
@Autowired annotation anywhere, either inside your constructor or inside your class.
So now, using this AccountService, I'm going to invoke the createAccount method.
And to this method I'm going to pass the CustomerDto object.
And if there is no exception, which means my next line will be executed and here will be sending this
successful response.
Whereas if there is an exception inside my service due to this business exception, then definitely
it will never reach to my controller layer.
Instead, it will go to the GlobalExceptionHandler and this ErrorResponseDto will be written to my end
user.
But here you may have a question like what if there is some RuntimeException due to any other exceptions?
Don't worry about that.
I'm going to handle that in the coming lectures.
For now, let's try to save these changes.
Do a build.
You can see my automatic restart with the help of dev tools might have failed.
That's why it wrote these hard swap fail.
So whenever you get this kind of scenario because you might have done a lot many changes which can't
be recognized by the dev tools, then you need to stop the server and start it again manually.
So let me do a build.
Once the build is completed.
I'm trying to start my application.
My application started successfully at the port 8080.
As a next step, we can go and send a request to my create API and validate if my account is successfully
created or not.
For the same, I came to the postman.
Postman is an tool using which we can invoke REST APIs easily.
If you don't have this tool, please download from the web and I'm going to show a lot many APIs inside
this course and I'll populate lot many requests.
So to make your life easy, what I'm going to do is I'm going to upload this entire microservices collection
into the root location of my GitHub repo.
What you can do is you can download this collection and you can go to the file and click on this import
option that you have in the postman and you can drop the collection.
Basically it is a Json file.
As soon as you drop all the operations that I have inside, my collections will be downloaded into your
postman.
You just have to follow these instructions.
You don't have to type all this one this way it will save some time for you.
So as of now you can see I have create account request where I'm trying to send a post request this
API which is localhost 8080/api/create to this API under the body.
I need to send the json with the name as Madan Reddy.
.
This is my name.
That's why I'm sending.
Please feel free to send your own name.
And this is my official email and this is the sample mobile number.
I'm not mentioning my actual mobile number just for some privacy here, but please make sure this name
email, mobile number has to match with the fields that you have inside your customer data.
If you see inside the AccountsController, we're accepting the customer data as a input RequestBody.
So the fields has to match like name, email and mobileNumber.
These names has to match with what you are sending inside the Json.
If the fields are matching, then the spring boot is going to take care of converting this Json to the
dto object.
How this is going to happen Inside the spring boot, there are Jackson libraries with the help of those
Jackson libraries, the conversion from Json to Pojo object.
And similarly, when we return the Pojo object in the Response.
The same will be converted to Json and send back to the client.
So let me click on this send button.
As soon as I click send you can see I'm getting an exception.
The reason is my spring data JPA framework did not receive the data like createdBy and createdAt this
are not null values.
For the same, we can go to the service class before we try to save this customer information.
We need to pass like customer.setCreatedAt(LocalDateTime.now())
So with that I'm populating the createdat.
Very similarly, I'll invoke the set createdBy.
So for now I'm just trying to mention anonymous.
So someone is trying to create this account.
Later on I'll show you how to automatically populate this
createdAt, createdBy the help of Spring Data JPA Framework.
For now, let's try to populate this values manually.
Very similarly, I'm also going to mention
the same for Account object as well.
So just after this branch address, I'm going to do the same for the Account object.
So with this we should be good.
Let me save the changes and do a build.
Now the build is completed.
The server also might have restarted successfully.
Here
let me try to invoke this API again.
This time you can see I'm getting a successful response status code and status message, which is 201
account created successfully, and this is the status that we are returning with the help of ResponseEntity.status
.
And this is the body that we are sending inside the Response.
So let's try to invoke the operation again with the same mobileNumber.
We should get a business exception.
You can see I'm getting a API path like I tried to invoke this path error code, bad request error message
like so and so user already registered with the so-and-so mobile number and this is the error time.
So my exception handling also working fine.
Let's go to the H2 console and validate if the records are saved successfully or not.
So here I need to invoke H2 console and connect to my H2 console.
First
I will try to invoke customer table here.
You can see these are the details that we have inserted.
And very similarly I can check the accounts table and this is the account random account number that
is created and the customer ID also link between accounts and customer table.
This way we have successfully created create API inside accounts microservice.
I hope you are super super clear.
Please try to understand and digest all this information because I'm going to give an activity for you
where you need to build all these logic for cards and loans microservice by yourself by referring to
the code present inside the GitHub repo.
So understanding this is very important.
If you face any issues, don't worry, I'm going to explain cards and loans microservice very quickly
as well.
So with this we have developed only create operation inside our AccountsMicroservices
.
We should also develop, read, update and delete APIs.
Are you excited?
I'm also super excited that I'm making some progress with you.
Let's try to implement a read API or select API in the next lecture.
Thank you.
Bye.