Now, inside this lecture, let's try to create a new rest API inside accounts microservice that will
help us to delete the existing customer and account details and how I'm going to support this API is
my client application
they have to invoke my delete API along with the mobile number. Based upon the given mobile number
I Will try to load the customer entity details from the database.
From the Customer entity.
I'll be getting customerId, using customerId, I'm going to delete the records present in both tables,
which is inside the accounts and customer because both tables have this common column, which is customerId.
So let's do the same for the same.
First, I need to create a new method inside my IAccountService interface.
So let me create a new method here.
So this is the new method with the name deleteAccount().
And this is also going to return a boolean value saying that if the delete operation is successful or
not and it is going to accept the mobile number as an input parameter. Now we can go to the AccountService
and I'm going to put the cursor where I want my method to be generated.
Now I'll go to the top and I'll run this error and click on this implement methods and click okay.
So this will generate a new empty method inside deleteAccount().
So now, quickly, I'm going to paste a few lines of code which we can discuss, and this is going to
be super, super easy.
The reason why I'm saying easy is it's always easy to destroy, to delete something, but it's very
hard to create something from scratch.
That's why I always feel like deleting something is very easy.
Now here I'm pasting few lines of code.
First, I'm trying to fetch the customer details based upon the findByMobileNumber() method available
inside CustomerRepository to this method we're passing mobile number as input.
If there is no record exist, we are throwing the ResourceNotFoundException.
Now I have Customer entity in my hand with this Customer entity
I'm going to get the customerId and with the help of this AccountRepository and CustomerRepository,
I'm going to invoke this methods deleteById() and deleteByCustomerId().
So this deleteById() is available from the framework.
If you see this method available inside the crud repository belongs to the framework.
So what this method is going to do is it is going to delete the record based upon the primary key value.
Since inside the customer table the primary key is customerId, we are able to invoke the deleteById()
But for the account table
In order to invoke the deleteById(), we should pass the what is the account number so I can fetch the
account number by firing a query again on top of the accounts table, but it is unnecessary firing of
a query.
Instead,
I will try to delete the record based upon the customerId column present inside the accounts table.
Since this customerId is not a primary key inside the accounts table, we need to write this method
inside the AccountsRepository.
So here I'm going to create this method which which will return void and the method name is deleteByCustomerId
and it is going to accept customerId value as an input.
With this my Spring Data JPA Behind the scenes it is going to generate a delete query just like
findBy() indicates select query deleteBy indicates to prepare a delete query to the spring data JPA framework
and here the column name that we want to consider is customerId.
That's why I have to mention the same field name present inside the Accounts entity like this is the
customerId, the same field name I have mentioned here.
Now here there is a catch.
With the help of our custom methods, we are trying to change the data inside the database.
Previously we are only trying to read the data.
It is not going to change the data in any way, but whenever you are trying to update or delete with
the custom methods that you have written, we need to make sure we are mentioning two annotations on
top of these abstract methods.
These two annotations are @Transactional and the second annotation is @Modifying.
Modifying will tell to the spring data JPA framework that these method is going to modify the data.
So that's why please execute the query of this method inside a Transaction.
That's why we are mentioning Transactional annotation.
When my spring data JPA runs my query inside a Transaction and if there is some error happens at the
runtime, any partial change of data that is resulted due to the queries will be rolled back because
the entire transaction will be rolled back by the spring data JPA and we are in safe hands.
It should not be a scenario where like we deleted the account but not the customer.
So those kind of scenarios we need to make sure we are handling with the help of this transactional
and modifying.
And here you may have a question like we are also invoking these deleteById method inside the
CustumerRepository then why you are not mentioning
Transactional and Modifying for this method.
Please note that this method is from the framework.
Framework is going to take care of it.
But this method we have returned with our own hands since framework cannot identify that.
We need to let framework that this method is going to modify data and please run it inside a Transaction.
And if there is some error happen, please roll back the Transaction.
That's what we are trying to communicate with these two annotations.
Once the delete operation is completed, we are simply returning true post that I can go to the controller
class inside controller class
also, I'm going to create a new method.
So here I'm pasting the new method just to save some time.
So like you can see the annotation is @DeleteMapping.
We need to use delete() method only to delete the data and the API path that it is going to support is
/delete.
The method name is deleteAccountDetails().
It is going to accept mobile number and we are invoking the deleteAccount() method available inside the
service layer and we're accepting a boolean.
If the boolean is true, we are sending a ok response with the status 200 and the message has request to
process successfully.
But for some reason, if this boolean is false, we are sending these error saying that 500 is a code
and the message has an error occurred.
Please try again or contact dev team.
So with this we should be good.
Let me save this changes.
Do a build like you know the build will restart my application and all the data will be lost inside
the database.
But don't worry, we can quickly create the data.
I know this is very annoying step right now, but later on when we move to a proper MySQL database,
that is going to be super, super helpful.
So first I'm creating the new account.
I'm taking the same mobile number.
I'll validate if the account details are present by invoking this get method so the details are created.
That's why I'm getting the successful response.
Now I'll go to this deleteAccountDetails() and the path that we need to invoke is /api/delete
delete with the Http method as delete and we need to pass a query param mobile number with the
same mobile number value.
As soon as I click delete you can see I'm getting a successful response.
Now,
If we go and check the fetch API you will get not found error because the data is deleted successfully.
Now coming to the native scenario, I can try to invoke the delete API again.
You can see right now my delete API also throwing not found because there is no such data.
Hooray.
We completed all the four crud operations inside our Accounts
Microservice, I hope you are clear.
Take a break.
Take your favorite drink, coffee, whatever you want,
come back.
We are yet to discuss more standards like proper RuntimException handling auditing of the metadata
columns with the help of spring data JPA documenting the REST APIs.
So these three important topics we need to discuss.
I hope you are excited.
I'm also super excited.
I'm going to take a small break and catch you in the next lecture bye.