As of now, inside our accounts.
Microservice We have built four REST APIs supporting the Crud operations.
Like you can see there are four different API operations inside this lecture.
Let's try to handle the runtime exceptions that may happen inside our REST APIs at any time, at any
location.
As of now, if you go to the GlobalExceptionHandler inside this GlobalExceptionHandler, we are
only handling two exceptions, and these two exceptions are business exceptions are user defined exceptions.
So these are the two exceptions like ResourceNotFound and customer already exist.
Exception But what if there is some runtime exception happens inside your application?
You should be able to send a proper response to the client application that so-and-so issue occurred
so that they are aware that API invocation is failed for the same.
It's going to be super, super easy.
We just need to copy one of this method here and paste the same inside.
The GlobalExceptionHandler here instead of ResourceNotFoundException class, I'm going to mention
Exception.class inside Java,
we know Exception is a class that can represent all kind of exceptions, including checked and unchecked
exceptions.
With this, the method that I'm going to define right now is going to handle all kind of exceptions.
But here you may have a question like user not found exception is also a type of exception.
Only the way it is going to work is for Springboot framework is going to look for handler methods which
are with the exact exception details.
If there is no such handler exception, then the logic inside this exception handler is going to be
invoked.
Let me change this method name to handleGlobalException() and at the same time we need to change this
ResourceNotFoundException
to normal exception class.
And apart from that here I want to return an
ErrorResponseDto as an response.
And I want to send what is the path that they invoked?
And instead of NOT_FOUND, I want to send internal server error.
So this indicates that there is some runtime error happened.
And the same I'm going to mention here as well, post this internal server.
We should be good with whatever exception message that we receive from the spring boot framework along
with these LocalDateTime.now().
So with these changes now our application can handle the runtime exceptions and it can execute the logic
that we have written here if needed in real time applications.
You can enhance this method to trigger an email to operation or to make an entry into one of the table
where you are maintaining all the exception details for reporting purpose.
So the scenario can be anything based upon your business requirements.
So now we have this logic available.
The question right now is how to test a runtime exception.
That's going to be super, super easy.
Let's try to introduce a runtime exception intentionally inside my AccountsController.
As of now we have this AllArgsConstructor.
I'm going to delete this.
With that, there will be only default constructor for our class and with the default constructor the
autowiring will not happen.
And when no aut wiring happening then this
IAccountService is going to be null and I'm going to get
a null pointer exception in all my API operations.
So let me save this changes and do a build.
Once the build is completed, we can try to test one of the API,
maybe we can try to test create API itself.
So this is the API that I want to test.
So let me invoke with a proper request.
So I'm clicking on the Send button.
You can see I got a runtime exception saying that this is the API path, this is the error code which
is internal server error and the same we are getting here like 500 internal server, which is the Http
status.
Now coming to the error message, you can see we are getting actual runtime exception saying that that
so-and-so object is null because autowiring failed.
The same will happen for all kind of APIs.
Like you can see we we are getting the same here.
Let's do the same for update account and the same for delete account.
You can see the power of global exception.
So this is going to be super, super important.
And if someone want to test your spring boot knowledge and your rest API knowledge, they can simply
ask you how to implement global exception logic inside an application.
So please remember that we need to use this annotation like @ControllerAdvice and we need
to write a method and on top of this method we need to make sure we are mentioning this annotation
@ExceptioHandler post that you already know what we have to do inside this method.
The short answer is the combination of ControllerAdvice and ExceptionHandler is going to help you
to implement the global error logic inside all of your Controller methods.
I hope this is clear.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.