Inside this lecture,
let's try to enhance documentation related to our schema objects.
So using certain annotations, we can enhance this documentation further.
Just like how we made some changes inside the controller class and on top of the Java methods inside
controller class.
Very similarly, we need to visit these dto classes that we have.
Like first let me try to visit this CustomerDto. Here inside my CustomerDto.
Since I don't want to display this technical name, I can choose a different name which which is going
to be more business friendly.
So for the same, I'm going to use a annotation which is @Schema.
Using this annotation, we can invoke name and to this name I'm going to mention just simply Customer.
The same name is going to be displayed inside my swagger UI as well.
Now, coming to the description here, I can mention a description explaining about what these schema
is going to hold.
That's why I'm telling schema to hold customer and account information.
So once we define these details, we can also define field level information as well, like whatever
schema that we have mentioned here.
Very similarly, we can also define these kind of information at the field level.
For example, I can define schema annotation on top of my name field.
I don't want to overwrite this name.
I'm fine with whatever field name that I'm going to show.
By default, the field name is going to be displayed in the open API documentation.
So now I have to update the description.
What is this field about?
So that's why I'm going to mention a description which is Name of the customer.
So this field is going to hold the name of the customer.
And very similarly, I can also invoke example. Using example, I can provide some example data.
So here I'm just going to mention a name like Eazy Byte.
So the same example data is going to be displayed inside our open API documentation.
So let me define similar schema details for remaining fields that we have here.
So I'm just mentioning on top of email like the description is going to be email address of the customer
and this is an example email value.
And similarly for mobile number also I can describe.
So this is what I'm mentioning for mobile number like description is mobile number of the customer and
this is a sample mobile number value.
Now here on top of accounts, I'm going to mention schema information saying that this is the description
like accounts details of the customer.
And here I don't want to pass the example information because anyway, I'm going to provide more details
about this data inside this class itself.
So inside AccountsDto first, I need to make sure I'm mentioning similar information like schema here.
So let me take this value and paste it here.
And the name that I want to consider here is accounts, and this is going to hold the account information.
So let me update the same here.
Now as a next step, I'm going to provide schema details on top of the accountNumber field.
Like this is the description Account Number of Easy Bank Account and example is not a mandatory.
That's why in order to show that I'm not giving any example information for accountNumber, people
should be able to easily understand by seeing these rejects expression.
So now coming to the account type, I'm going to mention the schema details.
So here I'm just mentioning schema details, saying that description Account Type of Easy Bank Account
and example is savings.
So let me do the same for branch address as well.
Here also, I'm not going to do any example data, I'm giving only description information.
So it is up to us whether we want to give example information or not.
Now, similarly, we need to go to the response that we have.
Like let me go to ResponseDto on top of this ResponsDto we need to invoke an annotation which is
schema, and to this annotation we need to invoke name.
And the name that I want to have here is response and post that we can also invoke description inside
the description.
I'm just mentioning schema to hold successful response information.
Now let me do the same for statusCode and statusMessage as well.
So I'm just mentioning schema description as statusCode in the response and example as 200.
So now for status message also I'm mentioning like description is status message in the response and
example is request to process successfully. As a next step
let's go to the ErrorResponseDto and here I'm going to mention @Schema annotation post
that I'm going to mention
what is the name of this DTO.
The name I just wanted to keep it as ErrorResponse.
Now post that, I can also pass the description and under this description I'm going to mention schema
to hold ErrorResponse information. As next step,
we can also mention schema details on top of this path.
Very similarly, we can mention for error code as well.
So for error code I'm just mentioning error code representing the error happened.
And similarly I'm going to mention for error message as well.
So here I'm not mentioning
any example values because these errors can keep change based upon the scenario.
But if you have such requirements, you can always mention example details as well.
So with this, all the dto are also well documented with the help of these Openapi specification
annotations which is @Schema.
So let me save these changes.
Do a build.
Once the build is completed, we can go to the swagger UI and try to understand how this information is
being reflected inside the UI.
As of now you can see the Dataverse has technical names, so let me try to refresh this page and you'll
be able to see that these schemas right now has a meaningful business name like accounts and this is
the overall information about the schema object.
And similarly, you can go to the field and there will be a description.
And for accounts you can see there is an example value also.
Very similarly, if you go to the Customer, there is a name and this is the example value and this
is a summary of the each field.
Now if you go and check any of the APIs, you can see the schema right now has example values populated.
Like this is a name, this is the email, this is a mobile number.
So this is looking good except this account number and branch address.
So let me try to mention that we'll go to AccountsDto and inside AccountsDto.
I'm just going to mention example and this example
I'm going to mention a ten digit account number.
Similarly, I'll mention a example value saying that 123NewYork.
So let me save this changes.
Do a build.
I'm refreshing this page this time
you can see the same examples
Information are being considered here.
This way we enhanced our documentation to a great extent and right now everything is looking very professional
inside our swagger UI.
And here there is a small bug as of now you can see and a schemas there is one dto missing which is
ErrorResponse.
Why this information is missing is we are going to throw this ErrorResponseDto only from our
GlobalExceptionLogic.
So inside our GlobalExceptionLogic, whenever an exception occurs here we are trying to populate this
ErrorResponseDto with an 500 status.
So since my open API documentation cannot scan these GlobalExceptionHandlerLogic automatically,
I need to provide that information inside my ApiResponse.
So let's try to understand how to mention this information. For the same,
what we can do is I'm going to show you for one of the API operations how to mention a schema object
inside your ApiResponse.
So after this description, I'm going to invoke content to this content.
I'm going to mention an annotation content, and inside this annotation I'm going to invoke schema parameter.
And to this schema parameter, I'm going to pass the schema annotation and inside this schema annotation
I'm going to mention implementation.
And what is the implementation class?
The implementation class is ErrorResponsDto.class.
This I'm telling to my spring dog for these update operation, there is a good chance a 500 error can
happen.
Whenever that 500 error happened.
I'm going to send the ErrorResponse by following the schema defined inside this ErrorResponseDto.
So let me save this changes.
Do a build.
Once the build is completed, we should be able to validate this inside our swagger UI.
So here, inside my swagger UI right now you can see there is an ErrorResponseDto appearing.
If I go to my update operation under this 500 you'll be able to see a schema with API path error code
and ErrorMessage and ErrorTime.
So this way we can define an schema object also for your ApiResponse with the help of these annotations
@Content and @Schema.
As of now inside our microservices we are sending these 500 event in the scenario of updation failed
or deletion failed.
So if it is confusion to your clients, you can choose some other error code or error response code
so that you can define multiple response codes so it's up to you based upon your requirements.
You can play with this schema definition.
With this, we enhanced our microservices with one of the standards which is documenting the REST APIs.
I hope this is clear.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.