In the previous lecture we discussed that the same error Code 500 is being used both for RuntimeException
like inside the GlobalExceptionHandler.
Whenever a RuntimeException happens, we are throwing an internal server error with the status code
500.
And very similarly, we also use the same 500 error code both in update operation and delete operation
whenever the update or delete operation fail.
So this gives some confusion to the client.
I said in the previous lecture you can change it based upon your requirements, but I thought about
it and decided to correct it inside this small lecture because many students, they refer to my code
and I don't want to create any confusion to them.
That's why I have quickly fixed the issue behind the scenes
let me show you what I have done inside the GlobalExceptionHandler.
I have not changed anything, but if you go to the controller class inside the update operation, whenever
this boolean is false, I am using a new HttpStatus code which is 417.
This indicates this exception failed.
So I thought like this error code, I can use the same status code I am also sending as part of ResponseDto
I have created a constant status 417 and there is also a message I have created for the update operation
which tells update operation failed.
Please try again or contact dev team. And the same for delete operation
I have created a separate message. To go to the delete operation as well.
If the boolean is false, I'm sending the same 41 status with the same exception
failed HttpStatus with a message delete operation failed.
Please try again or contact dev team. With this we no more need the status 500 and message 500 constants.
I'm going to comment them in case if you want to refer them for some other reason.
So let me save this changes.
And apart from these changes, if you go and check right now all the ApiResponses for my four APIs,
you'll be seeing that for each operation
I'm passing these ApiResponse with the schema as ErrorResponseDto.
because any API can have RuntimeException.
That's why with the response code 500 with this description, I have mentioned that I'm going to send
this content with the schema of ErrorResponseDto.
So the same 500 related ApiResponse I have mentioned for all the APIs.
Similarly for the fetch operation, I have mentioned the RuntimeException related ApiResponse.
Now coming to the update operation. update operation is going to have one more extra ApiResponse with
the response code 417 and description as exception failed.
So update operation is going to have three different API response 204, one seven and 500.
And very similarly, the delete operation
also, we are going to have three different responses.
Now if I try to look at them in the UI, everything is going to be super, super cool.
Like you can see for the update operation 200, 417 indicates there is an exception fail and 500,
this is the object response that you are going to get.
So this looks everything good, but you can see for 204 and 417, the status code is showing as 200.
The reason is inside the ResponseDto
we have mentioned the example values as 200 and request process successfully.
So this gives some confusion to the clients.
Like why in the case of 417, I'm going to receive the status code as 200.
So that's why mentioning examples is not always a good advantage.
Sometimes you don't want to mention the examples because it will create more confusion.
For that reason,
let me go and remove these example value inside the ResponseDto.
So here I'm just removing these example as 200 and very similarly, I'm going to remove these here
as well.
So with this, let me do a build.
Now, if I try to refresh this page, you can see the status code is going to be String status message
is going to be String the same for 417.
So this is going to appear in all the API's like for the response codes.
So each API is going to have at least two response formats, one for success scenario and the other
one for RuntimeException scenario.
And 417 is going to be present for both update and delete operation.
Now ErrorResponseDto is also appearing inside the schemas and with this I believe everything is looking
perfect
now.
I hope you understand the changes that I have done.
Please take your time, digest this information and I'll be catching you in the next lecture bye.