Inside this lecture, let me try to set up Discovery Server with the help of these Kubernetes manifest
file.
So here you may have a question like why we are not using helm chat.
There are two reasons on why I'm not using helm chat here.
The very first one is Discovery Server is a one time setup inside your Kubernetes cluster.
You don't have to do multiple changes every time.
With that reason, manually running these manifest files should be fine because this is only one time
activity.
And the second reason is as of now there is no helm chat developed by the helm chat community, including
Bitnami for these discovery server.
So if we try to integrate these manifest file into our easybank helm chat, then it is going to need
a lot of efforts which I felt like it is not worth since this is only going to be one time activity
to run this and fine running the manifest file manually.
I hope you are also fine with that.
So to install the discovery server from the terminal, we need to run the command which is cubectl
followed by -f.
And what is the file name.
The file name is kubernetes-discoveryserver.yaml.
So let me try to execute this command and this is going to create a service service account, role binding
role and deployment.
I can go to the Kubernetes dashboard and make sure that Discovery server is started successfully.
Inside my dashboard,
I will go to the pods and here I will open the logs just to confirm that my discovery server is started.
Like you can see here, my discovery server started successfully in 20s and this is a spring boot application.
So how do we know that,
if you see here we have logs from the spring confirming that this is a spring boot application.
With this, we successfully set up that Discovery server inside our Kubernetes cluster.
As a next step, we need to make some code changes inside our microservices to remove the Eureka related
changes on top of that, we should also make some changes inside our microservices to leverage the discovery
server exposed by the Kubernetes.
So to get started around those changes, I'm going to copy all the microservice code that we have under
the Section 14 because Section 14 has the latest and greatest microservices code changes.
So here, let me select accounts cards, config server, gateway server loans message.
We don't have to copy the Eureka Server because we're trying to get rid of Eureka Server and I'm also
not going to copy the Docker compose.
The reason is we are going to deploy all our microservices into Kubernetes cluster and Docker compose
files is of no use right now. So let me copy all these folders and post that
I will go to the section_17 and here I'm going to paste all these microservices.
After pasting these microservices, I'm also going to paste the helm folder present inside the section_16.
.
So let me copy this helm folder and paste it inside the section 17.
In the coming lectures we are going to make some changes inside our helm charts also because we need
to remove the details related to the Eureka Server inside our helm charts.
So with this we have the section_17 related folder ready.
As a next step, I can open this folder inside my IntelliJ idea.
Here I'm going to click on this open post that I will go to storage, workspaces, microservices section_17 and
I'm going to click on this open button post that I'm going to click on this load button.
And after my microservices are loaded as Maven projects, I'm going to do a build and it will ask me
to enable the annotation processing.
So let me enable that.
So now we are good to get started with these changes, so let's try to do the same from the next lecture,
but please make sure you are Discovery Server is up and running inside your Kubernetes cluster.
So as of now my deployment pods replica set, everything is showing in a green color.
This indicates that my discovery server is working without any issues inside my Kubernetes cluster.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.