Inside this lecture,
let's try to make all the required changes inside our microservices to get rid of Eureka Server and
use that Discovery server available inside the Kubernetes cluster. For the same first, I'll get started
with the accounts microservice.
Inside this, I'll go to the pom.xml and here first I'll try to update that tag name.
So I'll change this to s17 because right now we are into the section_17.Post that I will look for Eureka
dependency.
So as of now you can see we are using that dependency with the name Spring Cloud starter Netflix Eureka
Client.
So instead of this dependency, I'm going to use a dependency with the name Spring cloud starter Kubernetes
hyphen discovery client.
So let me save this changes and do a maven refresh.
Once that is completed, I'll try to do a build.
As soon as I try to do a build, I'm getting an error inside my CustomerController.
Seems whenever I deleted the Eureka client related dependency, it is internally is also going to delete
the interrelated dependencies.
That's why I'm getting these https related error.
So let me remove this.
And with that my spring boot will try to use one of the https available at this package which is
org.apache.hc.core5.http.HttpStatus.
So let me try to do a build again to make sure there are no compilation errors.
So now I don't have any compilation errors.
I can close this now
I'll go to the spring boot main class inside my accounts microservice.
So here on top of these AccountsApplication class we need to mention an annotation which is
@EnableDiscoveryClient.
So this is the annotation that I have mentioned just now.
Please make sure you also mention the same.
So let me save this and close this file.
Now I'll go to the application.yml file because inside the application.yml we have defined
a lot many configurations related to the Eureka.
First, let me try to delete all the eureka related configurations.
So here I'll search for Eureka and these are all the properties related to Eureka.
So let me select all of them and delete them. And post that,
now we need to add a property or configuration related to the Discovery server of Kubernetes.
So this property we need to mention under the spring.cloud.
So let me go to the top and here I have the cloud element and this cloud, I'm going to mention a new
property which is spring.cloud.kubernetes.discovery.all-namespaces as true.
So what is the purpose of this property?
As of now, we are deploying all our microservices into that default namespace of Kubernetes.
But sometimes some projects they may deploy different, different applications in different, different
namespaces.
So in such scenarios, to make sure that our application is able to discover the services present inside
other namespaces as well, we need to make sure we are mentioning these all namespaces as true.
I hope you are clear with this property.
Now as a next step, let me go to the location where we are using feign client to connect with the other
microservices inside my accounts microservice.
Under the service package, we can open the folder which is client.
So under this client package itself, we have the interfaces with the name CardFeignClient and
LoansFeignClient.
First let me open the CardsFeignClient.
So whatever configurations we have defined here, they will work perfectly with the Eureka Server because
inside the Eureka Server, all my applications are going to be registered with the application name
as cards.
Using the same application name my accounts
microservice can fetch the details of all the instances of cards microservice from the Eureka server.
We also provided the Eureka server connection details inside the application.yml so there is a clear integration
between your accounts microservice and Eureka Server and using the same integration, it is going to
use this name which we have defined here, which is cards to get the details of cards, microservice
instances.
But in the scenario of Discovery server, we are not providing any integration details between our accounts,
microservice and Discovery Server.
Nowhere
I have mentioned that Discovery server details, so that's why my feign clients cannot really understand
what is the service name or the host name or the dns name or the port number where it has to forward
the request.
So to resolve this issue, we need to provide details with the parameter which is URL.
So inside the annotation of  Feign client, apart from the name as cards, we should also mention what is the
url at which my cards microservice is available.
So what is the name that we have given for the cards
microservice service.
It is the cards
only.
So using this service name the communication between accounts microservice and cards
microservice is going to happen within the Kubernetes cluster and where all my cards microservice containers
are going to be available at the Port 9000.
So this is the only detail that we need to provide to the Feign client.
And here the Feign client is not going to perform any load balancing.
It is simply going to forward the request to this URL inside the Kubernetes cluster.
If the same is happening outside the Kubernetes cluster, then it is not going to work because outside
of your Kubernetes cluster there is no hostname or dns name with the name cards.
So that's why whenever you are trying to do some local testing without Kubernetes cluster, try to give
your localhost URL.
So now very similarly, let me try to mention the same inside the LoansFeignClient as well.
So here also I'm going to mention the same URL.
Here the service name is going to be loans and the port number is going to be 8090.
I hope you are clear with these changes.
So let me close all these accounts
microservice related files.
We should be good from accounts microservice perspective.
So as a next step, I'll go to the cards and here also first I'll open the pom.xml In the place of Eureka,
we are going to add a new dependency with the name Spring Cloud starter Kubernetes Discovery client.
After this, I'm going to update the tag name from s14 to s17.
So let me load the Maven changes.
Once this is complete, I'm going to do a build. As a next step,
I'll go to the cards Microservice main class.
So here I'll open the CardsApplication.
On top of this we need to mention an annotation which is @EnableDiscoveryClient.
Next I'll go to the application.yml file present inside the accounts microservice and here I will
look for Eureka and I will delete all these properties.
Post that I will search for cloud and here I don't have any cloud related properties.
So what I can do is just after this spring I can create a new element with the name cloud.
So let me create the same here.
So just under the config, I'm going to create cloud.
Now under this cloud we are going to define a property related to the Kubernetes Discovery server.
The property is same as like we discussed inside the accounts
microservice. Like Kubernetes Discovery all namespace as true.
So with this we should be good with all the changes inside the cards
microservice. I don't have to make any fin client related changes because my cards microservice does
not have any fin client related business logic.
So let me close all these files and I'll go to the loans microservice to make the similar changes.
First I'll go to the application.yml and just after this config I'm going to paste the same property
which is cloud.kubernetes.discovery.allnamespace as true.
Next I'll go to the pom.xml.
Inside the pom.xml I will look for Eureka and I will remove this dependency in the same place,
I'm going to add a new dependency which is spring cloud starter kubernetes discovery client.
Next, let me update the tag name from s14 to s17 and load the Maven changes. As a next step,
I'll go to the main class inside the loans microservice.
Here, I'm going to mention an annotation which is @EnableDiscoveryClient.
So with this we should be good with all the changes inside the loans
microservice. As a next step, let me go to the config server.
Inside the config server, we are nowhere connecting with the Eureka server. So there is no need of any
changes except the updating the tag name to the s17.
Just to be consistent, I'm trying to update the tag name to s17 and load the maven changes,
do a build.
Very similar changes we have to do inside the message microservice as well.
The message microservice also does not have any integration with the Eureka server.
We should be good if we just update the tag name from s14 to s17.
So now if you see, we have done all the required changes in all the microservices except the Gateway
server.
So let's try to continue this discussion and make the changes inside the Gateway server as well in the
next lecture.
Thank you.
Bye.