Now, inside this lecture, let's make the changes related to Kubernetes Discovery Server inside the
Gateway Server project as well.
So first, let me open the pom.xml and search for Eureka in the place of Eureka client dependency.
And I'm going to add a new dependency, which is spring cloud starter kubernetes discovery client and
post that I will search for the tag, which is s14.
And here I'm going to update these to s17 tag.
So let me load the Maven changes and do a build.
Once the build is completed, I can go to the Gateway Server main class, which is GatewayserverApplication.
So here I need to mention an annotation which is @EnableDiscoveryClient.
After making the changes inside the same class,
if you try to scroll down as of now, you can see the routing configurations that we have done here
is going to have a uri configuration, which is lb://ACCOUNTS and lb://LOANS  and similarly ld://CARDS.
So what is this
lb indicates, lb indicates load balancer.
So with this we are telling to the Gateway server, please leverage the spring cloud load balancer and
do the load balancing at the Gateway server itself.
But we don't want that to happen because we are no more using the Eureka.
So to communicate to the gateway server to not perform any client side load balancing, we need to update
these uri details with the actual URL details of your individual microservice.
So for the accounts the is going to be accounts 8080.
Here also, the beauty is we are not hardcoding the hostname or domain name as long as if you start your
accounts microservice with the service name as accounts, then your gateway server, your thin clients
integration should work without any issues.
So now very similarly, let me try to mention the same under the loans as well.
For the loans
the port is going to be 8090.
So let me update the same.
And the host name is going to be loans.
After this, I'll go to the cards.
And here also I will delete the cards related configurations and I will mention the service name as
cards followed by port number.
The port number is going to be 9000.
So with these changes, we should be good from these Gateway server application class.
As a next step, let me go to the application.yml file and here first we need to delete the properties
related to the Eureka server.
So here we have mentioned these discovery locator enabled and lowercase service ID as true.
So these are the properties related to Eureka server
let me delete them.
Post deleting the Eureka specific properties just at the same location where I have Gateway.
Very similarly, I'm going to define a new property with the value as spring.cloud.kubernetes.
discovery.enabled as true and at the same time discovery.allnamespace as true.
So with this discovery.enabled as true, we are telling to the gateway server,
please leverage the discovery server available inside the cluster to forward the request to the other
microservices like accounts, cards and loans.
So these are an extra property that we need to define inside Gateway server because our gateway server
is an edge server and it is going to responsible to handle all the incoming traffic.
If you try to define only this property and try to start your gateway server, you are going to get
an error.
Because when I'm trying to test these changes, I got an error.
So to overcome that error, we need to define one more property under the spring.cloud and this
property is spring.cloud.discovery.client.health indicator enabled as false.
So by default there is an health indicator bean is going to be created internally.
And whenever this is happening behind the scenes, my library, which we have added related to the discovery
client of Kubernetes, is going to create an problem because it is not going to create a bean that is
required for this library.
So I looked into the official GitHub issues for this project and there is an issue also raised inside
the GitHub repo and the spring cloud
kubernetes team also confirmed. For now to overcome that error, we should define these property, which
is discovery.client.health indicator enabled as false.
So in future when this issue is resolved, then we can remove this property.
So by the time you are looking at this course, if this property is not available inside the GitHub
repo, then that is an indication that this issue is resolved.
Otherwise we should continue to define this property.
So these are the required changes inside my gateway server.
As a next step, I'm going to generate the Docker images for all the microservices with the
tag name as s17.
So I'm going to do that behind the scenes.
By the time I come to the next lecture, I will generate all the Docker images of s17.
And at the same time I'm also going to set up the Kubernetes cluster with all the required components
like Kafka, Keycloak, Grafana, Prometheus.
Since you already familiar with that process, I'm not going to repeat that again.
I will simply do that setup behind the scenes.
But in front of you, I will try to update the helm charts of Easy Bank with the latest tag name, which
is s17 and post that using the same helm chart,
I'm going to set up all our microservices into the Kubernetes cluster.
I hope you are fine with this approach.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.