Behind the scenes
I have generated that docker images of all the microservices with the changes related to the section17
.
That's why you are able to see the images with the tag name s17 inside my Docker desktop.
Apart from generating the Docker images, I also installed Keycloak, Kafka, Grafana related components,
prometheus inside my Kubernetes cluster.
As a next step, we need to update the helm charts of Easy Bank and post that we can deploy our own
microservices into the Kubernetes cluster based upon the latest helm charts.
So to update the helm charts inside the section17, we have a folder with the name Helm.
Let me open that.
Here we can go to the easy bank services.
First, let me delete the folder related to the Eureka server. And post that I need to open the values.yaml
of all the microservices and update that tag name from s14 to s17.
And apart from updating this image tag name for accounts microservice, I'm going to create two replicas
since I want to show you the demo of load balancing at the server side, I'm going to mention the replica
count as two inside this account service related helm chart.
Let me update the tag details inside other microservices as well.
So here inside cards, I'm trying to update the tag name from s14 to s17.
Now let me update for config server inside my config server
also, I'm updating.
Next I will update for gateway server.
Here I'm trying to update the tag name from s14 to s17.
Next, I'll go to the loans, inside loans
also, I'll open the values.yml and update the tag name to s17.
Let me do the same for last microservice, which is message microservice.
So here I'm going to update the tag name. As a next step,
I'm going to open the environments folder here under the dev env.
I'm going to open the chart.yaml. Inside the chart.yaml,
we have defined all the dependent chart details. Inside this dependencies list,
we need to delete the dependency related to the Eureka server.
So let me do the same for prod env as well .
Here also I'm going to look for Eureka server related helm chart and delete the same.
I'm going to do the same change inside the qa env as well by opening the chart.yaml and post that I
will delete these Eureka server.
So once we have done these changes we need to recompile our environment specific helm chart so that
all the latest values that we have defined will be compiled and copied into the charts folder of our
environment helm charts.
So for the same inside my terminal, I'm going to navigate into the helm folder post that I will go
into environments inside environment,
first I will try to open the dev env.
Here I'm going to run the command which is helm dependencies build. With this
the compilation should happen, but like I said before, sometimes the chart.log will create some issues
because we deleted some dependencies inside the chart.yaml.
So to fix this issue we need to delete the chart.log file inside the folder.
So here we can delete this chart.log.
Let me do the same for other folders also.
Finally I'll delete inside the qa - env as well.
Now let me try to run this helm dependencies build.
So this time the compilation is going to be successful.
Post that I will navigate into the prod env and run the same command which is helm dependencies
build as a next step,
navigate back to the parent folder.
After that I'm going to navigate into the qa -env.
So here I'm going to execute the helm dependencies, build the compilation is going to be successful.
Now let me go back to the environments folder as a next step,
we can try to install all our microservices with the help of helm install command.
The command is going to be helm install,
what is the release name that we want to give.
The release name that I will give is easybank and what is the chart name that we are going to consider.
Here
let me try to use the prod env chart. For the same,
I need to mention the folder where my helm chart is available.
So I'm trying to execute this command and the installation is going to start behind the scenes.
Let's go to the Kubernetes dashboard and confirm the same inside my Kubernetes dashboard
I'll go to the pods for accounts
you should be able to see two parts if I search for accounts,
so there are two parts because we have defined the replica count as two.
So first let me check the logs of config server to make sure that my config server started successfully
post that only my remaining microservices are going to start.
So this is going to take few minutes time because inside my local system we have installed too many
components and due to that my laptop is going
to perform very slowly.
So let me wait for these deployments to complete behind the scenes post that we can continue the discussion.
Behind the scenes,
I waited for more than five minutes, but unfortunately my gateway server loans, cards and accounts
microservice, they are not able to start with an error saying that we didn't provide the URL details
of discovery server.
If you see this error, it is clearly highlighting that we missed mentioning this property using which
we need to provide a valid URL of discovery server.
So without mentioning that discovery server URL, how my gateway server accounts, loans and cards will
know.
That's why to fix this issue we need to define this property. Inside the blog
also, they have clearly highlighted this like whoever is using these dependency, they need to make
sure they are setting this property by providing the URL of the Discovery server deployed on Kubernetes.
But it is my bad that I missed mentioning these changes inside the helm chart.
So let's go to the helm chart and try to update the same so that we can try to redeploy our applications
one more time.
But before that, let me run the command of Helm Uninstall for the Easy Bank release.
So here I'm trying to run the helm uninstall command, so this will uninstall all my microservices.
As a next step, I'll go to the helm chart inside the helm chart,
first, I need to go to the easybank-common Helm chart and here I'm going to open the config map template
because we are going to create a new property using which we are going to provide the discovery server
URL.
So here in the place of Eureka client service URL default zone, I'm going to create a new property
and this property is going to be SPRING.CLOUD.KUBERNETES.DISCOVERY.DISCOVERY-SERVER-URL.
The variable name
also, I will change from eurekaServerURL to discoveryServerURL.
So let me change this to discovery.
So these are one of the change that we have to do.
The next change that we need to do is, inside the deployment template files
we need to write a if condition based upon the Boolean value.
We need to set this property. For the same,
let me open the deployment.yaml.
Here we can look for Eureka server URL if condition in the place of Eureka enabled, I will mention boolean
value as discovery enabled.
Post that I'm going to change the environment variable name,
similarly under the key as well
I'm going to change.
So with this we should be good from the deployment.yaml file perspective.
As a next step, I need to go to the easybank services and here I'm going to open the accounts microservice
helm chart.
So let me open the values.yaml and here I will change the variable name Eureka enabled with discovery
enabled.
So the very similar change I have to do inside the values.yaml of all the remaining microservices.
So let me open the cards
microservice values.yaml.
And here also I'm going to change this variable name.
Let me do the same for config server inside config server values.yaml
also I'm trying to change.
So similarly I'm going to change for the remaining microservices as well.
Let me change this time for Gateway server.
So here we have Eureka enabled.
I have changed that to discovery enabled.
As a next step, I'll go to loans microservice values.yaml and look for Eureka enabled and change that
let me do the same for message microservice.
So in this file also I'm going to change the variable name.
So as a next step we can go to the environment folders inside the environments folder
first, I'll open the values.yaml.
So inside these values.yaml only we are trying to define a variable name which is Eureka server URL.
We need to replace this Eureka server URL with discovery server URL.
So let me update this with Discovery once we corrected the variable name, we should also correct the
URL details.
So the URL of Discovery server is going to be spring cloud kubernetes discovery server and the port
is 80.
So how do I know this service name?
If you go and check the Kubernetes manifest file that we have used to deploy the Discovery server here
inside this file, under the service type, we have mentioned the name as spring-cloud-kubernetes-discoveryserver
.
So the same name we have to give inside the values.yaml.
So I need to make the similar change inside other environments as well.
So let me copy this and go for the prod env and open the values.yaml and I'm going to replace this Eureka
server URL with the discovery server URL.
Now as a next step, let me do the same change for qa env as well.
So here we need to open the values.yaml and replace this eurekaServerURL with the discoveryServerURL
.
So now we have made all the
required changes.
Let me recompile all the helm charts.
So for the same first I'll go back to the helm folder here
first, I'll go inside the easybank-services folder and navigate into the accounts helm chart.
Now I'm going to run the helm dependencies build so the dependencies are recompiled.
So let me do the same for other helm charts as well
very quickly
behind the scenes.
Behind the scenes I have recompiled all the helm charts, including the environment helm charts like
dev env prod env and QA env.
So before I try to install all my microservices into the Kubernetes cluster, let me make sure if my
helm charts are properly compiled or not by using the helm template command.
So I'll try to run the helm template command from the prod env folder.
So I'm getting a successful response.
That means there are no compilation issues.
We can also quickly validate for one of the microservice like loans for these
you can see we are injecting a environment variable related to the discovery server URL.
So this confirms all our changes are recompiled properly.
As a next step, I will navigate back to the parent folder and here I'm going to run the helm install
command by providing a release name as easybank followed by prod env, which is my helm chart.
So let me execute this.
So this is going to start my installation of my microservices.
By the time I come to the next lecture, all my microservices are going to get started successfully.
I hope you are clear with all the changes that we have done in this lecture.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.