We discussed that there are three pillars for observability and monitoring, and these three pillars
are logging metrics and traces.
So to implement these concepts inside our microservice network, we need to make sure we are generating
all these data so that using them we can try to understand the internal state of our microservices and
monitor them.
So first let's try to implement log aggregation inside our microservices.
What are these logs?
Logs are discrete records of events that happens inside any software application over time.
Usually logs contain a timestamp that indicates when the event happened, as well as the information
about the event and its context.
The information present inside the logs can be used to answer the questions like what happened at a
particular time, which thread was processing the event or which user a tenant was in the context.
We all know that logs are the essential tools for troubleshooting and debugging tasks.
They can be used to reconstruct the scenario.
What happened at a specific point of time in a single application instance.
Logs are typically categorized according to the types of severity such as trace, debug info, warn
and error.
This will allow us to log only the most severe events in the production.
We should not also do the over logging inside our application or microservices because that will have
some performance implications.
We should only log the severe events like there is an exception happened or there is an error happened
inside production.
Off course, inside the testing environment and development environment, we can try to log as much as
information with the help of severity like debug and info.
If you are not clear about how to implement logging inside any spring boot application with the help
of these severities, please check my course on spring Spring boot.
There is a separate section inside that course where I talked about how to perform logging inside the
spring boot applications, how to activate a specific severity based upon the environment.
So all such best practices I have discussed inside the spring course.
So basically what I'm trying to say here is, we can also attach severity to a particular log statement the purpose
of the severities is this will allow us to log only the most severe events in production and if needed,
we can activate or deactivate a particular type based upon the environment where you are trying to run
your application.
So whenever we try to perform logging inside monolithic application, since all the code is in a single
codebase, all the logs that are generated from your code will be present inside a single location or
inside a single server.
This makes very easy for the developers to search the logs and to troubleshoot the problems because
you have all your logs in a single folder location.
Whereas with microservices logging is going to be complex.
This is because each service has its own logs.
With that, the developer has to check the logs from the multiple containers which are present in multiple
locations to understand or to debug an issue.
So to address these challenge inside Microservice Network, the best practice is to follow the centralized
logging.
So what is centralized logging?
With the help of centralized logging, we can collect the logs from all the services and store them
in a single location.
This makes developer life easy to find and troubleshoot problems because the developer has to look in
a one place only. Without log aggregation
the developer will be forced to search the logs information in hundreds of microservices that you have
deployed inside your organization.
Do you think it is a feasible option?
Off course not.
That's why we need to perform log aggregation.
So here you may have a question like how to perform this log aggregation.
Do I need to write some logic inside my microservices
as a developer, that is one of the most basic approach.
Like you can write some logic to save or to stream your container logs into a centralized location.
But this approach where the developer is responsible to handle the logic of log aggregation has many
disadvantages because log aggregation is not related to the business logic.
If you force your developers to worry about the log aggregation also, then you are wasting their time
on unnecessary things like log aggregation.
We as a developer or we as intelligent humans, we should always focus on the client problems or the
business logic.
That's why we are going to look for an option which is going to perform the log aggregation without
making any changes inside our microservices.
There are such beautiful products.
Let's try to explore them from the next lecture.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.