In the previous lecture, I was telling you that we should not force the developers to implement all
the observability and monitoring logic.
Instead, we should leverage the tools or the best practices that will help us to implement observability
and monitoring with less efforts from the developer. For the same,
throughout this course, I'm going to use the tools at the plugins available inside the Grafana.
So what is Grafana?
Grafana is a company which is building a lot of tools and plugins to implement observability monitoring
inside any kind of applications.
It's not only about microservices, even for other type of applications like web applications, IoT
applications for any kind of applications, with the help of the tools provided by the Grafana, we
can implement observable and monitoring.
The reason why I choose the Grafana to implement observability and monitoring is, it provides open source
tools for various scenarios.
For example, if you want to implement log aggregating system, then go for the tool Grafana Loki.
Similarly, if you are looking around metrics, then you can integrate Prometheus with Grafana and
build some dashboards alerts very easily.
And for tracing information you can leverage Grafana tempo.
This way there are many tools available inside the Grafana for various kind of scenarios and it has
very good integration with other standards like Opentelemetry, Prometheus.
We are going to discuss in detail about these tools.
Grafana itself is a very fascinating subject and many operations are platform engineers.
It is a mandatory skill for them to learn everything about Grafana.
But inside this course I'm going to teach you some basics and how to use grafana,
how to build observability and monitoring
with the help of Grafana tools in the real projects.
It is not the developer responsibility to implement observability and monitoring.
The developer has to work with the operations team or platform team and implement the same.
But I'm trying to teach about this inside this course so that whenever you have challenges or problems
related to observability and monitoring inside your projects and organizations, you should be able
to give some directions to your operations team or platform team.
Or you can also build some demo applications with the help of all the concepts that we are going to
discuss.
And with that, you will become a super, super hero or a super developer inside your project.
When you climb yourself as a microservice developer, you need to aware about all these concepts, otherwise
it is going to be super, super tough to clear the any interviews around microservices.
Any interviewer can ask you how observability and monitoring is implemented inside your microservices.
If you don't know these concepts and if you scratch your head inside the interview by thinking that
as a developer, business logic is only my responsibility, then you will never be able to clear any
microservice interview.
I hope you are clear about quick introduction about the Grafana.
Now let's try to understand how to implement log aggregation or centralized logging with the help of
Grafana.
When we decide to manage logs with the help of Grafana, we need to use other tools available inside
Grafana ecosystem. Over all Grafana is a large ecosystem under which we have many tools based upon our scenario
or problem.
We need to choose these tools and integrate with the grafana.
So here to manage the logs, we need to use Grafana Loki and prompt.
Let's try to understand what are these like we discussed first, Grafana is a open source analytical
and interactive visualization web application.
This Grafana provides various features like we can build charts, graphs, alerts for our web applications
or microservices by connecting with the other supporting tools like Loki and Promptail, we can easily
install this grafana and its tools with the help of Docker or Docker
compose or kubernetes . Over all Grafana is a popular tool for visualizing metrics, logs and traces from variety
of sources.
It is being used by many organizations of all types right from startup to the enterprise organizations.
Majority of the projects they are using Grafana because it is open source.
So this is a quick introduction about Grafana.
Now let's talk about Loki and promptail.
Grafana Loki is a horizontally scalable, highly available log aggregation system.
It is designed to store any amount of logs from your microservices and applications.
So Loki is a centralized location where you can store all your microservices logs.
But with Grafana, Loki alone, we can't implement the log aggregation.
We need to have promptail, which is a lightweight log agents that will run inside your same network where
your containers are running.
So this prompt tale it is going to
read all the logs that are getting generated from your containers, the same it will collect and send
to the Grafana Loki.
Grafana, Loki will store all these logs with the help of Grafana
we can easily see the logs inside an application together Grafana, Loki and promptly provides a powerful
logging solution that can help you to understand and troubleshoot your applications.
I know here you may have questions.
Let's try to understand more detail about these Grafana, Loki and prompt.
If you see here, I have my microservices running inside their containers.
As a developer, I'm not doing anything to send my logs to the promptail or Loki or Grafana.
The promptail, which is a agent running inside the same network of your microservice containers.
It is going to fetch and collect all the logs from the containers and forward them to the Loki.
Loki is a storage system where it can store all the logs, since it is a centralized location.
In other words, we can also call it as log aggregation system.
So Loki is like a folder location where we can store all our logs from all the containers.
But do you think it is a good idea for the developers to go into these folder location and search for
the logs manually by opening all the logs?
Off course not.
That's why by integrating this Loki with the Grafana, we we can visualize all the logs inside an application.
Apart from visualization, we can also query and search logs based upon our own criteria.
When you see all this in demo, you are going to super, super like the tools of Grafana.
But for now I'm assuming that you are clear about what is the role of Grafana, Loki and prompt how to
achieve this.
Don't worry, I'm going to talk about them in detail in the coming lectures.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.