Inside this lecture, let's try to implement open telemetry related changes inside our microservices.
Before I try to implement these changes.
First, let me stop all my running containers.
So here I'm going to run the command, which is docker
compose down. With this
all my running containers will be stopped.
As a next step, I'll go to the pom.xml present inside the accounts microservice.
So let me open this pom.xml. Here I need to add that dependency related to the Opentelemetry.
When I add this dependency inside my pom.xml, the same jar will be available inside the classpath of
my application.
Or in other words, the same jar is going to be packaged and available inside the Docker image so that
we can use the same whenever we are trying to generate a Docker container from the Docker image.
Here first I need to mention what is a Opentelemetry version that we are trying to use.
As of today, it is 1.27.0.
In future, if you have an updated version, like I said, I'm going to update all the code inside the
GitHub repo every quarter.
That's why please always check the GitHub repo, whatever I have mentioned inside the GitHub repo,
the same version you can also use inside your pom.xml.
After mentioning these otelVersion just after the actuator, I'm going to add the dependency related to
the open telemetry Java agent.
So let me mention the same here.
So like you can see here, the group ID is going to be io.opentelemetry.java agent and the
artifact is going to be opentelemetry-Javaagent and we are trying to refer to the version variable
that we have created in the top. And the scope
you can see I have mentioned the runtime, which means during compilation, I don't need this open telemetry
only when I'm trying to run my application at runtime only
I want this library to be utilized.
So let me save this changes.
Do a maven refresh.
After mentioning these dependency as a next step, I'm going to open the application.yml file present
inside the accounts microservice. Here
I'm going to introduce a new property just under the logging parent.
I'm going to create a new child property and this property is logging.pattern.level and I'm
trying to give a logging pattern. By default
the opentelemetry is going to follow some logging pattern.
Since I want to have my own custom pattern.
I'm trying to mention the same here with the help of this pattern.
So the first pattern, which is percentage %5p indicates I want to assign some file length characters
before my application name.
Inside this five length character Opentelemetry can try to generate some log severity, like whether
the log is debug info or warning or error.
After mentioning this pattern.level, you can see I have opened the square bracket and similarly
at the end I also close the square bracket.
Inside the square bracket I'm going to add three parameters.
The very first one is tag.
So inside the tag I'm trying to mention the metadata information which is related to the
spring.application.name.
And after this tag information, I'm trying to convey to my spring boot framework at runtime Open Telemetry
library is going to generate the trace ID with the context information.
trace_id. The same I want to inject here. After trace ID.
We also want to inject span ID at the runtime into all my logs.
So my spring boot framework, whenever it is trying to generate a log statement, it will look for this
pattern and for these kind of dynamic information.
And accordingly it is going to append the same inside all my log statements that are going to be generated
by my microservice.
Now, as a next step, I'm going to make these two changes inside all my microservices behind the scenes.
Now, behind the scenes, I have made the changes related to the open telemetry inside all the microservices.
As a next step, I will go to the CustomerController class, inside the CustomerController class.
As of now we are trying to generate the logs and try to append the correlation ID that is being sent
by my gateway server.
You can see we are trying to attach this.
Instead of this, I'm going to introduce new logger statements saying that fetchCustomerDetails() method
start. To this logger statement
my open telemetry at runtime
It is going to inject application name trace ID and the span ID.
With that reason we no more need these correlationId.
Let me try to mention the same kind of logger before the return statement, but this time I'm going
to mention fetchCustomerDetails method end. This way you can add any number of logs inside your microservices
at the controller layer, service layer, Dao layer.
It's up to you where you want to define the log statements.
By default, all the logs will have distributed tracing information based upon the pattern that we have
mentioned.
So very
similarly, let me go to the LoansController class.
Inside the LoansController class also added the fetch API.
We are trying to generate the logs with the help of correlationId.
Here
also I'm going to mention the same log, but instead of fetchCustomerDetails I'm going to mention
the method name, which is fetchLoanDetails method start.
So let me mention the same at the end of the method as well.
Saying that method and as a next step I'll go to CardsController. Inside CardsController
also we have fetch API under fetch API
we are trying to generate the logs with the help of correlationId, so let me remove them and mention
my own log statements with the method name as fetchCardDetails.
Method start and I'm going to mention the same logger again towards the end of the method saying that
fetchCardDetails method and with this we are done with all the changes related to the opentelemetry
inside my microservices.
So with the Opentelemetry we are going to add the distributed tracing information to my logs.
Do you think just by adding distributed information is going to help the developers.
Off course, to some extent it is going to help developers, but to make developers life easy, we need
to provide some UI where they can try to see all the information related to a request.
By giving the span ID or the trace ID, we need to set up such solution inside our microservices.
So let's try to understand how to set up the same.
Like I said before, with the help of Opentelemetry, we are going to add that traces and spans information
automatically open telemetry, also known as OTel.
It is a vendor neutral open source observability framework for instrumenting generating, collecting
and exporting telemetry data, such as traces, metrics and logs.
How these open telemetry is going to generate a trace information is, at runtime
it is going to attach some byte code to your microservice application. Using the same byte code
it is going to attach all the tracing information span information or any other metadata information.
Once my open telemetry generated all the logs with the required tracing information, we are going to
use a component inside the Grafana ecosystem, which is tempo.
What is the purpose of this tempo?
Just like Loki for logs and Prometheus for metrics.
Similarly, using tempo, we are going to index all the tracing information.
This tempo again is a open source product, highly scalable and cost effective solution.
Using this tempo, we are going to store and analyze all the trace information. So tempo is capable of
only storing the tracing information.
We need some UI application which is going to connect to the tempo and display the same inside an UI
page.
That's where Grafana will come into picture.
So you can see the ecosystem of Grafana is very beautiful and fascinating.
They always have a common UI component which is grafana and based upon the data source, are based upon
the connection details.
It can connect with various components like Loki, Prometheus, tempo and based upon our scenario,
we can search for logs or tracing information or metrics information.
That's why learning the basics of Grafana and its various components inside Grafana ecosystem is mandatory
for any microservice developer or platform or operations team member.
So using tempo, the Grafana is going to show all the distributed information in an easily understandable
visual information.
When we see the demo, it is going to be super clear for you.
As of now we are done only the changes related to open telemetry.
As a next step, we need to generate the Docker images for all our microservices and post that we need
to update the Docker compose file to implement the changes related to the tempo and the integrating
the same with the Grafana.
I hope you are clear where we are going.
By the time I come to the next lecture I'm going to generate all the Docker images based upon the latest
open telemetry changes.
If you are following with me, please delete the existing Docker images and try to generate the Docker
image again with the tag name S11.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.