Inside this lecture, let's try to update the Docker compose file with the changes related to the Opentelemetry
tempo and Grafana integration of tempo.
For the same, I'm going to open the prod profile inside my Docker compose folder.
First, I'm going to open the common-config.yml.
Here I'm going to define some environment properties that are going to common for all microservices.
Since I want to mention the properties that are common for all microservices, I need to define the
environments under this microservice-base-config.
If I define under this microservice-configserver-config, then my config server will
not receive all the properties that I'm going to define here.
With that reason, I'm going to define environment details under these base config.
So let me mention environment here.
Under this environment I'm going to paste few environment properties like Java tool options and Opentelemetry
related properties.
So if you try to understand what are these properties first with the help of Java tool options, I'm
trying to pass Java agent parameter along with the path where my Opentelemetry jar is going to present.
Since we have defined the opentelemetry dependency inside our pom.xml, this jar is going to present
under this path inside all the containers.
That's why I have mentioned the same.
Now if you see I am trying to mention Otel exporter endpoint.
So to this endpoint property I'm trying to mention tempo service name and what is the port where my
tempo is going to expose its service.
So the Opentelemetry is going to send all the tracing related information to this tempo service and
at last using this property which is Otel metrics exporter, I'm setting as none because I don't want
to get metrics with the help of Opentelemetry because we already used a better tool whenever we are
trying to export metrics, which is Prometheus.
With that reason, I'm trying to set none value here. So let me save these changes.
Now I'll go to the Docker compose file and here under all my microservices I need to create an environment
property.
First
let me mention the same under the config server.
Under the config server I'm trying to mention an environment property with the name
otel_service_name. With this property which is otel_service_name.
We are trying to convey what is a service name to the Opentelemetry library.
So let me mention the same kind of environment in other places as well.
So here also I'm going to mention the same in all the places, the spring application name and your
hotel service name is going to be same.
There is no mandatory that you need to use the same, but I'm trying to be consistent here.
Let me mention the same under accounts microservice as well.
So here I'm going to replace with accounts and post that I'm going to mention the same for loans as
well and replace this eureka server with loans.
Now I'll go to the cards and I'll mention the same here by replacing these Eureka server with cards.
At last I'll go to the gateway server and mention the same.
The service name is going to be Gateway server here.
So now we have defined all the environment property details inside common config and Docker compose
which are related to opentelemetry.
As a next step, we need to add the configurations related to tempo.
Before that, under the observability, I'm going to create a new directory with the name tempo.
Inside this folder, I'm going to create a new configuration file which is related to tempo.
Let me paste the file here.
The file name is going to be tempo.yml.
If you try to understand what is present inside this tempo.yml.
We have some tempo related configurations like it is going to listen at the port 3100 and there is some
other information like what is the trace idle period which is 10s, what is the maximum block bytes,
what is the maximum block duration?
So these are all the configurations related to tempo which we need to follow based upon the official
documentation.
I'm not going in detail about these configurations because in real projects the responsibility of all
these configurations belongs to the platform team.
Now under this Docker compose file just above the Grafana, I'm going to create a new service with the
name tempo.
So here just above the Grafana let me create a new service.
Like you can see, I have created a new service with the name tempo and this is a Docker image and the
container name is going to be tempo and it is going to invoke the command file which is present at this
location with the name tempo-config.yml.
Now under the ports we have mentioned the port mapping the same port which is 3100.
We have to mention inside this tempo.yml you can see.
We have mentioned this Http listener port.
The same port 3100 we have to mention here. But we can't expose the same to the outside because the
same 3100 is already being exposed in some other place.
If you try to search the same inside our Docker compose file, you can see this service, which is Gateway,
is already exposing the Port 3100.
So since we can't expose at the same number, I'm trying to mention a different port number which is
3110.
Apart from this, we also have other port mapping which is at the port number 4317.
Now coming to the volumes, I'm trying to copy the tempo.yml file which is present inside my observability
folder to the etc location with the name tempo-config.yml the same we are trying to use here
now as a next step, we are trying to extend the network related information from the commonconfig.yml.
.
With this we have introduced a new service tempo inside our Docker compose file.
As a next step we need to provide the integration between grafana and tempo. So where we need to provide
that with the help of datasource.yml file present inside the grafana.
As of now you can see we have created two data sources with the name Prometheus and Loki.
So very similarly, let me mention data source details related to tempo as well.
First, I'll try to delete any data source with the name tempo that I'm going to create a new data source
with the name tempo.
So here, let me paste some data source related details related to tempo.
So just after the Prometheus, I'm going to paste the data source related changes of tempo.
So let me bring these tempo configurations to the correct location.
With that, the error will get resolved.
Like you can see, the name of the data source is going to be tempo and it is of type Tempo.
The Uid that I'm trying to give for this is tempo and the tempo is going to start at the port
3100 and my grafana is going to interact with tempo with the service name tempo.
After making these changes, my grafana should be able to connect with my tempo and we should be able
to see the tracing information inside my Grafana application.
I hope you are clear with all the changes that we have done. In the next lecture, let's try to start
all our applications and see the distributed tracing in action.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.