With the current setup, we are able to see that trace ID and spam ID inside our Loki logs.
But to understand that tracing information with the help of tempo, we need to take this trace ID,
we need to go to the tempo and search for the same and post that only we are able to see the complete
tracing information.
But don't you think it is going to be super easy for developers if they can directly open the tempo
from this log statement itself.
We can achieve the same.
For the same,
we need to go to the Loki data source.
So let me go to the Loki data source.
Here under the connections, I'm going to click on the data source and I'll open the Loki.
So if you see under the Loki, we have a concept called derived fields.
With the help of these derived fields, we can try to tell to the Loki whenever it identifies some pattern,
it can try to derive a field and using that field we can try to link with other components inside the
grafana.
For the same, we need to click on this ad, so here I'm going to give the field name as trace ID and
post that we need to give the regex that is going to match our logging pattern.
So let me give the regex pattern here.
So this is the regex pattern that I want to give.
We can also try to test this pattern by taking some example log message.
So here we can try to paste our log message.
So let me take the log message by opening the grafana in another tab.
So here I'm going to open the Grafana and go to the dashboard and go to the Explore option and search
for logs of accounts
microservice. So let me run this query and here I'm going to take this entire content of tracing information.
So let me copy this value into the debug log message and you can see based upon the regex pattern I
have given here from my log message, it is going to extract that trace ID and this value will be assigned
to the field name that I have created, which is trace ID.
So whenever it extracts a field like trace ID, I want to establish a link to one of the components
inside the Grafana.
So for the same we need to click on this internal link and post that we need to select what is our data
source of other component.
Here we want to go to Tempo from Loki.
That's why we need to select this tempo. And post that
using this query we need to pass some query param which my tempo is going to use to search for the tracing
information based upon the trace ID. For the same,
since it is going to be internal link, we don't have to mention any domain.
We can directly mention this value which is dollar value.raw.
So let me mention the query value as $__.value.raw.
So what we are trying to say here is whatever value that we have extracted, the same we want to
pass as a query value to this TempoDataSource.
So let me save these changes by clicking on this save and test.
Now I can go to the Explore option.
Here this time I'm going to search for the logs again, like container and under the value I'll select the
accounts microservice and look for the logs of accounts microservice.
So here if you try to click on any of the log where we have trace information, you'll be able to see
a new field with the name trace ID and along with the trace value.
So here there is a link option for you with the name Tempo
if I try to click on this on the right hand side, it is going to open all the tracing information related
to that particular log.
Don't you think this is a very good option?
Off course everyone will like this option.
So this is the beauty of Grafana here.
So to make our life easy, instead of defining all these derived fields from the UI application every time,
what we can do is, we can try to define all these derived fields information inside the datasource.yml
file that we have.
So let me go to the datasource.yml file.
So under the Loki here, under this Json data, I'm going to mention some configurations related
to derived fields.
You can see I'm trying to use the datasourceUid of tempo. Under the tempo
you can see the uid that we have created
is tempo. The same value we have to mention here?
And what is the matter is what is your field name, which is trace ID and what is the internal URL or
query value.
So we have mentioned the same inside UI as well. But here we need to go to dollar symbols since this
is a Yaml configuration and very similarly under the regex pattern
also just to make sure that your Yaml configuration is considering the slash, we need to make sure
we are putting one more slash in all the places, wherever we have slashes, we follow the same kind
of rules whenever we try to create strings with special characters inside Java as well.
The same I'm trying to follow here. With this,
you don't have to mention the derived fields manually whenever your grafana is trying to create along
with the loki data source, it is going to consider all these derived fields that we have mentioned.
I hope you are
super, super clear.
Thank you.
And I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.