As of now, we installed a helm chart which is available inside one of the public repository with the
same helm chart.
We set up the wordpress website, but in any real projects or in any enterprise organizations, they
should build their own helm charts based upon their microservices requirements.
So that's why we should also try to build our own helm chart so that using the same helm chart, we
can deploy all our microservices into the Kubernetes cluster with a single command.
And very similarly, we can also uninstall with a single command.
And this will make our life very easy in maintaining any number of Kubernetes manifest files for any
number of microservices that we may have inside our organization.
So to get started, I came to my workspace location, and here I'm going to create a new folder.
And the name that I'll give to this folder is section_16, because right now we are into
the 16 section inside this new folder that I have created, I'm going to create one more folder with
the name Helm.
Once I created this folder inside this helm folder only, I'm going to create all the helm charts that
I need for my microservices deployment.
So let me open my terminal at this location. For the same,
I'm going to copy the path of this folder location and I'll go to my terminal.
Inside my terminal,
I'm going to run the cd command cd and what is the space that I want to navigate?
So inside the Section 16, I want to go into Helm folder.
Now I'm at the right location.
As a next step, I can try to create a helm chart inside this folder.
So to create the helm chart, we can run a command which is helm create and what is the name that
we want to give for our helm chart?
So the name that I want to do here is easybank-common because first I'm going to build a helm
chart that is going to be act as a common chart for all my microservices.
So that's why I'm giving this name.
So as soon as I enter inside my folder location, a helm chart might have created with the name
eazybank-common.
We can validate the same here.
So here I have a folder and inside this folder we have a helm chart with all the predefined files and
folders that we have discussed previously.
So whenever we try to create a helm chart with the help of Helm Create Command, the helm is going to
give some predefined helm chart.
This predefined helm chart is going to have some content to deploy a website.
Since we want to write our own content, what we can do here is, first we can try to delete all the template
files that we have inside our helm chart. And post that
I will also open the values.yaml.
So inside the values.yaml we have many values related to nginx because using this nginx only the default
helm chart is going to deploy a website.
So since we don't want to follow these values, we can remove all the values.
And as a next step I'm going to check if there are any dependencies that this particular chart has and
the charts you can see as of now it is empty, which means the default chart that is created by the
helm
it does not have any dependent helm charts. So we should be good with this empty helm chart folder.
As a next step, I'll open this chart.yaml. Inside this chart.yaml,
you can see I have opened this yaml file in visual code IDE.
The version is v2,
I'm fine with that.
I'm fine with the name, description and type as application and the version here is 0.1.0.
So this indicates what is the version of your helm chart.
So I'm fine with the default value.
The next value here we have is app version.
So what is a version of app that you are trying to build?
Since the default helm chart that is provided by the helm has some nginix website.
It has a version which is one dot 16.0, but I want to maintain my own app version, so I'll just keep
it as 1.0.0.
So once we make these default changes as a next step, I'm going to create the required template files
for my easybank microservices.
If you can recall in the previous section to deploy all our microservices, we have written deployment,
manifest file and service manifest file and config map.
As of now, my microservices need only these manifest files to deploy my microservices into the Kubernetes
cluster.
So that's why I'm going to create a three template files inside this helm chart which can be used by
all my microservices like accounts, loans, cards and many other microservices that I have inside
my microservice network.
For the same, I'm going to paste three template files inside this folder post that we can discuss all
of them in detail.
So here I'm pasting few files.
Like you can see I have pasted three files, so let's try to open them and try to discuss them one by
one.
The first file that I want to discuss is about the service.yaml because this is simple yaml template.
File.
So let me open this.
So here by looking at these Yaml file, you can easily understand this is a helm template but not a
Kubernetes manifest file because you're able to see these curly braces throughout the Yaml file and
that is a hint for you.
So now let's try to understand in detail about this template.
So first I'm trying to define a name for this entire template.
The name is common.service.
So with the help of this, define function or define keyword, we are trying to give a name to this
entire Kubernetes template file so that other microservice helm charts that we are going to build in
future.
They can try to refer with the name common.service.
So that's the purpose of define here.
And whatever hyphens that you see at the starting and at the end, those are helpful to trim any space
that you may have before and after of your statement.
So basically Helm is using Go template language and in few places it also uses spring template language.
But we don't have to go deep dive into the helm because we're trying to learn helm on a high level, helm
itself need a separate course to learn everything about helm.
But we as a developers, we don't have to learn everything about Helm.
So whenever we are defining a name for your template with the help of this define at the end,
we should also close that by using this end statement.
So whatever we have defined between the define and end.
So this template will be assigned to a name which is common.service.
So now inside the template, the first element that I have is API version with the value V1 and the
kind is service.
So these are static values.
They are never going to change.
That's why I'm directly mentioning the key and value for them.
Now, under the metadata name, I need to inject a dynamic value.
So whoever is going to use this template Yaml file, they need to provide a service name inside their
values.yaml.
The same name will get injected here.
So values is a helm framework object.
So inside that values object keys and values that you have defined inside your values.yaml will
be available and to access them.
I need to use .values. and what is the key name of the property.
So the key name is going to be service name.
And similarly, under the specification selector app we are using a key which is app label inside the
Values object and the type for the service
we are going to read with a key which is service.type.
When I show you the values example for this template file, then it is going to make more sense to you.
For now, please note that all the values that we have mentioned inside this curly braces along with
the Values object, those are going to be dynamically injected at runtime by the helm based upon the
values that we are going to provide.
Now under the ports, we have the name as Http and the protocol is TCP and post that we need to provide
what is the port and what is the target port.
Since these are dynamic values, I'm trying to read them with the help of Values object with a key as
service.port and service.target port.
So I hope this is clear now very similarly, let me open the deployment template yaml file so that we
can discuss the same.
So here I have a deployment.yaml file.
Let me try to open that, here
also we are using the same define and the end.
The name that we are giving for this template is commo.deployment.
Under the API version we are giving app/v1 and the kind is going to be deployment under the metadata
name label apps.
We are trying to inject some dynamic values now under the specification replicas.
We are trying to get the replica count from the values and post that selector match labels app
also, we are trying to inject the app label value now under the templates metadata labels app.
Here also we are trying to give the app label name and at the specification we are trying to give a name
to the container with the same variable which is app label post that under the image we are trying to
provide the image details based upon the values which has a key like image.repository.
And after the image we are also providing that tag using this image.tag.
Under ports, we are mentioning the container port and protocol is going to be TCP.
Now, after defining all the container related properties, we should also try to inject environment
variables that are required for my particular microservice.
That's why you can see here I have started a new element with the name env.
I'm trying to inject a lot many properties but against each property I have a if condition.
So inside helm we can write the if tag by using this if .values. app name enabled.
So if this boolean value has true, then this entire environment variable is going to be injected into
the particular microservice deployment yaml file.
So each if check has to end with a end statement.
So the reason why I have
return this check is maybe there might be some microservice where I don't have to pass the property,
which is spring application name.
So for such microservice we can have the app name enabled as false inside the values.yaml.
And with that this environment will not be injected into the Kubernetes manifest file.
I hope this is clear.
So for this environment property, we are trying to assign the value from the using the app name variable.
I'm not trying to inject the value with the help of config map.
The reason is is going to be different for different, different microservices.
So I can directly mention what is the name inside the values.yaml of the particular microservice.
Post that I'm using
one more if condition which is if the profile is enabled.
So for some microservices we want to inject a environment variable which is spring profiles active.
So using this environment property, we can tell to the spring boot application whether we want to start
our application with the prod profile or profile or a default profile.
So that's why I have mentioned this profile enabled condition.
Only if this is true, then only this environment variable is going to be injected.
So the value for this environment variable, I'm going to get it from the config map with the name that
I have mentioned inside the values.global.configmap name.
So the key inside the config map is going to be the spring profiles active only.
So based upon this key inside the config map, my helm is going to look up for the value.
The same is going to be assigned to this environment variable which is spring profiles active.
So very similarly, if the config enabled is true, then I'm going to inject the spring config import
environment variable and post that based upon Eureka enabled
I'm trying to inject this environment variable which is related to the Eureka service URL and at last
using this resource server enabled
that means if my microservice is acting as a resource server inside Oauth2, which is going to be the
scenario for Gateway Server, I'm going to inject this environment variable. For all the remaining microservices
other than Gateway server.
This boolean is going to be false and with that we are not going to inject this value in all the other
microservices except in Gateway Server.
And at last, since we are going to set up the entire microservice network along with the Grafana Opentelemetry.
So for the same we need to inject some properties like what is the location where our open telemetry
jar is available.
So the same I'm going to inject with the help of this Java tools option and this property is going to
be injected only when the hotel is enabled for a particular microservice and if the same hotel enabled
is true.
I'm also trying to inject other environment variables like what is the hotel exporter endpoint to which
we need to provide the what is the endpoint URLs where my open telemetry can send the details And after
these property, we also need to mention these hotel metrics exporter and at last we also need to inject
these environment variable which is hotel service name all these hotel related environment variables
along with the Java tool options we discussed inside the observability and monitoring section.
I hope you remember them.
If you have some questions, you can look at the Docker compose files that we have built in those sections.
And with that you should be able to understand why we are injecting these properties.
So these four properties we are going to inject, only these hotel is enabled. And after these hotel
enabled we also have one more if condition which is Kafka enabled.
Since I'm going to show you the demo of complete microservice setup inside this section, I'm going
to leverage Kafka to demo you the event driven microservices.
So for the same like, you know, the accounts microservice and the message microservice, they are
going to connect with the Kafka broker.
So for those microservices, I'm going to mention the Kafka enabled as true.
So whenever this variable is true, then we need to inject these environment along with the environment
value from the config map.
So this is that deployment.yaml file.
As a next step, let me open the config map template that I have written.
So here we have a configmap.yaml.
If you try to understand this is very simple.
First, I'm trying to give a name to this config map template with a name common.configmap and
post that version v1 kind as configmap and the name I'm trying to give from the values.global.
configmap name.
So I'm going to follow a standard like wherever I mentioned a prefix value as global.
So that property name is going to be common for all microservices inside my microservice network.
So the config map name is going to be common for all the microservices.
That's why I'm mentioning the global as a prefix and very similarly spring profiles active
I'm going to read from the values.object with a key as global.active profile.
Same for springconfig
support Eureka Service URL and what is the Spring Security Resource Server URL where my gateway server can
get an certificate of my keycloak.
So those details also I'm going to provide with the help of this keycloak URL and at last, with the
help of this Java tool options, I'm going to mention where is the path of Opentelemetry Java agent.
So if you see here, I'm trying to create all the environments that we have used inside the deployment.yaml.
But I'm not trying to mention the direct hardcoded values inside the configmap.yaml because I may
have different, different requirement
like for dev environment, I may have different profile, different URLs.
And similarly for QA and prod, I may have different values.
So that's why we are going to maintain values.yaml for different, different environments.
But the template is going to be the same.
That's why I'm trying to mention these variable names instead of hardcoded values inside this template
file.
So with this I'm assuming you are clear about these three template Yaml files that I have written inside
the easybank-common helm chart.
As a next step we can check values.yaml and make sure this is empty because this helm chart, which
is easybank-command, this is going to be leveraged by the other helm charts.
So whoever is going to leverage this common helm chart, they are going to provide their own values.yaml
and this helm chart, which is easy bankhyphen command does not have any specific requirements to pass
its own values.
So that's why we are going to keep the values.yaml for this helm chart as empty.
So with this easybank-common helm chart, we have prepared a common helm chart which has a template
files related to service deployment and config map.
As a next step, we need to create the helm charts which can leverage these templates and provide their
own values.yaml based upon the microservices requirement.
So let's try to do the same in the next lecture.
Thank you.
And I'm assuming your super clear bye.