Now, inside this lecture, let's try to create a helm chart which is specific to an environment.
So that we can deploy all our microservices with a single helm chart command. For the same inside the same
folder where I have easybank-common and easybank-services.
I'm going to create a new folder with the name environments. Inside this folder,
I'm going to create a new helm chart.
So inside my terminal I'm going to run the command, which is helm create.
First, I'm going to create a helm chart which is specific to that dev environment.
So for the same I'm going to mention dev-env so the name can be anything, but I'm trying to
give this name which is dev-env.
So let me try to execute this and my command will create a helm chart with the name dev-env. Inside
this folder
first I'm going to make sure all the templates we are deleting and similarly I will also delete all
the values present inside the values.yaml file.
So let me delete them.
Now as a next step I'm going to open the chart.yaml.
So inside this chart.yaml.
I'm fine with these api version name description, but app version I'll just keep it as 1.0.0.
So just to be consistent with the other helm charts.
Now as a next step, we need to define the details of all the dependent helm charts.
You know, what is the format that we need to follow Using the dependencies, we can mention any number
of dependent helm chart details.
So first I'm trying to mention easybank-common and post that config server, Eureka server, accounts,
cards, loans, gateway server and message.
So once you have defined all these details as a next step, we can go to the templates folder. Inside
my templates folder,
as of now you can see it is empty.
But before I try to proceed with the next step, I have a question for you.
So what are the template files that we have needed for these particular dev environment helm chart?
Do you think we need deployment and service manifest files whenever we want to set up an environment?
Off course we don't need because all those microservice specific template files are already present inside
the helm charts which are specific to your microservice. Inside the environment
related helm chart.
We just need to use the config map template because whatever we define with the help of config map,
it is going to be common for all the microservices.
That's why inside this templates folder we need to have a template which is related to the config map.
For the same,
I'm going to copy a file here.
If I try to open this config.yaml, here we're not going to mention the actual template of config
map because we already defined a config map template inside the easybank-common helm chart with the
name as common.configmap.
The same I'm trying to import here and use the same template.
So with this we have set up the template files inside environment.
As a next step, we should populate the values.yaml file.
So as of now you can see it is empty.
So here I'm going to paste few values.
Like you can see here, the prefix value that I have mentioned for all these values is global because
whatever I'm going to define inside these values.yaml this is going to be applicable for all my
microservice.
So that's why I have these prefix.
But this is not a mandatory or a standard from helm.
This is a prefix that I want to maintain for my own understanding.
So under the global.config map name we are trying to give what is a configmap name.
So the same is going to refer inside the config map template that we have created.
I can try to open the same if I go to the easybank-command and open the templates folder here I have
configmap.yaml.
So here while we are trying to create the config map under the metadata we need to give a name for our
config map.
So the name is going to get from global.configmap name which we have defined here.
So for dev environment, I'm going to have the name as easybankdev-configmap. And here active
profile I have mentioned qa, but this should be default because right now we are trying to build a chart
for the dev environment.
So inside the dev environment we want to use the default profile of spring boot.
So that's why I have mentioned the default.
Now coming to the config server URL, this is the value where my config server is going to be available.
So here the host name has to be same as your service name that you have defined.
So the service name that we have defined inside the service.yaml file of configserver is config
server.
Similarly for Eureka server, this is the service name.
The same I have mentioned as Eureka server URL.
Now coming to the keycloak URL here you can see this is the host name which is like Keycloak.default.svc.
cluster.local and it is going to available at the port 80.
So this is something new for you because in the coming lectures we are going to set up all the third
party components like Keycloak, Kafka and Grafana components with
the helm charts only. In that process they are going to be deployed with the production standards.
So when we follow those production standards, this is how our service name is going to be built inside
the Kubernetes cluster.
That's why I'm trying to mention the same here.
Now after this keycloak url, I'm trying to mention where is the path where my opentelemetry related
jar is going to be present?
And at last, what is the tempo of Grafana?
So these are tempo URL service name.
Since we are going to install Grafana tempo with the helm chart, this is how the service name is going
to come and the metrics exporter
I'll mention the value as none and coming to the Kafka broker URL,
this is the value that I want to mention.
So here also the service name is not going to be simple because we are going to install the Kafka with
the help of helm charts available inside the web.
So with all these values, this configmap.yaml is going to be populated and behind the scenes a
config map is going to be created inside your Kubernetes cluster and from the same config map all your
microservices can read the values at runtime.
If you have any questions please go and check the Docker Compose files that we have built, the same
properties we injected into the microservices with the help of Docker compose as well.
So with this we have set up the values.yaml template and we also updated the chart.yaml of
dev-env environment.
As a next step, I need to compile these helm charts so that I will be able to see all the dependent
charts inside these charts folder.
So for the same I need to go into the folder which is dev-env and here I'm going to run the common
which is helm dependencies build.
So this is going to compile all the dependencies helm charts.
The compilation is successful.
Let me go to the folder location.
So now you can see under the charts folder I have all the dependent helm charts available in a packaged
or compressed format.
So with this we set up the helm chart for one environment which is dev.
Very similarly, I'm going to set up for QA and production as well.
For the same,
let me copy the same helm chart and rename this to qa-env.
Post that.
I'm going to open the chart.yaml.
Here we can change the name to qa-env and with that we should be good from chart.yaml perspective.
As a next step we can update the values.yaml.
Here the changes that we need to do is under the active profile.
We need to mention the profile value as QA.
And similarly I'll just make the config map name as easybankqa-configmap.
And apart from that we don't have to change any other values.
But for some reason if you are having some different host names or service names inside your specific
environment, you can always update these values.
So with this we set up the environment helm chart
also. As a next step, let me copy the qa environment and rename this to prod-env.
I'll go inside this folder and I'll open the chart.yaml and rename this name to prod-env
and post that.
I'll open the values.yaml and here I'll just mention the actual profile as prod and I'll also update
the config map name as easybank-hyphen configmap.
So with this we have created all the required helm charts for all the environments.
So now whenever I want to set up my microservices I can simply install one of the helm chart like dev
env or prod env or qa env behind the scenes,
it is also going to install all the remaining microservices along with the required config map.
I hope this is clear.
Thank you.
And I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.