One of the great advantages of Helm is it has a very good community.
With that reason, you should be able to easily find the helm charts to install any product inside the
software industry.
For example, if you want to install Kafka inside your Kubernetes cluster, you don't have to prepare
the Kubernetes manifest files manually.
Instead, you can rely on the helm charts available inside the web.
So one such company are community, which always maintain these helm charts with a great production
standards is Bitnami. So bitnami make it easy to get your favorite open source softwares up and running
on any platform, including your laptop, Kubernetes or all the major clouds.
So this bitnami is supported by VMware.
So inside this course we are going to leverage the Bitnami Helm charts to install all the products like
Kafka, Grafana, Prometheus, Keycloak inside our Kubernetes cluster.
For the same inside the Google, you can search for bitnami helm charts gitHub.
This will show us the GitHub repo where Bitnami is maintaining all the helm charts.
You can see here I have a first link inside my Google search results with the name Bitnami Helm chart.
So let me click on that.
I'm also going to mention this GitHub URL inside our course GitHub repo.
Inside this repo, if you can open this Bitnami folder, you should be able to identify the helm charts
for the majority of the products that any organization needs.
So here we have products like Argo CD, Cassandra Console, followed by Drupal, Elasticsearch.
Similarly, all Grafana related helm charts are also available here like Grafana Loki Grafana Tempo,
Grafana.
If you can scroll down, you'll be able to see many other products like Kafka, Keycloak, Kibana,
Cube prometheus, MongoDB,
logstash.
Mariadb.
Similarly, you should be able to identify some helm charts related to MySQL, Nginx, Postgres database,
Rabbitmq,
Redis.
So there are good amount of helm charts available.
So based upon your requirements you can always leverage these Bitnami helm charts.
As of now we leverage one of the helm chart which is wordpress while seeing demo of helm charts
in the previous lectures.
So in the same location we have many other helm charts and we are going to leverage them to set up required
components inside our Kubernetes cluster.
So to download these helm charts, what I can do is, I can go to the charts folder and here we have an
option to download all these helm charts into local system.
So I'm going to click on this download Zip option and this will download all the helm charts that are
provided by the Bitnami.
I can choose whatever I required and leverage them to install the components inside my Kubernetes cluster.
Let me go to the downloads folder and look for the helm charts that we have downloaded. Inside my downloads
folder,
like you can see I have a folder with the name Bitnami.
If I can open inside this, I have all the helm charts that are provided by the Bitnami.
As a first step, I'm going to use the Keycloak Helm chart. For the same,
let me search for Keycloak and here I have the helm charts related to Keycloak.
Let me copy this and go to the location where we are mentioning all helm charts.
So inside this folder only I'm going to paste the folder related to Keycloak Helm chart.
Inside this Keycloak Helm chart we have all the required files like chart.yaml templates and values.yaml.
If I try to run this Keycloak helm chart into my local Kubernetes cluster by default it is going to
deploy my keycloak service with a cluster IP.
But since I want to access my keyclock to create the client details and roles information, I'm going
to expose my key clock service as a load balancer.
So to change this behavior, we need to open the values.yaml present inside the keycloak helm chart.
So let me open this file.
Inside this file, like you can see, we have lot, many variables.
So let me search for cluster IP because this is a default service type that keycloak helm chart is
going to have.
So here instead of cluster IP, I'm going to mention as LoadBalancer, once you have defined the service
type as LoadBalancer, you can look for a variable with the name admin password.
So as of now you can see my keycloak helm chart is going to create the admin credentials with the admin
user as user and the admin password
here it is mentioned as empty value.
So whenever my admin password is empty behind the scenes, my keycloak helm chart is going to create
a secret which will have some random password.
So instead of that, what I can do here is, I can give my own password.
So here I'm going to give the password as password itself so that we can login into the keycloak admin
with the username as user and the password as password.
So once we make these changes, we should be good.
Let me go to that terminal. Inside my terminal,
I'm going to install the helm chart of keycloak.For the same,
let me go to the location where my key clock helm chart is available.
So let me go back and inside the helm.
I should have the keycloak folder from this folder location,
I'm going to run a helm command, which is helm install and what is the name that you want to give for
your keycloak installation.
So I'll give the name as keycloak itself.
So this is going to be the name of my release that I'm trying to install into my Kubernetes cluster
with the help of keyclock helm chart.
So once you have given some name to your release, you can mention what is the chart name or what is
the folder name where your chart is present.
So the folder name or the chart name is going to be keycloak itself.
So let me try to execute this command.
So if I try to run this command, it is saying my keycloak helm chart has some dependencies missing.
So how to fix this,
we need to run the helm dependencies, build a command inside my keycloak helm chart.
So let me go to the keycloak helm chart.
And inside this I'm going to run the command which is helm dependencies build.
So this will compile all the dependencies and make sure they are available in a packaged format inside
my keyclock helm chart.
So finally the build is completed.
I can now go back to the previous folder and from the helm folder I'm going to run the same command
which is helm install keycloak, keycloak.
So let me try to execute this.
And behind the scenes you can see the installation is completed.
And I also got an output saying that what are the steps that I can follow to access my keyclock URL?
So if I try to run these commands, I should be able to get the URL using which I can access my keycloak
URL.
So let me copy this value and post that I can execute these commands.
Here you can see I got an output saying that I can able to access my keycloak at the URL http and hostname.
Since it is empty we can use localhost and the port is 80.
And similarly, if we want to know what is the username and password, there is also instructions on
how to know the username and password.
You can try to take these commands.
Let me try to clean the console and run the commands again.
So the username is user and the password is going to be the password because inside the values.yaml
we have provided the password as password itself.
Please wait for 1 to 2 minutes for the LoadBalancer to get successfully created inside your local system.
It is going to take easily 1 to 2 minutes at least. Post that
you should be able to access the keycloak at the URL localhost 80.
So let me try to access the same.
So here I'm trying to access the URL.
You can see I'm able to access my administration console.
So let me click on that post that the username I'm going to enter as user and the password is going
to be password.
After entering the credentials, I'm clicking on the sign in button.
I'll go to clients and here I'll try to create a new client.
The client ID is going to be easybank-callcenter-cc
.
So let me click on this next post that I'll enable the client authentication and disable the standard
flow and direct access grants and enable the service account roles.
Let me click on this next save and I'll go to credentials, copy the secret value and I'll paste the
same inside these postman.
And also we should change this access token URL from 7080 port 280 because right now our health chart
expose the keyclock service at the port 80.
If I try to get an access token, it should work
you can see I'm able to get an access token, but we cannot use this because as of now we have not created
any roles.
So that's why
let me try to create some roles here.
The first role I want to create is accounts post that I will create a role related to cards followed
by loans.
With this, I have created required roles, so let me go back to clients and open these easybank-callcenter-cc
and go to the service account roles.
And here I'm going to click on this assign role and assign all the required roles to my client application.
Did you see how easy it is to set up a Keycloak server with the production standards by using Helm Chat?
That's a power of helm chats.
If you don't have helm charts, then definitely you need to prepare a lot
many Kubernetes manifest files.
I can also show you the template files, and with that you should be able to understand how complex
to create and install Keycloak inside a production Kubernetes cluster.
So here under the templates, you should be able to see lot many templates related to Kubernetes objects.
So all these to create manually is going to be a super cumbersome process.
On top of that, my keycloak also has dependency on other helm charts like Postgres because behind the
scenes my keycloak is going to use Postgres database. As a next step,
I want you to explain how we can derive the keycloak endpoint URL that we can feed to the other microservices.
If you see here inside the values.yaml of all the environments we have mentioned, the keycloak URL
as this is the host name, this is the port number.
So
how I know what is a hostname that I want to provide. For the same,
if you try to look at the output console that we received from the helm installation command here,
there is a important information saying that keycloak can be accessed to the following DNS name from
within your cluster.
So this is the DNS name that they have provided the same name I have mentioned inside the values.yaml
of Environment helm chart.
So when we try to give these URL details to Gateway Server, it should be able to easily connect because
my gateway server also is going to be deployed in the same Kubernetes cluster.
With this, we have successfully installed Keycloak with the helm charts.
Similarly, we need to set up other components like Kafka and Grafana, Prometheus components.
But before you try to do that, since we are going to do lot many installations into your Kubernetes
cluster, it may not work inside your local system because you will have very less memory inside your
local system.
So to some extent we can try to overcome this challenge by changing some settings.
For the same, we can go to the Docker desktop dashboard here, I can click on this settings.
After that, I'll click on this resources Under this resources, try to increase the memory that you
are trying to allocate to that Docker desktop. By default
inside my system previously it was CPUs as 4 and memory as GB.8
But with that default values I faced a lot many issues because the installations are very slow and the
response from the microservices are also very slow.
So to overcome this challenge I have increased the number of CPUs to 6 and the memory from 8GB
to 12GB.
So if there is a feasibility inside your local system, please do the same so that your installations
will be fast.
But inside production, this should not be a problem because inside cloud you will have some good amount
of memory and CPUs for some reason.
If your laptop is not cooperating, don't worry, we are going to do the same exercise in the cloud
and during that time you can follow my instructions and do the deployment into the cloud environment.
I hope this is clear.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.