As of now, we successfully installed keycloak component inside our Kubernetes cluster.
You can confirm the same by going into these pods.
Here we have two pods one related to keycloak, the other one related to keycloak PostgreSQL.
Similarly, you can check services.
You should be able to see services related to keycloak,
you can confirm the same under config maps secrets.
So in all the locations we have components related to keycloak.
So this confirms the keycloak installation is complete.
But for some reason if you uninstall the helm chart of keycloak or any helm chart with the help of
helm uninstall and try to install again, sometimes you may face some issues.
Your installation may not be successful.
The reason is, as of now, there is a defect in Helm which is related to the persistent volume claims.
So using these PVC or persistent volume claims, only the pods can climb some space inside the worker
nodes.
So whenever you try to uninstall a specific helm chart from your Kubernetes cluster, it is not going
to delete the PVCs that is created as part of the installation and this may create some issues.
So to overcome the problem, you have to delete the PVCs manually.
So like you can see here we have two PVCs.
One is related to keycloak, the other one is related to the Happy Panda Mariadb.
That means though we have uninstalled the WordPress related helm chart, there is still a PVC available
inside our Kubernetes cluster. So we don't want to retain this,
otherwise next time, if you try to install WordPress again, it is not going to work.
So to overcome this problem, I can delete this.
To delete
there are two options.
I can straight away select this one and post this
I can click on this delete button.
The other option is from the terminal
we can execute a command which is cubectl get pvc.
So this will list all the PVCs available.
And here I want to delete these first two PVC.
So let me try to execute this command, which is Cube Ctl.
delete pvc and what is the PVC name?
So with this my PVC will get deleted.
And next time if you try to install your WordPress related helm chart, they should not be any issues.
This is one of the limitation that I want to highlight about the helm uninstall command.
So as a next step, let's try to set up Kafka component with the help of Helm chart.
For the same, I'm going to take the Kafka related helm chart and paste the same inside the location
where we are maintaining all the remaining helm charts.
So I'm going to check in this entire folder into the GitHub repo so that you don't have to do all the
steps that I'm trying to do, like changing the values inside the values.yaml.
So now if I try to install this Kafka helm chart, it is going to have all production ready standards.
But I don't want to follow that because this is my local system and I don't have such a high capacity
inside my local system.
So to overcome this challenge, we can go to the Kafka Helm chart and open the values.yaml here, I'm
going to first search for the property, which is replica count.
You can see here we have the replica count as three.
With this, my helm chart is going to create three Kafka broker nodes inside my local Kubernetes, which
we don't want because that will slow down my system in real production applications only your Kafka
admin is going to control all these replica count and other values. For our local testing,
we need to change this value to three, two, one.
And apart from this change, I also want to reduce some security related communication because inside
production, always the communication with Kafka is going to be secured.
But inside local system, I don't want to follow that and set up complex security communication.
So to change this, I can search for a value which is SASL_PLAINTEXT.
So as of now, you can see at many places the protocol is mentioned as SASL_PLAINTEXT.
So this is the security protocol
By default
my Kafka is going to leverage.
So to change this and to reduce the security inside my local setup, I can simply change the value to
the plain text.
So here I'm going to remove this prefix, which is SASL.
So you can also see there are comments like what are other allowed values, plain text, SSL plain
text, SASL_SSL and SSL.
So these are all the valid values for our local testing,
we are going to use the plain text and this value is going to present at multiple locations inside your
values.yaml.
So let me search for the next value here
also, I have let me replace this to plain text.
Let me search one more time.
You can ignore the value present inside the comments here I have
so let me change this and post that
let me look for one more match
and I also have a match here.
So let me change this value.
And now I'll search one more time and I don't have any matches.
So all the matches right now are in the comment files only.
So with this now I have
change the security communication from plain text to plain text.
So now we should be good with these values.
Let me try to set up my Kafka with the help of Helm.
So here
first, I need to make sure I'm in the right location.
So inside this folder I have the Kafka helm chart so I can try to run the command, which is helm install.
And what is the name that we want to give to the installation or the release?
So I'll simply give Kafka only and the name of the helm chart.
The name of the helm chart is Kafka itself.
But before we try to run this command, we forget we need to run the dependencies, build command.
Let's see if it is going to work.
So here also it is failing.
So I need to make sure I'm running that dependencies build command.
So let me go inside the Kafka and run the command, which is helm dependencies build.
So here I'm trying to run the same.
Once the build is completed, we can navigate back to the parent folder and run the command, which
is Helm install, Kafka
Kafka.
So if I try to run this command, the Kafka installation will happen inside my local Kubernetes cluster.
So here in the output, you can see there is an information like each Kafka broker can be accessed by
producers via Port 9092 by using the DNS name.
So these are DNS name that we need to consider to provide to the accounts microservice and message microservice.
Because they need to connect to this Kafka broker to send the information asynchronously.
So the same value I have mentioned inside the config map values that we have defined inside all the
environment Helm charts.
I hope this is clear.
And here there are also other instructions which we can follow.
If you want to test our Kubernetes cluster by sending a sample message, that's fine.
We don't have to follow all this because anyway, we are going to test them using our applications.
So now my helm chart installed a Kafka inside my Kubernetes cluster.
I can also validate the same inside my Kubernetes dashboard.
So here I'll go to the parts.
Under parts you will be able to see Kafka related part.
And similarly, if I go to the services, there is Kafka related service.
All of them are defined as cluster IP.
I'm fine with that.
So this confirms that Kafka setup into the Kubernetes cluster with the help of Helm chart is also complete.
Thank you, and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.