Inside this lecture, Let's try to set up Prometheus inside our Kubernetes cluster so that my Prometheus
can scrape all the metrics from my individual microservices.
Post that we are going to set up Grafana related components and we'll make our grafana to talk with
the Prometheus, to search the metrics and to set up the dashboards.
So for the same inside my bitnami downloaded repository, I'm going to look for the folder which has
a name Prometheus and there is a folder with the name kube-prometheus.
So let me copy this folder and paste inside the helm folder that we are mentioning.
So here I have pasted the kube-prometheus.
As usual, we cannot directly install these helm charts into the Kubernetes cluster.
We need to make some changes inside the values.yaml.
So to get started with the changes, we need to open the values.yaml.
Here I'm going to search for a setting with the name additional scrape configs.
So here we have a details related to scrape configs using these configs only my Prometheus will decide
to scrape the metrics from the microservices.
So as of now you can see the additional configs is disabled.
We need to enable this to true and post that we should change this type to internal because we don't
want our Prometheus to scrape anything from outside of the Kubernetes cluster.
Everything we have inside the Kubernetes cluster only so we can change this value to internal.
After making these changes, we need to provide the details of our microservices using which my Prometheus
can connect with them and read the metrics of them with the help of actuator Prometheus URL.
So for the same you can see here under the internal job list as of now it is empty.
So here I'm going to mention some configurations, the same kind of configurations
we also mentioned when we tried to set up Prometheus inside our local system.
So under this job list, I'm going to mention all the job names using which my Prometheus is going to
fetch the metrics from the individual microservices.
So I have mentioned all these details in a Json format.
So here it has a list of jobs and each job is separated by comma value.
If you see here first I have mentioned what is the job name for config server
the job name is going to be config server.
And what is the metrics path and what is the location at which my Prometheus need to connect to get
the metrics.
So this is a service name inside our Kubernetes for config server and it is available at the port 8071.
Similarly for Eureka Server, I have mentioned accounts, loans and cards gateway server.
So for whatever microservices you need, you can mention those job details here.
So once we have defined these details, my Prometheus should be able to scrape metrics from my individual
microservices.
So as a next step, I can try to build the Prometheus related helm chart. For the same,
let me go inside the kube-prometheus folder and here I'm going to run the command, which is helm dependencies
build.
So this will compile my Prometheus helm chart post that we can try to install the same inside our Kubernetes
cluster.
So to install Prometheus, we need to go back and run the command, which is helm install.
And what is the release name that we want to give. The release name that we can give here is Prometheus
itself.
After the release name, I can mention the folder name where my helm chart is present.
It is present under the folder with the name kube-prometheus.
So let me try to execute this command.
This will do the installation of Prometheus inside my local system.
So by default Prometheus is set up with the help of cluster IP, so we cannot really access it.
But for some reason, if you want to access the same, you can run these commands which are related
to kubectl port forward.
So using the kubectl port forward command, we can temporarily expose a service.
So let me try to execute these commands by cleaning the console.
So I'm trying to execute the command and this should start exposing my Prometheus but seems still my
installation of Prometheus is going on.
Let's wait for few minutes.
So I'm going to wait for one two minutes behind the scenes,
I have waited for one minute.
Let me try to execute this command again.
And this time you can see the forwarding of the network is successfully into our local system.
So now I should be able to access the Prometheus at the port 9090.
So here inside my browser let me open 9090 port and this is my Prometheus.
Hree if I go to the targets, I should be able to see all the targets.
As of now, my accounts cards, config server, Eureka server all of them we didn't setup.
That's why the status for all of them is showing as in red color.
If you can scroll down, Prometheus will also try
to monitor many other metrics inside your Kubernetes cluster.
So that's why you are able to see many other components inside the target's location. Since this is meant
for production
ready.
Prometheus Behind the scenes, it is trying to monitor many other components inside your Kubernetes
cluster, but we are more interested about our own microservices.
We can validate the same once we set up our own microservices into the Kubernetes cluster.
For now, I can stop this command by pressing Ctrl C and that will stop exposing my Prometheus into
my local network.
Now, if I try to refresh this page, I will not get any response because the Prometheus is not exposed
to the local system.
With this, we successfully set up Prometheus inside our Kubernetes cluster. As a next step,
let's try to set up Grafana related components like loki, tempo and grafana.
And with that we should be done with all the required components for our microservices end to end testing.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.