As a next step, we are interested to set up Grafana related components inside our Kubernetes cluster.
So inside our microservice network we use loki tempo and grafana.
So these three components we need to set up with the help of helm chart.
So before we try to set up the actual Grafana, first we need to make sure we set up the loki and
tempo. For the same,
I'm going to copy these folders of Grafana loki and Grafana tempo into the helm folder and here I'm going
to paste them.
First, let me try to set up grafana-loki because loki is responsible to aggregate all the logs
that are generated by my individual microservices.
So to install loki, we don't have to make any changes inside the values.yaml.
We should be fine with all the default values available inside this chart. So I can straight away compile
this chart and install inside my local Kubernetes cluster.
So here, let me navigate into my grafana-loki folder and post that I'm going to run the command,
which is helm dependencies build.
So here you can see my loki has dependency on other charts like Memcached.
That's why it is trying to download all those dependencies.
So now my compilation is successful.
I can try to install the loki helm chart with the help of helm install command post that I'm going
to give a name to my release.
The name is going to be loki, but the chart name is going to be grafana-loki.
But since I'm in the wrong location, so let me go back to the parent location and here I'm going to
run the command, which is helm install and the release name is going to be loki.
And inside this folder we have a chart with the name grafana-loki, the same I want to install inside
my Kubernetes cluster.
So this will install many components inside my Kubernetes cluster like ingested, distributor, querier,
promtail, compactor, gateway.
Can you imagine setting up all these without helm chart?
Your Kubernetes administrator will need a lot of help from the developers and the Grafana admin to set
up these and it may need months of effort to have a proper setup, whereas with Helm it is super,
super easy.
As a next step we can set up the tempo as well. For the same,
let me go to the folder location.
Here we have a chart with the name Grafana Tempo.
So let me open the same inside this tempo chart,
we need to change few values inside the values.yaml. So let me open this.
Inside this file I'm going to search for otlp.
So these are related to open telemetry configurations.
So as of now you can see the open telemetry communication with the help of Http protocol and gRPC protocol
is disabled.
We need to enable both of them.
Then only the open telemetry Java agent that we have inside our individual microservices.
It can send the tracing details to the tempo. By default  otlp is disabled inside this helm chart.
So that's why we need to enable them by overriding these values from false to true.
So let me save this file post that I'm going to compile the helm chart, which is grafana tempo.
So here, let me execute the command, which is helm dependencies build.
So this will download all the dependencies of tempo.
Once the build is completed, I will navigate back to the parent folder, from the parent folder,
I'm going to run the command which is helm install and the name of the release I want to give here is
tempo. And post that
what is a helm chart name, the helm chart name is grafana-tempo.
So let me try to execute this.
So this will give some instructions like all these components are installed like ingested, distributor,
querier, query-frontend and compactor and vulture.
But here we have a problem, which is our individual microservices need a tempo url to which my open telemetry
is going to send the details of tracing details.
So here inside the output, we don't have the any information about the URL that we need to use.
So to overcome this challenge, we can try to run the command, which is kubectl get services and this
command is going to list all the services installed inside your Kubernetes cluster.
So as of now, you can see we have installed so many services related to loki, prometheus and similarly
related to keycloak, Kafka.
So if you can scroll down, there are some information related to tempo, so there are many tempo related services.
Like there is a tempo related service with the name gossip-ring, ingester, generator, querier,
vulture, compactor, distributor.
So the service that our open telemetry should connect is these distributor.
So that's why take the service name and we need to make sure we are mentioning the same inside the config
map values.
So here I have mentioned the same here and the port number has to be 4317.
So this is how we are establishing a link between our individual microservice open telemetry with the
grafana tempo.
So you may have question like how do I know that I need to use only distributor but not the other service?
So based upon my experience and official documentation information, I'm able to identify this information
and I'm trying to spoonfeed you this information.
So whenever you have such challenges or questions, always go to the official documentation and you
should be able to get this information.
With this, we successfully installed Grafana Tempo and Loki as well as the last step we need to set
up the Grafana.
So let's try to do the same in the next lecture.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.