As a last step, we need to set up grafana inside our Kubernetes cluster before we try to deploy all
our microservices.
So to install Grafana from the Bitnami folder, I'm trying to copy the Grafana related helm chart with
the name Grafana and paste the same inside the helm folder that we are mentioning.
Like I said before, I'm going to check in this entire helm folder into the GitHub repo.
Please use these helm charts only that I have checked in into the GitHub repo so that you don't have
to make all the changes that I have done inside the values.yaml.
So now before we try to set up this grafana, as usual, we need to make some changes inside the values.yaml
of Grafana Helm chart.
So let me open this inside this values.yaml I need to look for the information on how to provide the
data source Details of tempo Loki and Prometheus.
Like we discussed in the previous sections, Grafana is capable of connecting to these components like
Prometheus, Loki and tempo.
We can provide these data source details to grafana using Yaml configurations, or we can also manually
set up the data sources from the UI of the Grafana.
Since we want to avoid that manual task, we need to look for an information on how to set up the data
source details inside these values.yaml.
So for the same here I'm going to search for data source.
So here there is a section about data sources and here they have given an information saying that whenever
we want to set up a data source, we need to define the data source details under the secret definition.
So here there is an element secret definition under this element secret definition,
we need to provide the data source details like they have mentioned here.
They have mentioned a sample connection, details to Prometheus.
So using the same syntax, we need to set up the data source details for grafana.
So under the secret definition we need to define API version data sources and what are your data sources?
So let me delete these curly braces and navigate to the next line.
Here inside this next line, I'm going to mention few configurations like you can see.
So here I have mentioned API version as one and post that I have mentioned some delete data sources
if already existed in my grafana with these names and at last under data sources I have mentioned three
data source details like what is the Prometheus data source details?
So this is the DNS name of Prometheus inside my Kubernetes cluster.
And similarly for tempo.
So inside tempo we have many services like we discussed previously, so the service that we need to
use for connecting Grafana and tempo is Grafana tempo, Grafana tempo, query frontend.
So this is the one that we need to use.
And for this the port is going to be 300.
You can confirm the same here for the query frontend the port number is 3200.
So the same I'm trying to mention inside the values.yaml. Now coming to the loki.
So for loki we need to connect to the loki gateway service and this is the service name and it
is exposed at the port 80. And at last,
since we want to integrate loki and tempo, I have mentioned these derived fields configurations
just like how we did during our local testing.
So once we define these values now, my grafana should be able to connect with all the components related
to Prometheus, loki and tempo.
As a next step, we can compile these Grafana helm chart and install the same into our Kubernetes cluster.
So here, let me clean the console and post that I'm going to navigate into the Grafana folder.
Inside this folder I'm going to run the command, which is helm dependencies build.
Once the build is completed, we can try to navigate to the parent folder and inside this folder we
can run the command, which is helm install and the release name
I want to give it as grafana.
And what is the helm chart name.
The helm chart name is Grafana itself.
So if I try to execute this command, the Grafana is going to be installed inside my local system. By
default,
my Grafana is going to be exposed as a cluster IP service.
So whenever I have some requirements to debug any issues, my Kubernetes admin can run a command which
is related to kubectl port forward.
With this, my grafana is going to be temporarily accessible with the help of these 3000 port number.
So let me try to execute this command.
So here I'm executing the command.
After executing this command, we should be able to access the Grafana at the port 8080. Because we expose
that traffic at the port 8080.
So Grafana internally is going to start at the port 3000.
But here the traffic is going to be exposed at the port 8080.
But this is going to create some problems because for some reason, if you start your accounts microservice
as a LoadBalancer service, it is also going to expose the traffic at the port 8080.
With that reason, you may face some issues.
That's why I can kill this command and try to run
the same command again.
But this time I will change this port number from 8080 to 3000 itself.
This way my Grafana is going to be available at the port 3000 itself.
So let me execute this command.
Now I'll go to the browser and try to access the port 3000.
Here I'm trying to access the port 3000 and you can see I got an welcome message where I can enter my
username and password. But I don't know what is the username and password. For the same,
if you closely observe the instructions, there are instructions on how to get the username and password.
The username is admin, but to know the password we need to execute these two commands.
So let me go to the other terminal.
So here I'm going to run the command and the username is going to be admin and this is the password.
So let me copy this value.
Here I'm going to enter the credentials and post that
I'll click on the login and you can see right now I'm logged in into the Grafana successfully.
I can also validate if the data source connection is successful or not.
By going to these explore under this dropdown, you can see I'm able to see three data sources related
to loki, prometheus and tempo.
This confirms our Grafana setup also is completed.
As a next step, we can finally install all our microservices into the Kubernetes cluster.
Before that, let me stop this port forwarding and with this I will not be able to access my grafana
in future
whenever I need, I can try to run the port forward command.
So let me clean the console and try to run the command, which is helm ls.
This will show you all the releases or all the installations or deployments that we have done with the
help of Helm.
So as of now we have installed Grafana, Kafka, Keycloak, Loki, Prometheus and Tempo. And these
are the chart details that we have used to set up these components inside the Kubernetes cluster.
I hope this is all clear to you in the next lecture,
let's try to deploy our microservices into the Kubernetes cluster.
Thank you, and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.