Finally, we are going to deploy our microservices into the Kubernetes cluster with the help of Helm.
I promise you previously, whenever we are using Helm, we can install all our microservices with a
single command.
The same
I'm going to show you a demo inside this lecture. For the same,
first, let's make sure you are inside the environments folder and inside these environments folder,
we have three charts related to dev, prod and qa environment.
First, we need to decide under which environment we want to deploy our microservices.
Let's imagine we want to deploy our microservices into production.
So once we selected these production environment, we need to run a command which is helm install.
What is the release name?
The release name I can give here is easybank and post that
what is the chat name.
The chat name that I want to consider here is prod env because we are trying to deploy our microservices
using the production profile.
So let me execute this command.
As soon as I execute this command you will simply get an output that the deployment is completed or
initiated.
So as a next step, let's go to the Kubernetes dashboard.
Here inside the dashboard, we can go to the pods and all of our microservices, they will try to start at
the same time.
And since they are going to start at same time, they are going to fail multiple times because config
server is not going to available, Eureka Server is not going to available.
For that reason, the pods are going to be failed to start and whenever this kind of scenario occurs
inside my Kubernetes, my Kubernetes is smart enough to do multiple restarts till the pod is successfully
started or it reaches a maximum number of attempts.
And whenever it is trying to restart a particular part, Kubernetes will make sure it is taking some
time between multiple restarts.
First time it may take two seconds.
Next time it may take 4 seconds or 5 seconds.
So it is going to delay the next restart based upon exponential delay.
But what we can do here right now is, we can go to the logs of each of the service and make sure all
of them started successfully.
So the first service that we need to make sure to start is config server.
For the same,
we can click on these config server pod and here there is an option to see the logs.
So let me click on this view logs and you can see right now my config server is getting started.
So to automatically refresh the logs on this console, you can select these option which is auto refresh
every five seconds.
So this will automatically refresh the logs into your Kubernetes dashboard and at this port every five
seconds.
So let me wait for the logs to refresh and see the message, which is config server successfully started
and this is going to take a lot of time inside our local system because in my scenario I just have a
16 GB ram and inside this 16 GB ram I only assign 12 GB to the Docker desktop and Kubernetes.
And inside that 12 GB we are trying to set up so many components and that is why your installation is
going to be super, super slow.
So please wait for 5 to 10 minutes in between
you can keep checking the logs of all the services and make sure all of them are started.
So I'm going to wait for a few minutes here.
As of now you can see I got an output saying that config server started successfully, so this confirms
my config server started.
I'll go back to the pods and I'll open the Eureka server because my Eureka server has a dependency on
the config server.
You can see here it tried to start multiple times.
That's why we have restarts
has to.
Since config server is not yet available, the Eureka server is not started successfully.
That's why as of now to restart attempts happened by the Kubernetes cluster.
Now let me see the logs here.
So this time a fresh restart is happening.
So let me wait here.
Finally, after two minutes, my Eureka server also started successfully.
You can see in the logs we have a statement saying that started Eureka Server application in one 58
seconds.
My local system is super, super slow
now. The fan inside my laptop also is rotating at a full speed.
So now let me go back to the pods and as a next step I can try to check the logs of accounts
microservice. Accounts also has restarts of two times.
So here if I check the logs since my accounts microservice started successfully and it also connected
with my Eureka server, I can go back to my loans and cards and I can confirm the same whether they
started successfully.
My cards also started successfully.
Let me go back to loans.
Inside the loans we can check the logs and here also loans also started successfully as a next step,
I can check Gateway server inside the gateway server
I have logs saying that the gateway server application started successfully.
Next, I can check messages.
Messages should started successfully because it has no dependency on config server,
Eureka server.
That's why we have a number of restarts as zero here.
If I go and check the logs, you can see it started and it also connected to the Kafka broker that we
have provided. With this
all our microservices started successfully. As a next step,
let's try to test a few scenarios.
First, I'll make sure I'm testing some get APIs inside my accounts,
I'll try to invoke these contact info and you can see I got an output and these properties are related
to the prod profile.
So this confirms our application started with the production profile.
Let me go to cards PermitAll
here
I will try to invoke the Java version API available inside the cards
microservice.
I got unsuccessful outputs.
Let me go to the loans.
Here I will try to invoke the build-info API under  loans.
So this is also working fine.
As a next step, I will try to create a new account. For the same,
first, I need to get an access token by mentioning the character secret value and apart from secret
value, we should also make sure we have mentioned the correct keycloak URL port which is 80.
So let me try to get the access token.
I got an access token and using the same I'm going to invoke this API and this is going to create a
new account behind the scenes.
I got an output saying that 201 and account created successfully.
As a next step,
I'll go to the cards.
I need to invoke the cards API.
But before that let me take the secret value from this request.
So this is the secret value.
I'll go to cards.
I'll mention the same secret value inside this request as well and post that I will change this port
from 7080 to 80.
And now let me get the access token.
Once I got the access token, I will try to invoke this API and I should get a successful response.
Now let me do the same for loans API as well.
Here also I will mention the correct client secret followed by I will update the access token URL port number
to 80 and try to get the access token.
The same access token I will use and send the request to the loans API to create a new loan based upon
a given mobile number.
So I got a successful response.
As a final step, we can try to invoke these fetchCustomerDetails API for these mobile number and
with that we should get all the accounts, loans and cards information.
So let me try to invoke these API.
So I got a response inside the response,
I only have accounts information but not the loans and cards.
Seems there is a timeout issue inside my local system, so let me try to send the API one more time.
And this time you can see I have the information around loans and cards as well.
The complete setup of our microservices inside Kubernetes cluster is working perfectly even with the
help of Helm charts.
And this time we also set up other required components like Kafka, Grafana, Prometheus. As a next step,
let's try to validate few things inside the Grafana, for the same, we need to make sure we have exposed
the Grafana network at the Port 3000.
Like you can see as of now, I expose the Grafana network at the Port 3000.
That's why I'm able to see these outputs saying that handling connection for 3000.
So here I will try to refresh this page and I'll go to the Explore option.
First, I will look for the logs information. For the same,
I'll go to loki and select one of the label, which is container and post that I will select the
container name as gateway server and run this query and this will give all the logs present inside my
gateway server.
So these are the logs.
If I try to click on any of the log, I should be able to have a link to the tempo for this trace id.
So if I try to click on this, I will get the complete distributed tracing details.
This confirms loki is working, tempo is working and the integration between loki and tempo also
working. As a final step,
I can confirm Prometheus as well.
For the same, let me go to explore and select the Prometheus.
And under the metric we may have many metrics, but let me look for metric with a value up.
So at last I have a metric with the name up.
Let me select this and post that
I will select container and run this query and this will show me the graph for last six hours.
Let me change this to last 15 minutes and change this graph style to tackle lines and you will be able
to see a beautiful graph explaining about my metric uptime for all the running containers inside my
Kubernetes.
So this confirms our Prometheus integration with Grafana is also working.
I'm super, super happy with this because we are able to successfully set up our microservices along
with the supporting components inside a Kubernetes cluster.
Hooray!
You are one of the few developers who know about all this process.
You should feel proud about yourself.
You have learned so much inside this course and all of them we are trying to explore by doing lot many
practicals by taking a Kubernetes cluster.
In the coming sections,
I'm also going to discuss on how to set up all these environments in a proper cloud environment.
I hope you are also happy.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.