Now, inside this lecture, let me show you how to roll back to a desired previous working version with
the help of Helm.
The beauty of helm rollback is it is going to rollback your entire Kubernetes cluster components to
the previous desired state.
Whereas with Kubectl, if you want to roll back, you need to roll back component by component.
As of now, I may change only inside the gateway server.
What if you have made changes inside multiple microservices. Regardless of how many changes you have
done in various microservices with the help of the rollback command also is going to be a single command.
So to get started around these rollback command, first let me introduce to the helm History Command.
So this Helm History Command will show you the history of upgrades or installations happen for a particular
helm chart.
So what is the release name that we have for our microservices?
The release name is Easy Bank.
If I try to run this command, it will show me all the installations or deployments happen First.
Under the revision one installation is completed and post that using revision
two we have deployed the tag name s12 and we realized we made a mistake and at last we made againt
one more change by updating the tag name to the S11 And finally we did one more helm upgrade and that
is why we have here three versions.
And right now revision three has a status as deployed.
That means this is the revision right now deployed into my Kubernetes cluster.
So now think like we want to roll back to the previous working version, which is revision one where
my gateway server is going to be secured properly.
So for this, the command is going to be super simple.
The command that we need to run to roll back to the previous revision is, helm rollback
and what is your release name?
The release name we have here is Easy bank and what is the revision number to which you want to roll
back?
The revision number that I want to roll back is one.
So let me execute this command.
And with that, with a single command, the rollback was a success.
I can confirm the same by going into the Kubernetes dashboard.
Inside my Kubernetes dashboard, I'll go to the pods and I'll open the new pod that is right now getting
created.
You can see under the Gateway server right now, if you go and check the events here, you will be able
to see a new event where we'll be able to see a new Docker image with the name s14.
So this is the Docker image right now being deployed into my Kubernetes cluster.
So let me go to the logs and my gateway server is trying to get started.
Let me wait for a few seconds here.
After few seconds, my Gateway server application started successfully.
I can validate the changes inside my postman.
This time I should get a 401 error if I try to invoke this API and you can see I'm getting the 401 error.
Hooray.
The rollback is also completed with a single helm command.
Now if I try to run the command, which is helm history easy bank this time you should be able to see
a revision number four.
But the comments is rollback to one.
So this is a very clear information to the person who is trying to roll back in future.
Or if you want to understand the history of the deployments happened for a particular release, which
is easy bank in our scenario.
So I hope this is clear.
Now let me go back to the values.yaml and here I'm going to revert to the s14 because I need to check
in these files into the GitHub repo. With this
I hope this is all clear to you.
Thank you.
And I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.