Inside this lecture, I'm going to quickly revise all the helm commands that we have discussed.
The very first command that we have here is, helm create command.
With the help of these helm create command, we can create a blank chart or a default helm chart with
a given name.
So whenever you generate a helm chart with the help of Helm create inside the chart folder, you should
be able to see charts.yaml, values.yaml charts folder and templates folder.
And the next command that we have here is helm dependencies build.
So like we discussed, with the help of this command, we can build a specific helm chart and if there
are any dependencies defined in that chart, all the dependencies charts are going to be compiled under
copied under the charts folder.
The next command we have is helm install command and to this install command we need to provide what
is the name of the release and followed by what is the chart name or the folder name where your chart
is present.
So whenever we run this helm install command all the deployment instructions that you have provided
inside your chart and your dependent charts are going to be installed by the helm behind the scenes.
And for some reason, if you want to deploy new changes, then you can update your helm chart and recompile
it and post that,
you can run the helm upgrade command and whenever you want to roll back to a previous working release
or previous working revision.
First, you need to understand the history of your helm installations, but at the same you can use
the helm History command along with the name of the release.
Once you clear to which revision you want to roll back, you can run the helm rollback command by providing
the release name and the revision number to which you want to roll back.
If you don't mention any revision number, then Helm is going to roll back to the immediate previous
revision number.
And in the scenarios where you want to completely uninstall or delete all your microservices from your
Kubernetes cluster, you can run the helm uninstall command by providing the what is the release name
that you have used.
And the next command that we have here is Helm template, and with the help of Helm Template Command,
we can try to render the all the Kubernetes manifest files that your helm is going to use behind the
scenes whenever the actual installation is going to happen.
So this will help you to debug any issues.
And the last command here we have is helm ls, and this is going to list all the releases that you
have done with the help of Helm.
I hope you are clear.
Please refer this slide whenever you want to quickly refresh your helm knowledge before I try to close
this lecture.
I also want to confirm you that I checked in all the helm files that we have discussed into this GitHub
repo under this section 16.
If you go inside that there is a helm folder and inside that we have all the helm charts that we have
discussed.
So please leverage them if you want to try helm inside your local system or inside any cloud environment.
In the coming sections, we are also going to deploy all these helm charts into the cloud environment.
So that it is also going to be useful information for you to understand how the actual cloud environment
deployment will happen.
Most of the stuff is going to be very similar to what we have done inside the local system, except
that your Kubernetes cluster capacity will be more inside the cloud.
With this, we can conclude this section related to help.
I'm assuming your super, super clear about the helm.
Please take a break and we can meet again in the next section.
Thank you.
Bye.