In the previous lecture, I told you that in order to secure our microservices, we need to use a component
called Oauth2.
What is this
Oauth2?
Oauth2 is a security standard or a security specification that any organization can follow to secure
their web applications, mobile applications, or microservices, regardless of what is the type of
application that an organization develops, they can leverage these Oauth2 specifications to secure their
applications.
Before I try to give you a quick introduction about what is Oauth2, first let me try to explain you,
what are the problems that Oauth2 trying to solve?
Because before oauth2 specifications everyone they used to use basic authentication.
So you may also have a question like why should we use Oauth2 framework for implementing security,
why can't we use simple basic authentication?
To answer this,
first, let me try to explain what is basic authentication and what are its drawbacks.
Back in the early days of web invention, all websites they usually ask for credentials of an end
user inside an HTML form. So the end user will enter his credentials.
The same will be sent over to the backend server inside the backend server using the credentials provided
by the end user, the authentication will be completed and after the successful authentication, the
backend server is going to generate a session value and the same it is going to store inside a cookie
of the browser.
So as long as the session is active, the user can access the any protected resources and URLs.
So this is how the basic authentication used to work.
The drawbacks of this approach is backend server will have both business logic and authentication logic
tightly coupled.
So if there is a change that you need to make inside the authentication logic, then definitely you
need to make sure that it is not going to impact your business logic.
So there has to be enough
regression has to be done. Because both the business logic and the authentication logic is deployed into
a single server.
Moreover, this approach is not mobile friendly or REST API friendly.
And the second drawback of basic authentication is, it does not accommodate or it does not have a proper
solution to grant temporary access to your information to the third party clients. For example, think
like I'm storing my photos inside Google photos and one of the third party website
they offer very good features, like if I can import my photos from Google photos into these website,
they will allow me to edit the photos to prepare a collage from the photos so I can do many inside these
third party website.
But like you can see here, there is a challenge how to bring the photos that I'm storing inside Google
photos into this website.
If we follow basic authentication approach, then we need to provide our own Google credentials to this
website.
We need to believe this website folks and we need to provide our own credentials under the assumption
that they are not going to misuse our credentials.
So this is a very serious drawback.
Whereas in Oauth2 framework, we have a proper solution on how to temporarily grant access to the Google
photos to the third party website without sharing my own Google photo credentials, I'm going to talk
more about these in the coming lectures.
But as of now I'm assuming you are clear about why basic authentication is not a good consideration
these days and what are the challenges that we have.
Now let's try to understand what are the problems that Oauth2 trying to solve.
We all know that Google has many products like Gmail, Google Maps, YouTube, photos, Google Drive.
So under Google there are many web applications or mobile applications available providing various features
to the end users.
Have you ever wondered like, how come Google let me use the same account in all its products?
Regardless of what is the website of Google that you are using or what is the mobile app of Google
that you are trying to use.
If I go to the Gmail and try to login, I need to enter my Gmail credentials.
If I try to use another product of Google, like YouTube or Google photos or Google Maps there also
I need to enter the same credentials which I have used for my Gmail login.
Do you know how this is possible?
This is possible because behind the scenes, Google uses the Oauth2 framework and by following the Oauth2 recommendation,
they separated all the authentication and authorization logic into a separate component called authorization
server or authentication server.
So whenever an end user trying to login into any of the Google products, they are going to send the
credentials of the end user to the same auth server.
So from this, I'm assuming it is pretty clear for you one of the best recommendation of Oauth2 framework
is, to separate all your authentication
and authorization logic into a separate component. So that regardless of how many applications
you have or how many microservices that you have inside your organization, you can always have your
security related logic inside a single component.
And if there is a change that you need to make, then the change is going to be in a single place.
So this is the very first problem that Oauth2 is trying to solve.
Now let's try to understand what is the second problem that Oauth2 is trying to solve. For the same,
I'm going to give you a small demo.
I came to our favorite website, which is StackOverflow.
Like, you know, StackOverflow is all the developer's favorite website.
Inside this website, let's assume you don't have any account
as of now. You're trying to use this website where you are trying to post a question. For the same,
you're going to click on this sign up button.
As soon as you click on the sign up button, you can see there are multiple approaches on how I can
create an account inside this website.
The most basic approach is I can enter my name,
what is the email,
what is the password.
And with that a account will be created behind the scenes in the StackOverflow.
But apart from these approach, I can also sign up with Facebook, GitHub and Google.
So here you may have a question like how the StackOverflow will know, what are the credentials of my
Google, GitHub or Facebook.
The answer is, StackOverflow does not need to know your actual credentials.
With the help of Oauth2 framework, they can get your basic details like what is your name,
what is your email.
So here, let me try to sign up with GitHub.
So here I'm trying to click on this sign up with GitHub.
As soon as I click on this button you can see I will be redirected to the GitHub web page.
So you can see this is the gitHub.com domain.
And here I need to enter my GitHub credentials like I'm trying to enter my email and password.
So here it is pretty clear I'm not sharing my own credentials of GitHub to the StackOverflow because
I'm entering these credentials inside the GitHub website, which means I'm not sharing to any third
party web applications.
As soon as I click on sign in button if my credentials are correct, you can see I am landed back onto
the stack overflow.
Now my StackOverflow has my basic details like this is my email, this is my display name, which I have
stored inside the GitHub. Which means the resources that I stored inside the GitHub server now is shared
to the StackOverflow with the help of the Oauth2 framework.
And in the process I didn't share my credentials to the StackOverflow.
I entered my own credentials to the GitHub and behind the scenes GitHub gave my basic details to the
StackOverflow and it also going to issue an access token and using this access token in future, maybe
after two days or three days, if I came back into this website, the behind the scenes is that StackOverflow
can try to send a request to the GitHub and try to log in me automatically with the help of the access
token.
So what is happening here is, the GitHub is trying to give a temporary access token with a limited access
to the StackOverflow.
I didn't share my master credentials to the StackOverflow and at the same time GitHub also didn't give
an access token using which the StackOverflow can do anything on my GitHub.
It has given its access token, which has a very limited privileges like my stackoverflow can read what
is my name,
what is my email,
that's it.
Apart from reading these details, the StackOverflow website cannot perform any other operation inside
my resources in the GitHub.
It cannot create repositories.
So those are advanced privileges which GitHub did not give.
It is only given a very basic privilege which is reading the profile details like email and my display
name.
So this is one of the problem that Oauth2 is trying to solve.
Without sharing our credentials to the third party applications, we can still provide a temporary access
to them to access the resources that I stored inside a resource server like GitHub, Google or any other
application which has implemented Oauth2 inside their system.
I hope now you are clear.
What is basic authentication,
what are its drawbacks and what are the problems that Oauth2 is trying to solve.
In the next lecture, let me try to give you a quick introduction about what is Oauth2.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.