We decided to secure our gateway server with the help of client credentials
grant type flow inside Oauth2 framework.
To get started with the same first, we need to set up our own authorization server with the help of
tools like Keycloak.
For the same, I came to the website keycloak.org.
Here on this web page you can click on this, Get started.
And here there are various options on how we can set up authorization server with the help of keycloak.
Since inside our local system we have Docker installed and we also have Docker compose file for our
microservices.
It will be a good idea to get started with the help of Docker.
For the same, I'm going to click on this Docker option here.
Inside this page we have details on how to start the keyclock server.
So this is the command.
So let me copy this command.
Now inside that terminal, I'm going to run the same command, which is docker run -p and post
that we have a port mapping.
But here there is a problem with this port mapping.
We know we are following the same port mapping for our accounts
microservice also. So I'm fine
keyclock starting at the port 8080 internally inside the Docker network.
So I'm not going to change this, but I'm not going to expose keycloak to the outside world at the
port 8080. Because I'm already doing that for accounts microservice.
If I do the same for keycloak, then definitely there will be port to conflict error.
So with that reason I'm going to change this port number to 7080.
So from my local system I can access the keycloak server at the port 7080. Before this port mapping,
I'm also going to give -d, which will start my keycloak container in a detached mode.
And after the port mapping you can see we are trying to provide some environment variables with the
help of these -e.
.
The very first environment variable is KEYCLOAK_ADMIN.
So what is the username that we want to set for our keycloak auth server which can be used by the admin
to create the clients or to set up the auth server.
So the username I'm going to keep it as admin and very similarly the admin password
I'm going to set it as admin only. After this environment variables we have the docker image name of
keycloak after the Docker image name,
you should also give this command which is start -dev.
So with this we are telling I'm trying to run the keycloak server in the dev mode.
So behind the scenes the keycloak is going to have some internal database using which we can store
all the user credentials and the client credentials.
But in production environments we should have some dedicated database configured for the keycloak auth
server.
So I hope you are clear.
So now let me try to run this command.
With this,
you can see a new container started inside my local system.
I can also confirm the same by going to the Docker desktop.
Inside my Docker desktop, you can see there is a running container with the name keycloak and it is
exposing the traffic at the port 7080.
Now as a next step, I'll try to access the keycloak at the port localhost 7080.
So this is my keycloak home page.
Here I need to click on this administration console and it is going to ask me what are the admin credentials?
We need to use the same credentials that we have mentioned inside the Docker run command.
So let me use the same credentials which are admin and the password also is going to be admin.
Now I'm clicking on this sign in button and you can see this is my keycloak admin console. Using this
admin console
only my admin of the auth server can create various clients users, so there is a lot of functionality
available inside this auth server.
We're going to explore more about this ad server in the coming lectures, but for now I just wanted
to highlight you about what is this master realm.
So you can see there is only one realm as of now which is master and if needed we can also create
more realms inside the ad server.
So what is a realm inside any ad server like Keycloak realm is a boundary where you want to create
set of client credentials or user credentials.
So things like this is like an environment. By default
keycloak is going to provide a realm with the name master, but if needed, you can create more realms
like dev, qa, prod. So based upon your requirements because the end users are the clients, they are
not going to use the same credentials across various environments.
We can't force our qa team to use the same credentials like we have inside the production.
That's why
so to overcome these challenges, we have the concepts like realm inside the auth server.
As of now, we have only one realm which is master.
Throughout this course we are going to use the same.
I hope you are clear with this setup.
If you are facing some issues, please make sure you have at least a Java 17 inside your local system.
Otherwise the keycloak is not going to start because the minimum Java version is Java 17.
With this, we successfully set up auth server inside our Easy Bank microservices network.
Did you see how easy it is. Behind the scenes
this auth server has a lot of functionality based upon the OpenID and OAuth2 standards.
We are going to explore more about this in the coming lectures.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.