As of now, inside our gateway server, we are just checking if the client application is authenticated
or not.
That means we are only performing the authentication but not the authorization.
What if you have a scenario where you want to only process the request,
if the client application has certain roles or authorities or privileges.
So in such scenarios, instead of these authenticated, you need to invoke a method which is has role
to this has role method you can pass
what is the role that you are expecting which your client should have configured inside the auth server.
So here for all accounts related APIs, I'm going to expect my client should have a role with the name
accounts.
Very similarly, I can configure role based access for cards as well and loans as well.
But instead of accounts here, I'm going to keep the role name as cards and post that under loans.
I'm going to mention loans role name.
So with this now I have enforced the authorization inside my gateway server.
Now, as a next step, we need to configure these roles to our client applications.
So where do we need to configure those inside the auth server.
So let me go to the auth server.
Inside the auth server, let's go to the clients and under the clients here you will be able to see the
client which you have created.
So please click on that.
Now here there are two tabs like roles and service account roles.
Since this client is an client which is following the client credentials grant type, that means this
is also another application.
This is not an end user.
So in such scenarios we should not configure under roles, we should configure under service accounts
roles.
Here you can see there is a button assign roles, but I don't have any role that I want to assign.
So let me close this and I can click on these Realm roles.
So let me click on that and post that
I'm going to click on this create role.
And here first I'll create a role with the name, accounts and description
I'll just keep it as Accounts Role and post that I'm going to click on the save button.
Intentionally I'm not creating loans and cards.
After doing some negative testing, we are going to create those roles as well.
Now I'll go to clients and I'll open Easy Bank Call center CC and go to the service account roles and click
on this button Assign role.
This time you should be able to see the role with the name ACCOUNTS.
So let me select the same and click on this assign.
Now, if I go to the request where we are trying to get an access token, this time I'll try to get
a fresh access token.
So let me click on the send button.
So I got a new access token.
Let me take this.
Once I copied this access token, I will go to that jwt.io website and here I'm going to paste the same.
So let's try to see where the roles information is coming inside the access token. Under the payload
if you can scroll down, there is a data with the key realm access under this realm access key, we
have another object and inside this object we have one more key with the name roles under these roles,
you can see we have list of roles assigned to this client.
And here we have our own custom role that we have created with the name accounts.
All the remaining roles are default roles that are available inside the keycloak, but we are more interested
about these accounts role.
So now it is confirmed that the role information is coming inside the access token.
But I should write a logic inside my resource server or inside my gateway server to extract this role
information and convey the same to the spring security framework to use and validate my authorization
rules that I have configured. For the same inside the same package of config.
I'm going to create a new class and the class name that I want to do here is keycloak role converter
because this class is going to help me to extract the roles that I'm getting from the keycloak into
the format that spring security framework can understand.
So let me create this class.
Now in this class, I need to make sure that it is implementing a interface with the name Converter.
Let me try to import this JWT, so please make sure you are exporting these JWT present inside the Spring
Security Oauth2 Library.
Once we added these implementation details, it will expect you to override an abstract method.
So let me click on this implement methods and override this method which is convert().
So I'm trying to click on this okay button.
Now you can see I got a new override method where I need to write the logic to read the role information
from the JWT access token that I'm going to receive and convert the same into the collection of granted
authority.
So GrantedAuthority
Is an interface available inside the spring security framework.
Whenever we want to convey the role's information or privileged information, we need to make sure we
are sending those details with these interface formats only.
So inside this method I'm going to paste a few lines of code post that we can try to discuss.
I'm trying to save some time here.
You can also try to refer this code inside the GitHub repo.
If you see here,
first, I'm trying to invoke the method, getClaims() with the help of this Jwt class.
The purpose of this getClaims() method is it will give you access to the payload data available inside
your access token. Post that I'm going to invoke the get method because this getClaims() is of type Map.
And inside this getClaims map, I'm going to invoke the get method with the key as real access.
If you see here inside our access token, we have a key with the name realm_access.
So whenever I try to access that, I will get the value assigned to this realm_access.
But this value also is of type Map because this is a key and these are the values.
That's why I'm trying to assign that to the Map of type String and the object.
For some reason, if realm access is empty, that means I'm going to return an empty ArrayList.
Otherwise, from these realm_access, I'm again going to invoke the get method with the key as roles. Inside
this realm access,
like I said, we have a map and there is a key with the name roles.
That's why I'm trying to pass this key name which will give me all these values available here.
So once I have all these roles available, I'm trying to use this stream API and using the stream API,
I'm trying to use the map method.
So what is the map method is going to do?
Map method is going to iterate all the values available inside this stream.
We are going to get four different values, but we are more interested about these accounts.
The stream is going to iterate all these four values and inside this map method we are going to take
each of the role name and we are prefixing the value role_ for each of the role name available
inside the roles map.
Why I'm trying to assign these prefix role underscore because whenever we use this has_role method
inside the spring security framework, internally it is going to use a prefix which is role underscore.
You can see inside the documentation
also, if we configure the role as user internally, the spring security will convert that to role underscore
user.
Since we have this prefix, we need to make sure inside the converter we are prefixing the same, but
inside the security config we should not add that because behind the scenes, inside the framework,
the spring security is going to add the same.
Now, after adding this prefix name, my role name object is going to still be a string, but my spring
security cannot understand the roles if I pass as a string, so I need to pass it as an object of simple
GrantedAuthority.
So this simple granted authority is an implementation of this interface which is granted authority. Inside
this SimpleGrantedAuthority, there is a constructor which accepts the role name in the format of
string and post that it is going to return the object of SimpleGrantedAuthority by using this role
information.
So the same constructor I'm trying to invoke with the help of these method reference.
So with the new operator, I'm trying to create the default constructor available inside this object.
So first, with this map logic, we are going to append a prefix value for each role and post that again
I'm going to iterate each role and convert that into a simple granted authority and at last the entire
stream
I'm trying to convert that into a list which I'm going to return from this method.
Now we have successfully created a RoleConverter, but how to communicate about this RoleConverter
to the configurations that we have done inside the SecurityConfig.java class. For the same inside
this class, I'm going to create a new small method here.
Let me paste a new method.
Like you can see here, the method name is grantedAuthoritiesExtractor().
We can make this method as private as well.
So this private method return type is going to be this value which is Converter of Jwt Mono of abstract
authentication token.
Inside this method you can see first I'm trying to create an object of Jwt authentication converter.
Using this JwtAuthenticationConverter object,
I'm trying to invoke a method which is setJwtGrantedAuthoritiesConverter, which means I need
to tell where I have written my logic to convert the roles present inside the JWT token into a granted
authorities format.
Since we have written all that logic inside the Keycloak role converter, we need to pass the object
of the same with the help of this new keycloak role
converter.
At last I need to pass this JwtAuthenticationConverter object to the constructor of ReactiveJwtAuthenticationConverterAdapter.
.
So from this return statement it is going to return an object of this data type.
So once we have created this method, we need to mention this method inside the configurations.
As of now you can see I'm trying to use the default configurations for my jwt method.
That means I'm telling to the spring security framework, please go with your default assumptions and
I don't have any role specific information.
But now, since we have role specific information also to be processed by the spring security framework,
we need to make sure we are removing these customizer with the defaults and post that we need to write
a lambda expression by creating some lambda variable with the name JWT spec and I'm going to use the
same lambda variable name using this lambda variable, I'm going to invoke the method which is jwtAuthenticationConverter.
To this jwtAuthenticationConverter,
I need to pass the method which is GrantedAuthoritiesExtractor.
So this way I have established the link about my key role converter inside my spring security configurations.
So with this we should be good.
Let me save this changes and do a build in the next lecture.
We can try to test these changes.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.