Are you excited to see the authorization demo inside our Gateway server.
I know you're super excited, for the same without any delays
let me go to the postman.
Inside the postman,
first I will try to create a new account with the help of these accounts api create.
But this time we need to make sure we are changing the mobile number because we already created a account
with this mobile number.
So let me change this
6872688 and post that, I'll go to the authorization tab and here I will try to click on this new access
token.
So behind the scenes, my keycloak auth server will attach the roles information
also to this access token, I can click on this use token and post that
I'm going to click on this send button.
You can see I am getting the 201, which is account created successfully.
Now I'll go to the cards API,
here also, I will try to create cards information with the same mobile number, but do you think I'll get
a successful response?
So let's see what it is going to happen.
So I'm going to click on this new access token post that I'll click on this proceed.
I will use the new access token that I received, and now I'm clicking on this send button.
Boom !
you can see I'm getting 403 error.
That means I'm authorized.
That's why I'm not getting 401 error, but I'm getting 403 because I don't have enough privileges.
How to fix this issue.
We need to provide enough privileges to the client application.
For the same, I'll go to the Keycloak administration console.
Here I'll go to the realm roles and create a new role with the name cards and the description
I'll just keep it as cards role.
Let me save this and post that
I'll go to the clients,
I'll open this easy bank call center,
I'll go to the service account roles and here click on this assign role and I'm going to assign the
new role, which is cards with this,
now my client application should be able to invoke the cards API as well.
So before I try to test this API, let me go to the authorization and try to get a new access token.
This new access token will have the roles information related to the cards as well.
So let me copy these and press on this use token here under the JWT website, I'm going to paste the
same and this time you should be able to see two roles like accounts and cards.
So this confirms our cards role information is present inside the access token.
So now let me click on the send button.
You can see this time I'm getting a successful response.
As a next step, I'll go to the loans.
First, I'll try to invoke the loans API with the mobile number as 688.
Here, I will try to get an access token and this access token will not have the roles information,
which is loans.
So that's why I will get a 403 forbidden error here.
You know the drill.
First we need to go to the realm roles and here click on this create role and create the loan, which
is loans.
Please make sure you are following the exact case sensitive details.
Otherwise the authorization will fail.
In the description I'm going to mention loans description.
I'm going to save this role.
I'll go to the clients and open easy bank call center and go to the service account roles.
And here I'll click on this assign role and select the loans.
So now let me assign this role to the client application.
Now I'll go to the postman,
here first, I'll try to get a new access token.
Click on this Proceed Use token as a next step,
I will try to submit these requests with the help of this send button.
You can see I'm getting a successful response. With this
I'm assuming you are super clear about how to enforce authentication and authorization with the help
of OAuth2 framework and authorization server like Keycloak.
So I have defined my own security requirements.
In real world, your requirements can be more complex, but the approach is going to be same.
If you want to learn more about spring security, my request is to enroll my spring security course.
With this, we can conclude the client credentials grant type flow.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.