Now inside this lecture, let me show you the second approach that we have to read the properties,
and this second approach will help you to read the environment properties defined inside the environment
where you have deployed your microservices.
And here you may have a question like why do we need to define some properties as environment variables?
Why can't we directly define them inside the application Yaml file?
That's a very valid question.
Like I said before, some sensitive information like passwords or any other information.
We can't define them inside the application.yml file or inside any other place where it will expose
my sensitive information.
With that reason, it is always advisable to define the sensitive configuration details as the environment
variables only, so that no one can see those values because they will not have access to your production
server, only the server admins they will have access.
This way you're trying to secure your application whenever they are dealing with the sensitive configurations.
Like we discussed before,
this approach involves an interface with the name environment.
So first let's try to autowire the environment interface to this AccountsController.
So here I'm going to mention private post that environment interface and the variable name is going
to be environment on top of this field,
I'm going to mention Autowired annotation with this
now, all the environment details that I have defined inside my local system can be accessed with the
help of these environment variable.
To demo the same, I'm going to create a small REST API.
Let me go to the end of this file.
first, I'll try to copy the entire REST API related to the build info post that I'm going to paste
the same here inside this class.
Now I'm going to create a new REST API that will return the what is the Java version that my microservice
right now is using.
So inside my local system or in any Java developer system will always install the Java and will set
a environment variable with the name JAVA_HOME.
With the help of these environment interface, I'll try to read that environment property related to
Java version and the same I'll return to the client applications whoever is trying to invoke my REST
API.
So first I'll try to change the method name to get Java version.
And similarly I'm going to change the REST API path to java-version.
So with this I'm good from REST API perspective, but here after making these REST API changes inside
the body, as of now I'm sending the build version field information instead.
I'm going to use the environment variable that we have against this environment variable,
I'm going to invoke the method getProperty() since we have injected a wrong environment interface.
So let me go to the import statements here and the import statements.
If you see the environment right now we are importing is, from the hibernate, but we don't want that
hibernate related environment.
We want the environment present inside the spring core framework.
So let me try to press Ctrl space here so you can see we have the interface with the package
org.springframework.core.env.
So please make sure you are injecting the same into this controller class.
So once I define this and imported these into this class, I can go to the Java method and here now
I should be able to invoke the method which is getPproperty(). And to this getProperty() method I'm going
to pass the environment variable name regarding the Java version.
So these details we store inside a environment variable with the name JAVA_HOME.
So now my REST API is capable to read the Java home environment variable inside my local system and
send the same as a response to the client applications.
As a next step, I should also update the summary here.
Like first I'll change this to get Java version.
Post this
I'll also change the description details to get Java version details that is installed into accounts
microservice.
With this we should be good.
There is no need to change anything inside the API responses.
Let me do a build once the build is completed.
If needed, please restart your application.
I'm also restarting my application to be on safe side. So let me restart in debug mode and I'll go
to the postman.
Here inside the Postman I'm going to click on this java-version  API.
You can see here this is a complete path api/java-version and this is going to support
Http get method.
As soon as I click on the send button, I'm getting a response where my Java home is installed.
So inside the response, since I have used the SDK command to install the Java, it is simply giving
the Java home folder location, but ideally inside the production servers we will directly install the
JDK by downloading from the official website.
.
And in such scenarios it is going to give you the complete folder location along with the Java version
name.
So this output should be fine for me since I just want to show you the demo of how to use the environment
interface to read the properties of environment details.
I can also show you one more environment property demo. Inside my local system
I also have Maven installed, so whenever we have the Maven install, we are going to have the environment
property set with the name maven_home.
So after adding these property details, I'm trying to save the changes and do a build.
Once the build is completed, I'll go to my postman.
Here I am trying to click on the send button.
You can see it is giving me a location where my Apache maven is installed.
So from this folder location I can easily understand the version
right now we have installed is 3.8.6.
This way we can read any type of environment property inside your Java code with the help of environment
interface.
So let me revert these changes back to Java home and do a build.
Once the build is completed, I'm going to test again and here it is showing me the Java installation
folder location.
So this should be fine for me, though
it is not showing my Java version installed.
Like I said in production environment, it is going to work. With this,
I'm assuming your super clear about the second approach that we have used to read the properties, which
is with the help of environment interface.
Please note that when we are using this approach we can only read the environment properties but not
the properties that you have defined inside your application.yml.
So this approach also has disadvantages
like you can only read one property at a time and at the same time you need to hardcode the property
key name inside your Java code.
And this approach is also going to work only if you have 1 or 2 properties.
If you have higher number of environment properties that you want to read, then definitely this approach
is not recommended.
We'll see some advanced options that we have in the coming lectures, but now we should be good with
this approach 2. Inside the next lecture,
let's try to discuss the approach three that we have.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.