As of now, we have updated the accounts microservice with the concepts like spring boot profiles and
we have introduced many properties inside the application.yml file and we read the same properties
by three different REST APIs inside accounts microservice.
Now I'm going to give you an assignment.
Are you ready for the assignment?
The assignment is you need to make very similar changes inside cards and loans microservice.
And this is going to be super, super easy.
If you have questions like what is the property name,
what is the property values that I have to use, please refer the code present inside the GitHub repo.
If you see inside the GitHub repo eazybytes/microservice project.
Under this repo there is a section six and inside this I have uploaded the folder which is
v1-springboot.
Under this version one spring boot folder, we have three different microservices accounts we already
completed.
If you have any questions around cards, what type of properties we have to use, like I said, please
use the same properties like we created for accounts microservice, but try to give different phone
numbers, different contact details and different message.
So you can also get those details by going into this GitHub repo and look at the application.yml file.
And if you have any questions you can always refer to the code present inside this GitHub repo
and complete the assignment.
My sincere request is to complete this assignment so that you are getting enough
hands-On.
I'm trying to explain with one microservice and if you do the similar changes inside the two microservice,
that is going to bring lot of practice for you and these concepts will be entered into your subconscious
memory.
So even if someone is trying to take an interview by waking you up in the midnight, you will be able
to answer all the questions because you are doing lot of practice inside this course.
So please put an effort here and try to implement the changes inside the other microservices.
If you faced with some issues, don't get demotivated.
Anyway, I'm going to cover the code changes inside the cards and loans microservice very quickly inside
the next lecture.
I hope you will be successful at this assignment.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.