Okay
I am assuming you are successful at the assignment.
If not, don't worry.
Anyway, I'm going to cover all the code changes inside the cards and loans microservice right now inside
this lecture.
First let's go to the loans microservice. Like we know,
first we need to go to the LoansController class.
So let me go to the LoansController class.
First I have done the changes related to the autowiring of these environments and LocalContactInfoDto which
I have created.
On top of that, I'm trying to read the build.version property with the help of @Value.
And similarly, I have created a new constructor inside the LoansController and I'm trying to inject
this property which is ILoanService.
After making these initial autowiring related changes, I have created three different APIs towards
the end.
Like you can see, the first API is related to the build-info which will give the response what build
version we are trying to use right now with the help of this Java variable build version and accordingly,
I have mentioned this operation and ApiResponses details as well which will be useful for the
REST API documentation with the swagger UI.
Now moving on to the next API which will help us to read the JAVA_HOME environment variable.
And the Api path is very similar to Accounts Microservice java-version.
Very similarly
at last we have contact-info API where we are trying to read all the properties that defined inside
the application.yml by populating into the object of LoansContactInfoDto.
So let's try to see what is present inside these
LoansContactInfoDto. So here since inside the application.yml we are going to have a prefix as loans
for Loans Microservice.
We need to make sure we are using the same.
After that everything is going to be same.
Like it is going to be a record class and it is going to accept different fields like message, contact
details and on call support by following the data type based upon the properties that we have defined
inside the application.yml.
Now to activate these configuration properties inside the loans application class, we need to make
sure we are mentioning this annotation which is @EnableConfigurationProperties and to this
make sure we are passing the Dto class of
LoansContactInfoDto.
If you go to the resources folder, I have created two new Yaml files which is application_prod
and application_qa.yml file.
First inside the application.yml we have the properties related to the loans microservice like
build version loans message, loans contact details and loans on call support.
I just try to kept everything same except the values of this message,
contact details and on call support. Post that we need to import the new config files that we have created
which is application_qa.yaml and application_prod.yml.
And as of now you can see I'm trying to activate a profile qa by hardcoding the value inside the application.yml file.
.
Now let's go and validate the application_prod.yml.
You can see I'm mentioning to the spring boot framework to consider this
whenever someone is trying to activate a profile prod and you can see I have the build version and other
properties which has prefixed as loans, the same kind of setup is present inside the application_qa.yml.
.
So these are the changes that we need to do inside the loans microservice.
Most of the changes are very similar to accounts micro service.
Now let's try to test these APIs.
For the same I'm going to the loans application and starting the application in debug mode.
Now inside the postman under the loans folder, you have the APIs like build-info, java-version and
contact info.
So first let me try to invoke this build-info.
So I'm trying to invoke this since right now the qa profile is activated.
We should get the output 2.0.
So this is working fine.
The Java version anyway will come based upon that JAVA_HOME path setup inside my local system.
So that is what coming inside the output. Now going to the contact info.
Here we'll get the details from the qa profile.
Like you can see this is the message from the qa profile and these are the contact details and on call
support details in the qa profile.
Now let's try to quickly try to activate a profile of production using externalized configuration.
For the same,
I'm going to stop this server and right click on the loans application, select this Modify Run configurations
and maximize this.
Here I'm going to mention the property which is --spring.profiles.active=prod.
.
I'm just trying to activate the prod profile, so let me apply these changes and click on
ok.
And start the application again in debug mode.
Now we should get the response from the production profile properties.
I'm just trying to invoke these contact info.
You can see I'm getting the prod related properties inside the response.
The same you can confirm with the build info where we will get the 1.0 as an output.
With this,
all the loans related APIs are working perfectly.
Now, let me stop this application and try to show you what I have done inside the cards microservice, inside
the cards Microservices
also, it's the same story
first you will go to the CardsController inside the CardsController, first you will do all the
autowiring and dependency injection related changes at the top of the class post that you are going to create
three different REST APIs.
The very first one, which is going to return the build information based upon the build version Java
variable, followed by the API, which is going to return the environment variable with the name
JAVA_HOME and at last we have the contact info REST API, which is going to return all the details
defined inside this object CardsInfoDto.
So this Dto is also a record class.
Please make sure this has the prefix as cards post that you will go to the CardsApplication and you
will mention these
@EnableConfigurationProperties annotation along with the CardsContactInfoDto class.
After making all these changes, the next set of changes are inside the application.yml and
application_prod.yaml and application_qa.yml.
So once you have defined all these details you can start your application in debug mode.
So let me try to start this in debug mode.
First, we will see by default the profile is qa activated because inside the application.yml file
we right now activated the profile.
So let me go to the postman here under the cards folder.
You can see there are APIs like build info.
First, I will try to invoke this.
You will get 2.0 like expected Java version
It is going to work like expected.
Coming to the ContactInfo.
You are going to get the details from the profile.
Let's try to activate the prod profile by using command line arguments.
For the same, first let me stop this server now
I'll right click on this CardsApplication and select this Modify Run configurations post that I'm going
to mention the command line arguments with the prefix hyphen hyphen followed by spring.profiles.active
is equal to prod.
So let me apply these changes and start the application again.
So I'm going to the postman now to validate the changes.
Here I'm trying to invoke this contact-info API.
You can see I'm getting the properties from the prod profile.
The same you can observe for the build-info where you will get the 1.0 as an output.
This way we have done all the required changes in all the three microservices like accounts, cards
and loans.
If you have any questions, please, please refer to the GitHub repo.
Please make sure all your changes are very similar to like we discussed and please be very careful with
these application.yml files.
Even if you try to mess up with some space, your profiles will not get activated.
For example, instead of these profiles under the spring parent, if you try to provide one more space
that will take these inside the config parent, with that your profile will never get activated because
you have mentioned in a wrong location.
That's why this spacing is very important inside the Yaml file.
I hope you are super, super clear, but like I said, this is not the best approach.
This is the most basic approach that any microservice application can use for organizations where they
are going to build hundreds of microservices.
This approach may not work.
It has some serious disadvantages.
So let's try to understand what are those disadvantages in the next lecture.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.