As of now, with the help of config server and other microservices instances, we are able to test all
the configuration management related changes inside the local system.
But as a next step we need to containerize all our microservices applications, including the config
server and post that we should try to start all our microservices along with the config server with
the help of Docker compose.
That's why for the next few lectures we are going to put efforts to make this configuration related
changes work even inside the Docker environment. Because with the help of Docker containers only,
we are going to deploy into the production environments like into Kubernetes cluster.
So in order to get started with the continuation of my application, I can straight away generate the
Docker images of my microservices and the config server.
But before that I just wanted to write Docker compose files.
Once we are clear with the setup of the Docker compose files, then we can try to containerize our applications
because we may need to do few more changes inside the config server to make it work inside the docker
compose.
So that's why first, let's try to focus on preparing the Docker compose files.
I can prepare a single Docker compose file, but as of now we have three different environments or three
different profiles like default production and QA to support these three different profiles or three
different environments.
I want to create different Docker compose files for different environments, so that they will give flexibility
to make any changes specific to a particular environment.
So here I'm going to right click on this v2-spring cloud config and I'm going to create a new
directory.
The directory name is going to be docker-compose.
Inside this Docker compose directory, I'm going to create three more new directories.
The very first one is default and post that the next directory is QA followed by a new directory with
the name prod.
This way I have three different folders inside my docker compose folder and inside each of them I can
create Docker compose file specific to those profiles or environments.
As of now we have a docker compose file inside the accounts
microservice.
We have prepared this in the previous sections, so let me copy this Docker compose first into the default
profile.
So I'm trying to copy the same.
Once the Docker compose file is copied, I'm going to delete the file present under the accounts
microservice.
We no more needed that.
So let me delete the same.
Now I'm going to open the Docker-compose.yml file.
As of now you can see we have accounts, loans and cards microservice related changes inside the Docker
compose file.
So here we need to change the image name from accounts S4 to accounts S6. Because right now we are in
the section six.
That's why we are going to generate the Docker images which are specific to this section.
That's why we need to mention the tag name as S6.
So let me do the same for loans microservice as well.
Post that
I'll also do the same for cards microservice.
So apart from these three microservices, we also created a new service inside this section with the
name config server.
So that's why let's try to create the service related to config server inside the Docker compose file.
So for the same first I'm going to copy these loans related changes inside my Docker compose file and
post that I'm going to press, enter and paste the same details here.
So now I'm going to change this accounts to config server.
So under this config server service I'm going to mention all the details of my config server.
So the image name that we are going to generate will be config server itself.
That's why I have changed the image name to eazybytes/configserver:S6 and the container
name, we can keep it as configserver-ms. And the port where we have started the config server
is 8071.
The same I have to mention inside the port mapping.
Now the memory limits I want to follow the same for the config server
also. With 700 mb, I want to limit the memory utilization of config server to a maximum of 700 MB.
And this config server
also, I want to start under the same network with the name EazyBank.
This way all the microservices started inside the same network.
They can communicate with each other with the help of this service name.
With this,
now we have three different microservices along with the config server service inside our Docker compose
file.
Now, as a next step, we need to let our individual microservices and how to connect with these config
server inside a Docker environment. For the same,
if you go and observe inside the application.yml of any of the microservice, there is a property
that we are trying to use to establish the link between config server and individual microservices.
The link is spring.config.import and here we need to mention this endpoint URL, which is config
server http://localhost:8071 the similar set of configuration we need to provide inside the Docker compose
file.
And here you may have a question like why can't my accounts microservice or any other
microservice,
they can directly use what we have mentioned here.
They cannot use this property because we have mentioned this localhost here.
My accounts docker container tries to use the localhost to communicate with the config server.
It is not going to work because my accounts container will start in its own isolated network.
When I say localhost, it will try to connect with the config server within its own network, which
will never be successful.
That's why we need to externalize this property inside the Docker compose file and we need to override
the value present inside this application.yml with the help of environment variables.
For the same, we can go to the Docker compose file first under the accounts microservice,
I'm going to mention a new child element.
The element name will be environment.
Inside this environment we can define any number of environment variables.
So here what is the environment variable name that I have to give?
It should be very similar to what we have used here, like spring.config.import.
But whenever we are trying to provide an environment variable, we need to follow a syntax which is
converting all the letters to capital letters and replacing that dot with underscore.
That's why I'll try to create a new environment variable under this environment element with the name
spring_config_import. To this, I need to pass the value of my config server details,
so let me try to copy the value from application.yml.
So as of now we have this.
So let me copy this.
Once we copy this here we can remove this optional because we want our accounts microservice to be failed
in case if it is not able to connect with the config server.
So that's why please make sure you are removing these optional inside that docker compose file.
In local it is fine to use optional but when you are trying to deploy into higher environments using Docker
or Docker Compose or Kubernetes.
It is a good standard to not mention optional because most of the time our applications will depend
on the config server.
So the config server, this is the prefix that we need to follow always.
Now instead of localhost, I should mention a host name as service name and how my accounts microservice
can connect with the config server. Inside this docker compose like you see, the config server has a
service name which is config server.
So let me copy this config server service name and mention the same in the place of localhost. And behind
the scenes,
my docker will make this work because we're trying to start all our containers inside the same network,
which is EasyBank and with that all my services and containers they can communicate by using the service
name.
So here the service name is config server.
If you choose some other service name you need to mention the same regardless of what is your service
name,
the prefix should be always config server.
Here
coincidentally, we have the prefix value and the service name value is same, but prefix always going
to be the same like config server and service name
you can change based upon your requirements.
Now, the next environment variable that I want to pass to my accounts microservice is, what is the
profile that it has to consider while starting the microservice application.
For the same, we need to mention one more environment property which is spring_profiles_active.
.
So to this we need to mention the profile that we want to activate whenever we are trying to run this
docker compose Yaml file.
Right now you can see this Docker compose file is present inside the default folder.
That means whenever someone is trying to run this docker compose, I want to start in a default profile
mode.
So that's why I'm trying to mention the same here.
The next environment variable that I want to provide here is, spring_application_name.
.
The name of the application name should match with whatever name that you have considered for the naming
convention of your files that you stored inside the config server.
So inside the config server we are storing accounts related microservices with the naming conventions
that has a prefix of accounts.
That's why I need to make sure that I'm mentioning the spring application name
also as accounts we followed the same inside the application.yml. Like spring application name
as accounts.
The reason why I'm trying to mention the same value again inside the docker compose is, there is a defect
inside the spring cloud config server.
As of now, while I'm trying to record this lecture due to that bug we need to mention the spring application
name inside your docker compose yaml file also.
Though it is the same name which you have defined inside the application.yml.
So we're not trying to override anything with a new value.
We need to mention this to overcome that bug as a workaround for the defect inside the spring cloud
config server.
Maybe in future when you are trying, please try without mentioning this and if it is working then that
means the bug is fixed in the future versions.
Otherwise you can continue to mention the same under the environment variables.
So now I have to mention the same kind of
environment variables and they're all microservices. Like under loans,
I'm going to mention the same environment.
So you can see here, spring config import is going to be the same spring profile
active also is going to be the same.
But coming to the application name, this should be loans.
Let me copy the same value again to
cards microservice under the network, here I'm pasting the values
the only value that we need to change is the application name to cards.
Now we have the Docker compose file almost ready, but there is a challenge here.
As of now, we have a condition inside our microservices which is before the individual microservice
try to start.
We need to make sure that config server is completely started and ready to accept the request.
But with this setup, if I try to run the Docker compose up command, my docker is going to create the
containers in the same order like config server, accounts, loans and cards.
But the problem with this setup is, my docker will not wait for this config server to start completely.
It will just initiate the process of the config server and it will immediately jump on to accounts and
loans and cards.
And that may create issues because if accounts microservice try to start before the config server is
readily available, then it will be an issue.
That's why we need to make certain changes inside this Docker compose file to communicate to the docker
and how to identify whether my config server is completely started or not.
Once we provided that information, we should also mention that dependency information of config server
under all our accounts, loans and cards micro service.
That way my docker has a complete information and during the Docker compose command first it will try
to start the config server and it will wait for the config server to get completely started and it has
good health to accept the request.
Once the config server is started then only it is going to start accounts, loans and cards microservice.
So to make these changes first we need to understand two important concepts.
The very first one is liveness and the second one is readiness.
So let's try to understand these concepts in the next lecture.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.