Now we have our config server exposing the liveness and readiness information with the help of actuator.
As a next step, we need to make some changes inside this docker compose file to communicate with Docker
or Docker
compose on how to evaluate whether my config server is in healthy status.
For the same, we need to create one more child element under the config server you can create after
any element.
For now I'm trying to create after ports.
So just in the same portion where the ports is there.
Here we need to create one more element which is health check.
Under this health check you can see automatically a child element is created which is test.
So to this test property, we need to give instructions on how to evaluate whether my config server
is started and it is ready to accept the request. For the same,
here
I'm going to paste a command. Like you can see here,
I have pasted a curl command. Using this curl command,
I'm trying to invoke the API path which is localhost:8071/ actuator/health/readiness.
So whenever my docker compose, try to start my service config server, it will try to check the health
check if it is started successfully or not,
by invoking this actuator URL.
Once we invoke this actuator URL, we can get the output as up or down since we want to consider only
the status up as success.
Otherwise we want to consider it as a failure.
You can see that's why using this grep command, I'm trying to search inside the response with the value
up.
If it is there, then it indicates my service is started and its health is perfect.
Otherwise I'm telling to simply the exit this health check command, which means my docker compose will
consider that as my config server
health is not proper.
Now after this test command, we need to provide more configurations for this health check.
So let me try to mention the same.
If you leave with this test command alone, my docker compose will only try to run this command only
once, but maybe in the scenarios where my config server might have taken good amount of time, maybe
30s or 20s to get start the complete config server application in such scenarios will always get the
output as failure.
That's why we need to provide some metrics like you can see here just under the same test,
we need to mention the other elements like interval, timeout retries and start period.
I'm trying to tell with the start period, please try to execute these health check command only after
the 10s. And if there is a failure, I'm telling please do the retries for ten times with an interval
of 10s and inside the each check it has to wait for the maximum five seconds to get the response from
this URL.
So that is what we are trying to achieve with these commands.
So with this health check now my Docker or Docker compose is smart enough to identify if the service
config server is started completely or not.
Now, as a next step, we need to define the dependency details of this config server into my accounts,
loans and cards microservice. For the same under these accounts
microservice just after the ports
I'm going to create a new element which is depends_on, as soon as I click on the depends_on,
here i can try to mention on which service my accounts microservices depends on.
So you can see it is automatically trying to detect the available services inside the Docker compose.
But right now I have the dependency only on the config server but not on the loans and cards microservice.
So let me select this config server.
But if you mention only depends on config server, your accounts microservice will never wait for your
config server to get completely started and available with a healthy status.
Instead, it will only wait until your config server initiated the starting process and it will never
wait,
whether the starting process is completed successfully or it failed successfully, it will never wait
for such output.
Instead, as soon as the config server starting process is initiated immediately, my accounts microservice
also will try to start, but we don't want that.
We want our accounts microservice to wait till the config server is started completely with a good health.
That's why we need to bring these config server to the next line as a child under the depends_on.
After this I'm going to mention colon and press enter.
Now under this config server I need to mention an element which is condition.
There are multiple conditions that we have like service completed successfully or service healthy
or service started.
If you mention service started, it is going to wait till your service is started, but it will never
care for your healthy status which you have defined here.
If you want for these health check to be passed, then only your accounts microservice needs to be
started.
You need to mention the value which is service healthy.
Instead of service healthy
we can also use in some scenarios, which is service completed successfully in the latest versions of
docker-compose and Docker.
This is introduced, so this will wait for your service to get started completely, behind the scenes
it will try to do some checks to make sure that the service is started completely.
But if you don't provide this health check related information, it will never know how to perform the
health checks that are specific to our config server.
That's why it is recommended to define your own health check and mention the condition as service healthy.
So with this my accounts microservice is going to wait till my config server started with a status
as service healthy.
We need to define same dependency inside our loans and cards microservice also.
So let me try to define just after the ports we are going to mention the same here.
Like depends on config server.
The condition is service healthy.
So let me mention the same for cards as well.
Just after the ports.
I'm trying to mention this information.
So now we have the complete setup like config server is going to start first.
Once this health check is satisfied, then only it is going to start my accounts, loans and cards
Microservice parallely.
Since I don't have any interdependency between accounts, loans and cards, they can get started
parallelly.
As a next step, we need to add one more service inside our docker
compose.
The service is related to rabbitmq.
We know our config server and all other microservices,
they will depend on rabbitmq since we are using spring cloud bus inside the dependencies.
So to make this work we need to create a new service element.
Here to save some time.
I'm going to paste few lines of code.
Like you can see here,
I have created a new service with the name Rabbit and this is mentioned in the same position like config
server service and this rabbit service,
first I need to provide what is the image name?
So this is the image name like Rabbitmq and this is the tag name that we need to mention.
Post that,
we need to mention the host name which is Rabbitmq.
So this property is specific to Rabbitmq container.
That's why we don't have to mention this for other services that we have here.
Post that for Rabbit, we need to mention two ports mapping 5672 and 15672.
We have done the same when we tried to run the Docker run command for Rabbitmq.
Why two ports is, inside Rabbitmq
there are two components.
One is which will take care of the management of the Rabbitmq and the other one which will take care
of the core activities.
So since there are two components, they are going to start at two different port like
5672 and 15672.
That's why we need to mention these two port mappings.
Now, after this port mapping, we should also define the health check for Rabbitmq. Because my config
server and other microservices, they are dependent on my rabbitmq. Until my rabbitmq starts completely
with a good health.
I cannot really start my config server or any other service.
That's why we need to mention this health check along with the test command.
And at this test command I have given these value and these value is mentioned by the rabbitmq inside
their official documentation.
So whenever we want to test whether the Rabbitmq health is fine or not, we need to run this test command
inside the container of Rabbitmq. After this, you know about this interval timer retries and start period.
Now we have the service with the name Rabbit.
As a next step, I need to define the dependency inside my config server.
For the same, I'm going to invoke the element which is depends_on and to this element
I'm going to mention the service name which is Rabbit.
Since we want to make sure the rabbit is completely started successfully with a good health, we need
to bring this to next line as an element under depends on and post that we need to mention colon followed
by we need to mention condition. Under the condition
we need to mention service healthy. With this now my config server will wait for my rabbitmq to get started
and once it is get started, the health check that we have defined here should be successful.
Then only the config server will try to start post that
only my accounts, loans and cards will try to get started.
And here you may have a question like our accounts, loans and cards microservice
they also depend on this rabbitmq. Then why you are not mentioning this rabbit under the
depends on of accounts, loans and cards.
It's very simple.
The reason why I'm not mentioning is, anyway we have mentioned the dependency on config server inside
the accounts, loans and cards.
When my config server is waiting for my rabbitmq to get started indirectly my accounts, loans and cards.
They will also wait for this rabbitmq to get started.
That's why I don't have to mention again the rabbitmq dependency inside the accounts, loans and cards.
But if you want you can mention there is no harm in that.
Now our docker compose file for the default
is ready.
I'm assuming it is completely in a working state before we try to test this Docker compose file.
First, we need to make sure we are following a standard here.
As of now, you can see there is a lot of repetitive information inside our docker-compose.yml
file.
Like you can see at many places I have mentioned these deploy instructions and our config server and
accounts, cards and loans.
And similarly we have mentioned the networks also under all of the services. We need to move all these
repetitive configurations into another common file.
From there we can try to import so that the content will not be duplicated multiple times.
And at the same time, if you have the content in a single place, changing to a different value is
going to be super, super easy because you have to do the changes in only single place, but not under
the all services.
That's why inside the next lecture, let's try to optimize this docker-compose.yml file further before
I try to close this lecture.
We forget to mention these networks.
EasyBank under the Rabbitmq.
If you don't mention that, then rabbit service is going to start in a different isolated network and
the connection between rabbit, config server and other microservices will not work.
So that's why please make sure you are mentioning networks as EasyBank and the same network we have
created towards the end.
Like you can see, we have created a network with the name EasyBank which supports a driver bridge.
The same,
we are trying to refer in all the services.
I hope you are clear.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.