Inside this lecture, let's try to use the Docker compose file to start all our containers and make
sure the configuration related changes are working even inside the Docker environment.
Before we try to run the Docker compose commands, please make sure there are no running containers.
Inside my Docker desktop,
I can go to my containers.
You can see there are no running containers.
If there are any running containers or stopped containers, please delete them because you need a lot
of space and memory inside your local system. To run the five different containers, including like rabbit,
config server, accounts, loans and cards.
So I came to my terminal.
Here I'll go back to location where my Docker compose folder is present, so I'll navigate to the Docker
compose folder.
So inside the Docker compose folder,
as of now we have created the Docker compose file only inside the default folder.
So let me go inside this folder.
Here I'm going to run the command, which is docker
compose up -d. So as soon as I try to execute this command, you can see the containers are trying
to get started. As of now,
so first my rabbitmq service will try to get started.
Post that my config server will try to get started once my config server is created, then only my accounts,
cards and loans related containers will get created.
So it will take some time.
So please wait for some time here.
Meanwhile, you can open a new terminal and try to run the command which is docker ps.
So this will show you the list of running containers.
So as of now you can see inside my local all my containers started.
Very first one is rabbitmq and the status is healthy because we have provided the health check very
similarly config server, it has started and the status is healthy because we have provided the health
check details. Whereas accounts, loans and cards, they simply started less than a second ago and
my docker is not sure about their health status, because we didn't provide any health instructions on
how to check that.
But that's fine.
Whenever the config server and rabbitmq started our accounts, loans and cards, microservice also should
get started automatically.
Now we can go to the postman and try to test the changes.
So inside my postman under the accounts,
first I'm going to invoke this build-info. So the URL is going to be the same like localhost:8080/api/build-info
.
You can see we are getting the 3.0 because we started the containers with a default profile. Where we
have mentioned that default profile instructions.
If you check inside the commonconfig.yml.
We have mentioned this property using environment variables. Since the environment variables has highest
priority compared to what we have mentioned inside the application.yml.
My containers will start with the default profile.
Now let me try to test Java version
also, the Java version
you can see this is the JAVA_HOME path that has set inside my container.
And very similarly if you click on this contact-info, you can see we are getting the properties from
the default profile.
Very similarly, you can also validate cards and loans microservice if you are interested.
Now as a next step, we need to test whether the automatic refresh of the properties is happening without
the restart of the containers.
To get started around this, we need to make sure we have the webhook running inside the GitHub repo
like we discussed previously.
And fortunately whatever webhook session that I have created previously, I closed that.
that's why I'm going to create one more webhook session. For the same,
first, I need to go to a website.
The website name is Hook Decom.
So here I'll open this and I'll click on this test webhook post that I'll click on this add destination,
which will create a new session.
So here I need to run this command brew install already completed.
I will go and try to run this login command.
So inside my terminal I'm trying to run this command so you can see I'm getting 401 unauthorized because
the previous session that I have used is still present inside my local system somewhere in the cache.
So what I need to do is, I need to run hook deck logout command. So that will log out me from the previous
session and will clear any credentials that I have inside my local system.
So now I'm going to run the login command again.
This time the login is successful.
As a next step, I'm going to take this third command, which is hookdeck listen.
So let me copy this and run the same inside my terminal but with a port 8071.
So let me run this command post that it will ask me what is the path?
The path, you know, slash monitor.
Once we mention this path, we need to mention the hostname, which is localhost. Post that will get
a webhook URL.
So let me take this webhook URL. Here I am into my GitHub repository under this eazybytes-config.
I need to click on the settings button and after this I need to click on this webhooks.
Now as of now we have some current webhook so we can edit that or
we can create a new webhook.
So here I'll click on this edit.
It will ask me the password.
So let me enter the password.
Once I enter the password, I'm going to click on this confirm button.
As of now we have a different payload URL.
Instead of this, I'm going to mention the new webhook URL that we have copied.
Apart from this URL, everything else should be fine.
So let me click on this update webhook.
With that,
now I can try to change a property.
For example, I'll try to change this accounts.yml because right now our container started with
a default profile.
Here
let me click on this edit button post that I'm going to change one of the property under the accounts.
Instead of local,
I can keep it as docker.
So once I have mentioned these changes, let me commit the changes into the GitHub repo.
Now I'll go and check inside the terminal.
Inside the terminal we are getting the 500 status.
That means the refresh attempt fail.
So let's try to understand what is the issue here, to understand what is the issue?
First, let me test the log files of my config server container. for the same,
I came into my Docker dashboard, so inside my containers I can click on this config server ms to see the
logs of my config server container.
So here you can see it is trying to connect to my rabbitmq with the default connection details like
localhost 5672.
So this is not going to work because rabbitmq is not started within the same container of config server.
It has started as a separate container with a separate service name.
So we missed mentioning the rabbitmq connection details inside the Docker compose file, but here you
may have a question like how come other functionality is working
like we tested accounts microservice, APIs and we are getting a successful response, so let's try
to check the same.
So if I try to execute this actuator/health, you can see I'm getting the status as down, which
means the overall health is down.
Whereas if I try to check the readiness, I'm getting the status as up, because according to the config
server rabbitmq is an optional settings.
That's why it went ahead and started and it is trying to accept the request. With that reason,
our accounts, loans and cards microservice, all the containers they started since the readiness
health check is up.
So to fix this issue, it's very simple.
We need to provide the rabbitmq connection details for all our containers.
So let me go to that Docker compose file.
Inside the docker compose file, we can define the connection details under each container.
Instead of that, we can also define the connection details under the microservice based config, because
my config server accounts, loans and cards microservice, all of them needed the rabbitmq related configurations.
That's why I'm going to create a new element under the deploy with the name environment.
Under this environment I need to mention the properties related to the Rabbitmq.
So if you see here as of now inside the application.yml, we have mentioned these properties like
which is spring.rabbitmq host as localhost port and username and password.
So the port username and password we should be fine.
So these are the default values and my docker containers also they can use that, but this localhost
will not work.
Instead we need to mention the service name of Rabbitmq.
So that's why let's try to override only these host variable. For the same inside the commonconfig.yml.
.
I'm going to create a new environment variable with the name spring_rabbitmq_host.
The host name,
we should not mention localhost.
Instead we should mention the service name which is rabbit.
So all my containers they can connect with this service because they all started inside the same network.
So let me mention the host as rabbit here.
Maybe I can try to mention inside the double quotes.
So with this the issue should get resolved.
So let me save this changes.
And here inside my terminal where I have started my docker compose up command, I'm going to run the
new command which is Docker compose down.
So first I will try to delete all the existing containers that I have started previously.
So let this complete.
Once the deletion of all the containers is completed, I can try to run the command which is docker
compose up -d, so this will try to start all my containers again with the new Rabbitmq connection
details that we have provided.
I can also try to see the logs of config server if the connection is established successfully.
So let me click on this config server -ms.
As you can see it is trying to get started, so let's wait for a couple of seconds. Like we discussed
previously, you can also check the logs inside the logs.
Explorer.
It's up to you where you want to check.
Right now I'm trying to check this filter of config server ms.
And with that I will be able to see all the config server related logs, but for some reason I'm not
comfortable with this layout.
I'm always
comfortable by checking the logs directly inside the console.
So I'm used to this format because daily I'll check the logs in similar style inside my IDE,
that's why I'm comfortable with this process.
If you are comfortable with the logs Explorer, definitely you can follow the same.
So here you can see in the logs there is a connection
details like attempting to connect to the Rabbitmq 5672 and it successfully created
a new connection.
So now let's try to test the health of this config server.
So here I'm trying to refresh this page.
This time you can see the status is showing as up the same,
we can confirm for readiness as well here.
Also the up status is present.
So with that all our containers should get started.
So let me quickly confirm if my accounts microservice started successfully, you can see it started
successfully.
I can also confirm the same for cards.
It is also started.
Let me do the same for loans.
Now I'll try to invoke this contact-info.
As of now you can see we are getting local but we'll get the docker because all the services are restarted.
That's why we are getting the latest property.
So what we can do is, we can revert back to the local and see if it is working fine.
Meanwhile, please make sure the webhook related terminal is running.
The session is not yet closed.
I'm going to my repo and opening the file which is accounts.yml here inside this accounts.yml
file.
I'm going to revert this docker to the previous value which is local.
So let me click on this edit button and replace this docker with local and commit the changes to the
GitHub repo. Post this we can go to the terminal and confirm if we have received the 200 status.
You can see this time we received 200 status.
They're there in the down,
you can see I'm so happy this is working.
Now let's validate in the postman.
Now inside the postman.
I'm going to run this contact-info.
You can see previously we have the docker.
If I try to click on the send button, you can see right now we are getting the local API's, so the
refresh functionality is working automatically without invoking any URL manually.
So this confirms our docker compose setup is working for the default profile.
So let's try to quickly set up the same for prod and qa profile as well.
And we can also validate them if everything is working.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.