As of now, we are trying to send the request to the Gateway server by using the application name in
complete capital letters like you can see accounts, loans and cards.
If I try to send in a small case letter, it is not going to work.
I can show you the demo as well.
Here I'm going to change this accounts from capital letters to small letters post that I will try to invoke
these API.
So let me click on the send button.
You can see I'm getting an error, which is 404 not found.
If you are fine using completely capital letters, you should be good with the default behavior of the
gateway server.
But mentioning a value inside the path in complete capital letters is very odd.
Even we can't request our client applications to send only the application name or the microservice
name in capital letters.
That will be a very weird ask or weird behavior inside our application.
So to overcome this, we can introduce a new property inside the application.yml Gateway server.
So let me go to the IntelliJ idea.
Here inside my IntelliJ idea, I need to create a new property under this locator just in the same place
where we have enabled, in the same place
I'm going to mention a new property which is lowercase service ID.
With this, the property is going to be spring.cloud.gateway.discovery.locator.
lowercase serviceId to this property
I want to mention the value as true.
With this we are telling to our gateway server.
Please accept the service name with the completely lowercase.
So now I have made this changes
let me do a build.
Once the build is completed, we can try to validate the same inside the postman.
This time you can see we have completely small letters inside the service name or inside the application
name.
So let me click on the send button and you can see I'm getting a successful response.
Very similarly, we can also try to test the fetch API for the same
we need to take the mobile number and go to the other request and mention the same mobile number here.
First, let me check with completely capital letters.
So if I try to click on the send button, you can see now this time I'm getting a not found error,
so I'm going to make this as completely small letters. With this
If I try to send the response, you will get a successful response.
I'm going to continue this way only because this looks very professional to me.
And ideally we should never use complete capital letters inside a URL path.
I hope you are clear about this small change that we have done.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.