Now inside this lecture, let's try to make changes inside the individual microservices to accept the
request header that my gateway is going to forward along with the request. For the same
first, let me go to the accounts
microservice inside the accounts
microservice we have two different controller classes.
The very first one is AccountsController and the second one is CustomerController.
We don't have to make the changes in all the APIs available inside the microservices.
Instead, we can take a single API that is going to travel all the microservices.
We have such REST API inside the CustomerController.
Whenever my external client, they're trying to invoke my API path, which is fetch customer details
internally, my accounts microservice is going to forward the request to the loans and cards microservice
as well.
That's why let's try to make the changes related to the easybank correlation ID for this API only if
you are interested
you can do for the remaining REST APIs as well.
But inside this lecture I'm going to make the changes only for this API and post that I'm going to show
you a demo as well.
So here, just like request to param, we need to accept one more input method parameter and since we
want to accept a request header, we need to use the annotation which is request header. To this request
header we need to mention what is the header name.
So the header name that we have is easybank-correlation-d.
So whatever value that I have inside this header, I want to assign this to the a method param with
the name correlation id.
So let me create the same here.
So with this, this REST API which is present inside the accounts microservice will have access to
these request header that is being sent by my gateway server.
So now I'm going to create few lagers inside this controller and using those lagers and this correlation
ID value, I'm going to print some logger statements which will help us during the debugging for the
same.
First, let me create a logger variable in the top.
Here I'm going to create a new logger variable and it will have the class name.
Now using the same logger variable, I'm going to create few logger statements inside my fetch customer
details method.
So here I'm going to create a new logger statement.
You can see I'm trying to create a new logger statement that is going to print the correlationId.
My logger statement will be having the class name along with this statement which we are trying to print
like easybank-correlationId found
and what is the correlationId value.
We can make this e to small letter to be consistent with the gateway server.
Now if you see after leveraging this correlationId inside my accounts microservice, I want to forward
the same to my loans and cards microservice as well.
For the same, we need to pass this correlationId as a second parameter to the method present inside
this ICustomerService
fetchCustomerDetails. So let me open this fetchCustomerDetails method.
So here we are going to accept a new input parameter with the name correlationId.
As a next step, I can go to the implementation class of this service interface.
So the service implementation class is CustomerServiceImpl.
So here we are getting an compilation error.
I can fix that by introducing a new method parameter to this method with the name correlation ID, the
same correlation id I want to send to my loans and cards microservice.
So where we are trying to invoke the loans and cards microservice, we are trying to invoke the loans
and cards microservice with the help of this loans feign client and cards feign client.
So while we are trying to invoke these methods, we need to make sure we are passing the correlationId
as a first parameter followed by what is the mobile number.
So let me do the same for cards microservice as well.
So now as soon as we add these correlationId as a first method input parameter, I'll get a compilation
errors.
So to resolve this we need to go to the respective feign client related interfaces.
So here, just like how we have RequestParam with the String mobile number, very similarly, I'm going
to add the request header that is going to accept correlation ID value.
We already done this inside the CustomerController.
So inside the CustomerController we have this logic.
So let me take this logic and mention the same inside the loans feign client interface.
So I'm trying to mention the same here.
So let me do the same for cards feign client as well.
So let me open this method and here I'm going to accept a new method input parameter of type RequestHeader
.
With this all the changes inside the accounts microservice is completed. As a next step, we need to
make sure that these fetch APIs present inside the cards and loans microservice
they're also accepting the RequestHeader with the name as easybank correlationId so we know where
to make these changes.
So let me go
the LoansController.
Inside the LoansController there is a API that supports the path fetch to this method only.
I'm going to pass new request to input method parameter of type RequestHeader.
So here we have added the new input method parameter.
As a next step, we need to leverage this correlationId and try to log some statements inside these
LoansController
class.
First, let me create a logger variable here.
Here on top of the class, I'm going to create a new variable very similar to what we have created inside
the CustomerController.
So let me take this value and paste it inside the LoansController class.
But instead of CustomerController, we need to mention the correct class name, which is LoansController.
Now I'll go to the fetch related Java method here.
So under this method I'm going to create a new logger statement.
We can mention the same logger that we have mentioned inside the CustomerController.
Here we have a logger statement.
Let me copy this statement and go to the LoansController and inside the LoansController I'm going
to mention the same logger statement. As a next step,
let me go to the CardsController and inside the CardsController also, we need to make very similar
changes.
First, I'll make sure I'm adding these method input parameter of type RequestHeader.
So let me mention the same under the fetch related method.
So here we have a fetchCardDetails() method to this method I'm going to pass a new method input parameter
and using the same correlation ID, I'm going to introduce a new logger statement.
So let me copy this logger statement and mention the same inside the body of this method.
And since we have not defined the logger variable, we are getting an error.
So let me go to the top of the class and here I'm going to create a logger variable very similar to
how we have defined inside the other controller classes.
So let me copy this line of code and mention the same inside the CardsController post that I can replace
this LoansController with CardsController class.
With this, we have done all the Java changes. As a next step
let me go to the application.yml of Gateway Server.
So here you can see we have enabled the debugging logging for the package com.eazybytes.gatewayserver
.
Very similarly, we have to do inside the other microservices.
As of now we have created the debug loggers inside the accounts, loans and cards.
But if you don't enable them, you can't see the logger statements inside your console. For the same,
let me open the application.yml of my accounts microservice and here towards the end I'm going
to paste the same property that we have defined inside the gateway.
But here we need to make sure we are mentioning the correct package name, the route package that we
have inside the accounts
microservice is com.eazybytes.accounts, so I need to replace this gateway server with accounts.
So let me copy this value and go to the application.yml file of cards microservice.
So under the resources I have application.yml and towards the end I'm going to paste the same property
and replace this accounts with cards.
I need to do the same for loans microservice as well.
Let me open the application.yml file present inside the loans microservice and towards the end
I'm going to paste the same property and replace this cards with loans.
With this we are done with all the required changes.
Let me save this changes and do a clean build. Once the build is completed,
since we have done a good amount of changes, let's try to restart accounts, loans, cards and gateway
server. For the same,
first, I'm going to restart my accounts application.
Once I have restarted the accounts application, I'm also going to restart loans application followed
by cards application.
Once my accounts, cards and loans applications, they started completely and registered with the Eureka
server successfully then only I'm going to restart my gateway server application. After few seconds inside
my Eureka dashboard, I'm able to see all my accounts, cards and loans microservices.
They registered successfully. As a next step,
let me try to restart the gateway server.
Here I'm trying to restart my gateway server application.
Once this restart is completed, we can try to validate all the changes. In order to validate all our
changes
first, let me clean the console of cards, loans and accounts microservice along with the Gateway server
application as well.
So this will allow us to see our own custom logs that we have defined inside our custom filters.
Now I came to the postman to validate our changes here In order to test our filter related changes,
we can invoke the fetchCustomerDetails request present inside the Gateway server folder.
So this is going to send a request to the fetchCustomerDetails API presence inside the accounts microservice
by providing an input mobile number.
But as of now we don't have any data inside accounts, loans and cards microservices,
since we are using H2 database.
That's why
first, let's try to create the data inside the accounts, cards and loans.
So I have created respective request under the Gateway server.
First, I'm going to click on this accounts related request and I'm trying to invoke the create API
available inside the accounts microservice with the help of Gateway Server.
So I'm trying to pass the same mobile number inside the RequestBody.
So let me click on the send button.
I'm getting a successful response.
As a next step, I will invoke the cards microservice with the help of Gateway server.
Here also, I received that 201
let me go to the loans request and try to create a new loan with the same mobile number
and here also I received the successful response.
As a next step, I can go to the fetchCustomerDetails and try to invoke these APIs.
Let me click on this send button and see the output, what we are going to get.
So you can see we received the successful response like these are the account details, loan details
and card details.
And if you go and check the headers, there is a new header with the name EasyBank-correlationId
.
Now my client, they can use this correlationId in future whenever they want to reach out to the easybank
and saying that for so-and-so request with a so-and-so correlation id something is wrong,
please debug in the support ticket that they are going to rise to the easybank
they can mention these correlationId. Now using these correlationId, my developer can try to analyze
the log statements.
So first I'll go to the gateway server.
So inside the gateway server, if you try to search for the same traceId, you can see there are two
log statements
one, while we are trying to generate the traceId inside the RequestTraceFilter and very similarly the
second one inside the ResponseTraceFilter.
Whenever we are trying to create a new header inside the response that we are going to send for client
applications.
So this confirms that my gateway server has no issues.
Now let me go to the accounts application related log statements.
So here also I'm going to search for the same correlation ID.
You can see I have one correlationId saying that easybank correlation ID found with so and so value.
So this confirms that the request reached to the accounts microservice. In a scenarios where the request
never reached loans and cards microservice then definitely you can't find this trace related logs inside
loans and cards microservice.
But since in our scenario we received the successful response, we should be able to see the log statements
with the given trace ID inside the loans and very similarly inside the cards as well.
I hope you are seeing the power of Gateway Server, which is acting as an edge server.
Here I have taken some simple business logic, but in your real projects you may have some complex business
logic
also, you can implement any kind of cross-cutting concerns like logging, auditing, security inside
your edge server.
With the help of these filters available inside the Gateway server. I have a separate section where
I'm going to talk about the microservices security.
Inside that section, I'm going to leverage the Gateway server to implement the security so that only
authenticated and authorized users can invoke our microservices network.
I hope you are clear.
I know this is a lot of information for you.
Please try to understand all the changes by rewatching the videos for your reference inside the slides
I have mentioned all the important steps that we followed while we try to implement these Gateway server
with the help of Spring Cloud Gateway.
First, we have created a spring boot project by adding the respective dependencies post
we have added few properties inside the application.yml followed by
we have done some routing related configurations. Post that we try to invoke the microservices with the
help of Edge Server, which is hosted at the port 8072.
Please refer to these slides whenever you are trying to brush up these concepts.
Maybe whenever you are trying to attend an interview related to the microservices.
These slides are going to be super,super handy for you.
With this
I'm assuming your super, super clear about all the changes that we have discussed in this lecture.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.