As of now, we developed the Edge server for our microservices network and we tested everything inside
the local system. As a next step,
let's try to build the Docker images for all the projects that we have inside the Section9.
Post that we can update the Docker compose file and test all the Edge server or gateway related changes using
Docker containers.
So here, before I try to generate the Docker images, I want to enable the health related and readiness
and liveliness related URLs inside my accounts, loans and cards
microservice.
The reason is when we are trying to update the Docker compose file for this section9, we need to
define the dependencies for our gateway server saying that only once my accounts, cards and loans microservice
started and their health is good, then only try to start the gateway server.
For that reason we need to add the properties related to the health probes inside the accounts, loans
and cards.
We already defined these properties inside the config server.
If you can open the application.yml of config server.
Here we have properties where we are trying to enable the health related APIs which are available inside
the actuator.
So let me copy these properties and I'll go to the accounts application.yml.
Here I'm going to paste the properties just after the endpoints in the same portion where we have these endpoints.
After pasting these properties,
similarly, I should also enable the health related probes under the endpoint.
So let me go to the accounts application.yml.
We have endpoint here and at this endpoint I'm going to add the properties related to health probes
enabled as true.
So we need to make very similar changes inside the cards microservice as well.
So inside my application.yml first let me try to add the properties under the endpoint.
Just after the shutdown, I'm going to mention the health probes enabled as true.
After that I'm going to copy the other properties which we can mention under the management.
So let me copy these properties and go to the cards application.yml under the management
after endpoints, I'm going to paste the same properties which are related to health.
So with these we should be good from cards microservice perspective.
Let me go to the application.yml of loans microservice.
So here under the management, just after the endpoints, I'm going to paste the properties related
to health readiness and liveness readiness. Next under the endpoint just after the shutdown enabled as
true, I'm going to mention the properties related to the health probes.
By copying these values from cards microservice and pasting them inside the loans
microservice.
With this we should be good.
Let me save this changes.
Do a build and I'm going to stop all the local running instances. Before we try to generate the Docker
images
please check your pom.xml and make sure the tag name has S9 for all your microservices. Because we want
to generate the Docker images which are specific to section9 and inside your Docker desktop
also, please make sure there are no existing images related to your microservices.
As of now, you can see I don't have any eazybytes related Docker images and there are no containers
as well.
Now
I came to my terminal.
As of now you can see I have opened the terminal inside my section9 folder.
As a next step, I'll navigate into the folder accounts and inside this accounts I have a pom.xml.
At this location
I'm going to run the command which is maven compile followed by Jib:dockerBuild.
Please make sure B is capital letter.
So if I try to run this command a docker image of accounts microservice will be generated.
Please wait a couple of seconds here.
Now the Docker image of accounts microservice is generated.
Let me clean the console and navigate back to the parent folder and post that I'm going to navigate
into the loans project.
And here also I'm going to run the same command.
This will generate the Docker image of loans microservice.
Once this is complete, I'm going to follow the same instructions again.
After running the clear command, I'm going to navigate to the parent folder and post that
I'll go inside the cards folder and run the same command which is maven compiled jib:dockerBuild.
Since we are using the jib, it is generating the Docker images very quickly, whereas for Buildpacks
it is going to take good amount of time, like at least one minute it will take to generate each Docker
image.
So let me go back to the parent folder and navigate to the config server and run the same command,
which is maven compile jib:dockerBuild. Once the config server Docker image is generated.
Now, as a next step, we can go back to the parent folder and navigate back into the Eureka Server.
So here also I'm going to run the same command.
So please try to remember these maven related commands.
These are going to be very handful for you.
The same commands i have
mentioned inside the GitHub repo as well. As a next step, let me go into the gateway server and
for the gateway server I'm going to generate the Docker image with the help of Maven Command.
In total we have generated 6 Docker images.
We can also confirm the same by running the command, which is Docker images.
So you can see there are 6 Docker images with the tag S9 123456.
You can also confirm the same by checking inside the Docker desktop.
So under the images, if you search for images with the tag S9, you should be able to see total 6
docker images. As a next step,
let me push all these Docker images into my Docker hub repository.
The command that we need to use to push the Docker images is, docker image push docker.io.
What is your Docker username.
In my case it is eazybytes followed by what is your Docker image name, for example for accounts microservice
the Docker image name is going to be accounts: and the tag name is S9.
If I try to execute this command, my accounts microservice docker image will be pushed into my Docker
hub.
I will try to push the remaining Docker images into the Docker hub by the time I come into the next
lecture, but I'm assuming you are already familiar with all these Docker image generation process and
Docker image push process.
So please feel free to run these commands inside your local system and make sure you are generating
the Docker images at regular milestones so that in future, whenever you want to test a specific section
related changes, it is going to be super easy for you.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.