Behind the scenes,
I pushed all my Docker images related to the Section9 into my Docker hub.
You can see there is a gateway server right now.
Just pushed a few seconds back and very similarly all the images I pushed a few minutes back.
If you try to open any of these microservice like accounts microservice, you should be able to see
a new tag name, which is S9.
So this S9 tag will have all the changes that we have discussed inside this section.
As a next step, let's try to update the Docker compose file and try to run the same post that we can
validate all our edge server or gateway server related changes using Docker containers. Inside our
workspace location.
There is a folder docker-compose.
We can go to that default folder and open that Docker-compose.yaml file.
Here just like other services, we need to create gateway server related service.
So let me create the Gateway server related service just after the cards
microservice I'm going to paste the same card service here and rename these card service to Gateway
Server.
Once we have mentioned this name, we should also mention what is the image name?
The image name we are following right now is, gatewayserver and the tag name should be S9. So please
make sure you are searching for S8 inside your Docker
compose and replace this S8 with S9.
So I'm just trying to click on this replace all.
So that will replace all S8 with S9. As a next step
I need to change this container name, so instead of cards-ms I'm going to make it as gatewayserver-ms.
And the port where we want our gateway server to start is 8072:9000
So that's why we need to update these port mapping and the application name is going to be gateway server.
With this we should be good because under the common config file we have a service with the name microservice-eureka
.
So if I go and check that service, we are passing the Eureka related details along with the config
server details because this service is extending the parent service which is microservice-configserver-config
.
Now as a next step, we need to define the health checks for all our accounts, loans and cards
microservice. For the same,
let me copy the health check related information from Eureka Server.
So I'm trying to copy these configurations and I'll go to the accounts microservice, here just after
the ports, I'm going to paste the health check related information.
So under this health check we need to mention what is our port number of accounts Microservice.
The port number is 8080.
As a next step, I need to define very similar health check related configurations under the loans microservice
as well.
Just after the ports, I'm going to paste the health check related configurations and change this port
number from 8080:8090.
Let me go to the cards microservice configurations also.
also here we have another instance, details of loans, microservice.
I don't want to carry forward this into the section9, so let me delete this service and post that
under cards after ports configuration, I'm going to provide the health check related information.
So the port number here it is going to be 9000.
As a next step, we can go to the gateway server and here after the ports, I'm going to mention the
element which is depends on after mentioning the depends on we can mention what is the service name,
which is like accounts and the condition is service healthy.
Very similarly, I also have dependency on loans microservice with the condition service healthy and
after loans.
I'm going to mention cards with the condition service healthy.
With this we should be good.
Let me try to run the Docker compose command and see if we get any errors.
Right now I'm into the section9 folder inside my terminal.
Let me navigate into the Docker compose and default folder.
Once we entered into this default folder, I'm going to run the command, which is docker compose app -d
.
This will try to start all our containers.
The very first service that we are going to start is config server followed by Eureka Server.
After the Eureka server is started, we are going to start accounts, loans and cards.
Once all the individual microservices health is good, then my gateway server is going to start towards
the end.
So this is going to take at least one two minutes.
So let's wait for this to get complete.
After two minutes, all my containers started successfully inside my local system.
Let me validate the same inside the Docker desktop.
Here under the containers you can see all my containers are in running status.
If I try to click on the gatewayserver-ms, I will be able to see the logs related to the gatewayserver
.
Here you can see the gateway started successfully.
Let me try to clean all the logs inside the containers of gateway server cards, microservice followed
by loans microservice and at last inside the accounts microservice as well.
So that we can see our correlation logs very clearly as a next step to test these edge server related
changes,
First, I need to create the data inside my microservices. For the same,
first, let's try to execute the create API available inside the accounts microservice with the help
of Gateway server.
So let me send this request.
I'm getting a successful response post that I'm going to create a new card with the same mobile number.
Here
also, I'm getting a successful response and at last I'm going to create a new loan with the same mobile
number.
And here also we are getting the successful response.
As a next step, I'll go to the fetchCustomerDetails().
Here I'm going to invoke the fetchCustomerDetails() with the same mobile number.
Let me clean the body here.
Now I'm clicking on the send button with this
now you can expect a successful response like you can see accounts, loans and cards related information
we have received.
We can also validate the headers that we have inside the response.
Here we have a new header with the name easybank-correlationId and this is the correlation
ID that my Gateway server initially generated.
So let me copy this correlationId and the same I'm going to search inside my accounts microservice
and there is a log inside my accounts
microservice. Now let me go to the loans microservice here
also I have a log with the same traceId as a next step
I will check inside cards microservice.
Here also, we should have two logs and I have two logs here.
One is from the RequestTraceFilter and the other one is from the ResponseTraceFilter.
With this we successfully validated the changes inside the Docker environment by executing this Docker
compose file.
Now let me try to run the command which is docker compose down, which will stop all my running containers.
While these containers are getting stopped.
I can try to copy the same content into the other Docker compose files, so let me copy this Docker
compose file and mention the same inside the prod docker-compose.yml file and post that I'm going to
mention the same inside the qa/docker-compose.yml file.
I believe we didn't make any changes inside the commonconfig.yml.
That's why we don't need to update anything inside the commonconfig.yml.
So please make sure in the respective folders we have the correct profile and inside the qa
also we have spring profiles active as qa profile.
With this we are done with all the discussion about the edge server. In the coming sections, we are
going to come back again to the gatewayserver and try to implement that many business logic related
to security, fault tolerance and resilience.
But this is a very good start for us in terms of building a API gateway or an edge server for our microservice
network.
Now all my external clients, they don't have to invoke different, different individual microservice
API URLs.
Instead, they can simply rely on one edge server, which is gateway server.
I'm super, super happy here with the progress that we are making inside this course.
I'm also assuming you are also feeling very happy here.
Before we try to close this lecture, I have a request for you.
Please spend 1 or 2 minutes and provide your valuable feedback by providing your review inside the Udemy.
This will help me to understand your feedback and try to improvise this course further.
If you like sharing the feedback personally, please send an email to me or you can also send a message
inside LinkedIn.
All the contact details like email and LinkedIn.
You can find inside my official website, which is eazybytes.com.
If you are also interested in other courses that are created by me inside this website, you will be
able to see them.
So please enroll them if you are interested.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next section.
Bye.