To get started with the Apache Kafka inside our microservices.
First, we need to make sure we set up the Apache Kafka inside our local system.
For the same, you can come to this official website of Kafka, which is Kafka.apache.org.
So here you'll be able to see a quick introduction about what is Kafka, what are its core capabilities,
what are its use cases ?
If you are interested, please read them.
But I just wanted to highlight here you can see the statement, which is more than 80% of the fortune
100 companies they trust and use Kafka.
And apart from this statement, you should also see some more metrics here, like ten out of ten manufacturing
companies, they are using Kafka, seven out of ten banks, ten out of ten insurance companies, and
eight out of ten telecom companies,
they are using Kafka. Because all the organizations that come under these domains, they produce a lot
of data.
So they need something which is capable of processing a lot of data asynchronously or with the event
streaming.
That's why they are using Apache Kafka. With this,
I'm assuming it also gives a confidence to you that Apache Kafka is a better product compared to the
Rabbitmq.
So to get started with the local setup of Apache Kafka, you can click on this get started and there
is an option Quick start.
So let me click on that.
So since I'm using the Mac OS, I have the steps that I can follow inside my Mac system.
If you are using Windows operating system, you may need to use corresponding commands to set up the
Kafka inside your local system.
So first there is a download link.
I can click on that to download the Apache Kafka.
From this website I can click very first link that I have which will download my Apache Kafka into my
local system.
So you can see the download is right now happening.
Let's wait for this to complete.
Meanwhile, let's try to understand what are the commands that I need to run.
The very first command is to extract the compressed file that it is going to download.
After the extraction of the file is completed, I need to go inside the folder with the name provided
here.
So once my terminal is inside my Kafka folder, I can follow the steps that they have provided here
to start the Kafka environment.
Here they have provided two approaches Kafka with Zookeeper and Kafka with KRaft.
So Kafka with a KRaft is a newer approach because they are trying to get rid of Zookeeper, which is
a extra component that we need to set up whenever we want to set up a Kafka cluster inside the local
system.
Since the approach with Zookeeper is going to be retired someday, I'm going to use the newer approach,
which is Kafka with the KRaft.
So now my download is completed.
Let me go to my terminal.
I open my terminal at the downloads location.
If you can try to run the pwd, you can see right now I'm at the downloads folder location.
Now I'm going to run this very first command to extract the compressed downloaded file.
So let me copy this command and mention the same inside my terminal and run the same.
So the extraction process is completed.
As a next step, I can go inside my Kafka folder, so let me run this cd command.
Now I can try to run the commands that they have provided inside the website.
Inside this page,
if you can scroll down to the steps that they have mentioned under the Kafka with the KRaft section.
First, I need to run this command, which is I want to generate a random cluster ID and assign the
same to my Kafka cluster.
So let me run this first command.
Once the first command is completed, try to run the second command.
So this is the second command.
Let me copy this entire command.
I'll go to my terminal and here I'm going to run the same. Once the second command is also completed.
Finally, we can run the third command to run the Kafka server.
So this is the third command.
Let me try to copy the same and mention the same here and execute it. With this you can see my Kafka
started at the port 9092.
So this is the place where my Kafka broker is going to be available.
So with this now, we have successfully set up the Kafka inside the local system.
In the next lecture, let's try to update our accounts and message microservices code to connect to
this Kafka and leverage Kafka for event streaming and asynchronous communication.
Thank you.
And I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.