Behind the scenes,
I have generated the Docker images for all the seven applications that we have with the tag name as
S14.
The same I have pushed into the Docker hub as well.
You can also validate the same inside my Docker hub.
If you try to open any of the Docker image, there will be a tag name with a value s14. As a next step,
we need to update the Docker compose file to use these s14 docker images and along with that we need
to remove Rabbitmq related service details and introduce the Kafka service details.
But here there is a problem for me.
I validated the Apache Kafka official website to understand if there is any information on how to set
up Kafka with the help of Docker.
But unfortunately I didn't find anything. Post that,
after doing some good research, I found some information on how to set up Apache Kafka with the help
of docker or  docker compose.
So this information I have inside this GitHub repo which is maintained by the Bitnami.
So what is this Bitnami,
Bitnami is a kind of marketplace where they are going to help you to set up any kind of application
in any kind of environment like Cloud, Docker, Kubernetes.
So this is a very trusted company or this is a very trusted community because this is also supported
by the VMware.
So that's why we can safely use the docker compose instructions provided by them.
So I'm going to mention these URL details inside the GitHub repo as well.
Here if you try to see this format is very familiar to us.
First, they are trying to create a service with the name Kafka and they have provided the image details,
Portmapping and there is some volumes configuration.
So regarding this volumes configuration in the down, you should be able to see that with the help of
these volumes, they are trying to create a folder inside your local system with the name kafka_data.
The same
they are trying to map to the folder Bitnami present inside the Docker container.
That means the Kafka that we are going to set up with these Docker compose file.
It is going to store all the data inside your local system with the folder name as Kafka data.
And after these volumes configuration, we have some environment details which we need to follow.
So by taking these information, I have updated our Docker compose files.
If you see here inside our Docker compose file, previously we used to have rabbit related service.
I have deleted that and right now I have pasted all the content that we have from the Bitnami GitHub
repo.
So once you have defined these Kafka related information, we need to make sure we are tagging this
service to the same network where we are trying to start all the remaining microservices.
Now let me go to the accounts micro service related configurations.
Here previously we used to have depends on Rabbit.
I have deleted that and after that I also created a new environment variable with the name Spring Cloud
spring_cloud_stream_kafka_binder_brokers. The same
we also created inside the application.yml. Inside the application.yml
we have mentioned the localhost, but here we need to mention what is the service name of Kafka.
So the service name is going to be Kafka and it is available at the port 9092.
The same environment variable I need to mention inside the message configuration as well.
So you can see here I have created the same.
After making all these changes, I also make sure that the tag name is updated from s13 to s14.
These are the only changes that I have done inside the Docker Compose files.
Now as a next step, I can try to start all my containers with the help of Docker compose up command.
Before that, I need to stop all the running instances and containers inside my local system. So I make
sure all my microservices are stopped.
We should also stop the running local Apache Kafka server for the same inside the terminal where I have
started my Apache Kafka server.
I'm going to press control C that will stop the running Kafka server. Along with the Kafka server
we should also stop the running container of Keycloak because behind the scenes my Docker compose file
is going to start a new container.
So now I have stopped all the running containers and running servers inside my local system.
As a next step, I can try to run the Docker compose command.
So the command is going to be docker compose up -d.
This will start all my containers and it is going to take couple of minutes.
Let me wait for this to complete behind the scenes.
After couple of minutes all my containers started successfully.
As a next step, I need to set up the client details inside the keycloak.
For the same,
I came to my keycloak website and here I'm going to click on this administration console and enter
the.
Admin credentials.
Post that I will try to create a new client by using this create client option and mention the client
id as easybank-callcenter-cc.
So let me click on this next button and enable this client authentication followed by disabling the
standard flow direct Access grants.
After that, I'm going to enable these service account roles.
Now I'm going to click on this next button, save and post that I will try to get my credentials.
So let me copy these credentials and mention the same inside my postman.
Now my client is created but it does not have enough roles assigned.
Let me try to assign the same.
Here first I'll go to Realm Roles post that
I'll click on this create role and create a role with the name accounts.
So let me save this and I'll go back to clients and open the client that we have created.
And here I will click on this service account roles and using this assign role, I will try to assign
the role with the name accounts.
So now we have assigned the role to our client.
As a next step, I can try to test the API with the help of Postman.
So here, first let me try to get the access token using this get new access token.
The same I'm going to use inside my request post that I'm going to invoke this post API by using this
send button.
After few seconds, I got a successful response now to confirm whether the communication between accounts
and message happened or not.
With the help of Kafka and asynchronous communication, we need to validate the logs available inside
the containers of accounts and message microservice.
So here, first I'm going to open the message microservice logs.
Here you will be able to see there are some logs related to sending email with the details and sending
sms with the details.
Along with that, there are some other details related to the consume coordinator offset information.
So this confirms right now my message microservice is leveraging Apache Kafka.
So now let me go back to the containers and open the accounts microservice container logs.
And here we have the log, which is is the communication request successfully triggered?
There is a value true and post that we also have another logger saying that updating communication status
for the so and so account number.
So this confirms that the communication between two microservice is happening with the help of event
streaming platform which is Apache Kafka.
I hope you are clear with the demo.
Before we try to close this section, let me confirm you that I have mentioned that all the changes
that we have done inside the slides as well, we have just done two changes.
The very first one is replacing the rabbit related maven dependency with the Kafka and Post that we
also updated the Kafka connection details inside the application.yml of accounts and message microservice.
So I just mentioned them for your quick reference.
I also want to confirm you that I checked in all the code that we have discussed inside this section
14 into this folder inside the GitHub repo and you can see the comments against this folder which is
event driven microservices using Kafka, Spring cloud functions and stream.
With this we are done discussing about the challenge, which is building event driven microservices.
And in the same process we explored two products.
One is Rabbitmq and the other one is Apache Kafka.
So with these information you should be able to clear any interview whenever they are trying to ask
you questions around the event driven microservices.
You can impress them by talking about the capabilities provided by the spring cloud functions and spring
cloud stream.
Before you try to close this lecture, I have a request.
Please provide your review to the course.
If you are not provided as of now, please, please take a minute and provide your feedback inside the
Udemy.
This helps me as an instructor to understand your feedback and at the same time it is also going to
help to reach other students who are trying to learn the microservice course.
If you want to share the feedback personally to me, please send a message inside Udemy or LinkedIn.
Or you can also send an email to me by writing an email to tutor@easybytes.com.
You have all my contact details inside my website, which is easybytes.com, so please spare two minutes
to provide your feedback.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next section.
Bye.