In the previous lecture, we decided to create a Kubernetes cluster in the cloud with the help of Google
Cloud.
To get started on the same first, we need to visit cloud.google.com.
And here inside this website you can log in with your Gmail account. If you are logged in to this website
very first time, it is going to offer you $300 free credit that you can use within 90 days.
But if you have already used a Gmail account previously inside this website, I would recommend creating
a new Gmail account and log in again into this website so that you will be eligible to get a $300 free
credit.
I already logged in into this website using a gmail and since I'm a new user into this website with
my gmail, it is offering me to take the $300 free credit and explore more than 20 plus products with
this free credit.
So if you click on this banner, you will be taken to a website where you can see all the details about
your free credit.
If you can scroll down on this page, under this free tier products, you will be able to see a product
with the name Google Kubernetes Engine.
So this is the same product that we want to use to create a Kubernetes cluster inside the Google Cloud.
And since this is eligible under the free tier, I can use that $300 free credit that I'm going to get
whenever I create a new account.
So this is the main reason or a primary reason on why I choose Google Cloud compared to AWS and Azure.
I hope you are clear.
Let me close this tab.
Post that once you logged in into this website, you can click on this console button and if you are
landing on to this console page, very first time, it is going to offer you $300 free trial that you
need to use within 90 days.
You can click on this, try for free.
And with that it will ask you all your personal details to which country you belong and what best describes
about me.
Here
I'm going to select business idea slash startup idea was that I can select this checkbox under the terms
of services and click on this continue button.
Before that, you can also see here Google Cloud is going to give $300 in credit spend over the next
90 days and they are also assuring no auto charge after free trial ends.
Once you read all this information, you can click on this continue button.
Inside this page,
it is going to ask your credit card details.
All the cloud providers, they will ask your credit card details because after the free credit, if
you start using the other products, like creating a database or creating a server or creating a Kubernetes
cluster, they want you to charge.
That's why please, please make sure you are not creating unnecessary products inside the cloud and
always be cautious on what you create whenever you are done exploring about a product, please make
sure you are deleting the product so that you are not spending your $300 free credit within 1 or 2 days.
For some reason, if you are not comfortable providing your credit card details, please don't provide
them.
You can always see the steps that I'm following at the process that I'm following to understand the
steps that we need to follow to deploy our microservices into the cloud
kubernetes cluster.
Behind the scenes, I'm going to enter all my credit card details once the credit card details are entered
and validated by the Google Cloud, you can click on this button, which is Start my free trial.
Once you enter your credit card details
and the same is validated by the Google Cloud, it is going to show you a message something like this,
setting up your billing and in the down
also you should be able to see a confirmation saying that setting up your free trial.
So please give some time for this to complete.
After a few seconds you will be landed onto the Google Cloud Console homepage.
If not, you can visit the console.cloud.google.com.
And this is how it is going to look like.
By the time you logged in onto this page, the Google Cloud by default is going to create a project
with the name my first project, and this is the ID of your project.
Using this project, you can explore all the products with the help of $300 free credits.
So to get started around this, so now I can create a Kubernetes cluster inside the Google Cloud.
But before that we need to make sure we install the cloud SDK inside our local system.
Why should I install the Google Cloud SDK?
Because when we install this cloud SDK inside our local system, from our local system itself, we can
connect with the Kubernetes cluster that is created inside the Google Cloud and from our local system
itself
we can give some commands or we can also install our helm charts from our local system.
So to communicate with the products available inside the Google Cloud from your local system, we need
to make sure we install this cloud SDK.
So please visit this website, which is cloud.google.com/sdk.
On this page you can click on this, Get started in this page you will be having all the steps that
you need to
followed to install the Google Cloud CLI.
So before we try to begin, we need to make sure we completed these two steps.
One is creating a Google Cloud project which we already created previously because as of now I'm able
to see my project, which is my first project.
After that, we should also make sure the building is enabled for our Google Cloud project.
We did that in the previous steps by providing a credit card details.
If you can scroll down on this page based upon your operating system, you will be having the list of
steps that you need to follow to install the Google Cloud cli.
So please make sure you are following these steps based upon your operating system.
Since I'm using Mac OS, I already followed all these steps and installed the Google cloud CLI inside
my local system. So to confirm if your installation is successful or not, you can run a command which
is gcloud - -version.
So you can run this command inside your terminal from any location.
If the installation is successful, you're going to get an output
something like this.
And once you validate the installation, you need to run a command which is gcloud init. Using this gcloud
init,
we are going to login into our Google cloud account from our local system with the help of Google Cloud.
So let me run this command.
This will give some options to me.
I will go with the third option, which is it is going to reinitialize my existing configuration with
the name default.
So let me choose this third option and post that it is going to perform some network connection.
Once the network connection is successful, it is going to ask you whether I want to log in into my
Google Cloud account.
So here, please make sure you are giving the answer as Y, which means yes and post that it will open
your browser where you need to select your gmail account using which you want to log in into the Google
cloud.
So I'm selecting the Gmail account.
After you select your Gmail account, it will also ask you for your permission whether I want to provide
some privileges to the Google Cloud SDK to access my Google account details.
So I am going to click on this allow button and with that you will see this page which is your now authenticated
with the Google Cloud CLI.
You can also confirm inside the terminal.
Inside the terminal you can see I got an output saying that pick one of the Google cloud project to
use.
So the project that just now we created is liquid-muse-397814.
So that's why I'm going to give the input as one and post that I'll press enter and with that you will
get an output saying that your Google Cloud SDK is configured and ready to use.
It will also show you the email account and the project that you are connected with the help of Google
Cloud SDK.
I hope you are clear on how to set up a free account inside the Google Cloud and how to connect to the
same with the help of Google Cloud CLI.
As a next step, we can start creating a Kubernetes cluster inside the Google Cloud.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.