In the previous lecture, we have created a simple rest API that says hello to the world.
Now before we try to build other rest APIs which will help us to expose the crud operations to the clients.
First, we need to make sure that our database related code is completed and it is available for us
to interact with the database.
As of now, we are using internal H2 database to use this history database.
We can define some properties or configurations inside our application.
For the same, we need to go to these resource folder and this resource folder.
We have application.properties file.
As of now you can see it is an empty file inside this property file only we can define all the configurations
related to Spring Boot where we can mention the port number which needs to be considered by the spring
boot,
to start the service we can define database related configurations, we can define message queues,
related configurations, we can define actuator related configurations.
So there are good amount of properties or configurations that we can define inside this file, which
will make developer life easy.
With the properties that we mentioned inside this file, Spring Boot is going to do a lot of work behind
the scenes.
So instead of we writing the Java code or lot of boilerplate code to handle all those logic, we simply
mention the properties inside this file and Spring Boot is going to take care of connecting to database,
starting the server at the mentioned port number and enabling certain features of actuator.
This way we can achieve many functionality with these properties, but we are not going to write our
properties with the format of key and value, which is the default way inside spring boot.
Instead, we are going to define all our properties with the Yaml format.
So for the same what I'm going to do is I'm going to close this application.properties and rename this
file from application.properties to application.yml yml indicates that this file is going to support
the yml format.
So yml is a very famous format, just like XML and json.
Yml is the latest and mostly used format.
The reason why I'm using .yml format instead of .properties is Yml is very intuitive in nature.
We can easily read the Yaml file very easily and the same Yml format is going to be used inside Docker,
Kubernetes or any cloud providers that you go like AWS, GCP, Azure.
Since many places this is being used in future also, definitely
i'm confident that Spring Boot will move to the .yml format.
So right now it is supporting both .properties and .yml since we can achieve more with the help
of yaml format, I'm pretty sure that in future spring boot is going to migrate to .yml format.
With that reasons, let's try to define the properties with the help of .yml.
But here you may have questions like how can I define properties with the help of Yaml format?
What is the syntax that I need to follow?
So you may have many questions.
So let me give a quick introduction about Yaml syntax.
If you see this file, these are the normal property values that I can mention whenever I'm using
.properties format.
So you can see this is the key and this is the value.
So there will be a key and there will be a value.
The same applies for all other properties.
Every property will have a key and it is going to have a corresponding value.
So these are the properties and it is very clear for everyone there is no big complexity here
there is a key, there is a value.
So now let's try to understand how to represent this inside a yaml,yaml is going to work based upon
indentation.
When I say indentation you can see whenever I want to define this server.port as a key inside yaml
I need to first mention server followed by : post that I should immediately go to a tab space inside
my next row.
Like you can see here I have given a tab space.
Then only my Yaml is going to consider the key as
server.port.
And very similarly for spring.datasource.url.
I need to mention spring followed by a tab space
datasource: and since inside data source we are
going to have the URL we need to mention the URL again with the tab space.
So you can see I have mentioned the tab space here.
The advantage of Yaml, you can see this spring is repeated unnecessarily inside properties file for
every key, whereas with yaml it is going to have only once inside the same spring
we can define data source only once, whereas in property you can see it is repeated four times and
at last we reached to the end of the key which is URL.
Once we reach, we need to give the : and post the :
we need to make sure we are giving a single space followed by what is the value?
This is the value that,
i want to mention the same I have done for
driverClassName and user name and password.
And since I want to give empty password, I have given a single quote with empty value.
And very similarly, if you see for this property which is
spring.h2.console.enabled = true.
I don't need to mention the spring again.
I can straight away come to the same location where that data source is present and in the same location.
I can start the new key, which is h2.
This way I need to maintain this indentation properly.
Then only my Yaml is going to work.
If I screw up this indentation then my Yaml is not going to work.
That's why
Please please make sure you are giving the same space, same indentation like I was giving inside the
GitHub repo.
So let me copy these properties and I can mention inside the application.yml so you can see these
are the values that I have mentioned inside my .yml file.
I also installed a Yaml related plugin inside my ID.
That's why it is able to recognize this file as Yaml file based upon the extension that I have mentioned
here.
So with the server.port we are telling to the spring boot framework to start the port at 8080.
This is the default port, even if you don't mention it is going to consider the same, but it is a
good practice to mention the same inside your applications.yml file.
And when we are going to build other microservice, definitely we can't leave with 8080 because it is
already being used by the accounts
Microservice.
So in those microservice we are going to override to some other port number now coming to these properties,
all these related to the h2 database.
So with the spring.datasource.url, I'm telling to the spring boot framework that this is the
endpoint details where my application can connect to the internal h2 database.
So Jdbc:h2:mem:testdb.
So this is the value that we need to do and the
driverClassName we need to do org.h2.Driver
and username:sa
This is the default username.
If you want you can change and the password.
Also, I want to go with the default password, which is an empty value with the help of this
spring.h2.console.enabled.
I'm telling to the spring boot framework to enable the h2 console so that I can login into this h2 console
from my browser and I can see all the tables and records that are inserted are created into my internal
h2 database.
And very similarly we need to mention other properties like Spring.jpa.database platform and
the database platform that we are using is 2 dialect.
And with this spring.jpa.hibernate.ddl-auto as update we are telling to the spring boot framework.
If there are no tables created inside my internal h2 database, please go ahead and create them based upon
the SQL instructions that I'm going to provide automatically during the startup.
So that's the purpose here.
We don't want to create the tables every time manually inside our internal history database.
We want that process to be automatically happen when server is being started because h2 database is
an internal memory database
whenever you shut down the server, all the data and all the tables that you have created will be wiped
off
that's why to overcome the challenge of creating the tables and data manually every time we can provide
some SQL scripts based upon that, my spring boot framework can automatically create these tables behind
the scenes during the startup.
And at last we also mentioned spring.jpa.show sql as true with this property we are telling to the
spring boot framework.
Please print all the SQL queries that you are going to execute against the history database on the console,
and with this the developers can see what are the queries that are being executed behind the scenes
by the Spring Data JPA framework.
And these queries are going to help them during the debugging process.
I hope you are clear with these properties, please make sure you are also using these Yaml format.
This format is going to help you to work on multiple products like Docker, Kubernetes and cloud environments.
So let me save these changes.
Now, like I said, during startup we want some tables to be created so that we can store that data
inside these tables.
For the same Under these resources folder, you need to create a new file with the name schema.sql
Whenever you want to create the tables columns, you need to define a file with the name
shema.sql.
Whereas if you want to create data with the help of insert scripts or update scripts, you can define
a file with the name data.sql.
For now, I just want to create the tables inside my internal database.
So now inside this SQL file, I'm going to paste a few scripts.
So these are the scripts that I have pasted just now.
I'm
not typing all of them in front of you just to save some time here, please get these scripts from the
GitHub repo and you can also paste inside your \
schema.sql.
The same you can do for application.yml file as well throughout the course
i'm only going to type very important code in front of you to save some time.
You can always pass the video, you can always get the code from GitHub repo or you can type the code
by seeing at the screen, but please make sure you are passing the video.
So I'm doing this so that we can learn more with less time.
Because if I start typing all the hundreds and thousands of lines of code that we are going to discuss,
definitely the length of the course is going to become more since I want to teach you more with less
time so that you can learn quickly.
That's why I'm following this strategy.
I hope you understand.
So now let me save these changes and do a build once the build is completed.
Since my application is already started and we have dev tools inside our classpath, my dev tools might
have restarted the server.
You can see this time my server restarted in 1.237 seconds and my spring boot framework
considered all the details that we have given for the history database.
And you can see by default the spring boot framework is going to expose the h2 console with this path,
which is h2/console.
So let me try to access this h2 console in the browser.
So I need to go to the localhost 8080 followed by
h2 /console and here I'm trying to access it.
You can see you will get this page where you need to enter all your driver class, Jdbc URL, username
and password.
By default, these values will get automatically populated.
Please make sure the values are matching with what you have mentioned inside the applications.yml
file.
So the username is password is empty.
I'm just clicking on this
Connect with that.
This is the h2 console where you can see there are two tables created with the name accounts and customers.
My accounts table has columns like customer_Id,
account _Number, account_Type branch_Address created_At
created_By updated_At and updated_By very similarly, if I click on this customer, it has columns
like customer_Id, name, email, mobile_Number created_At, updated_At and updated_By.
So these tables are created based upon the scripts that we have provided inside the schema.sql file.
So if you try to understand these scripts first, I'm trying to create a customer table where we are
trying to save the name of the bank customer.
What is his email?
What is the mobile number?
And a few metadata related columns like Created_At created_By,updated_At and updated_By
So these four metadata columns are going to present in each of the table that I'm going to create inside
this course.
So this is the another standard that you need to follow inside the real projects.
These columns will help us who created the data, at what time the data is created and who updated the
data at what time.
I hope you understand.
For this customer table, a primary key is going to be customer_Id column and it is going to be automatically
incremented whenever I'm trying to insert a new record into the database.
So this is what we are trying to achieve with these customer table creation.
And the table will be created only if it not existed in the database.
Now, coming to the accounts table, you can see I'm mentioning the customer_Id column and there is
going to be a foreign key link between these customer and accounts table with these customer_Id column
and inside these accounts table, we are going to have a column with the name account number which will
act as a primary key and post that.
We'll also have columns like what is the account_Type, whether the account type is saving account or
current account, and what is the branch _Address followed by metadata columns.
So I'm just trying to keep the things simple so that we can focus more on the microservice concept rather
than creating complex tables, complex mappings and do a lot of unnecessary things.
I hope you are fine with that.
With this, we set up the h2 database with the help of this schema.sql file and with the properties
mentioned inside the application.yml file in the next lecture.
Let's try to build the code with the help of spring Data JPA that will help us to interact with this
h2 database and the tables that we can start leveraging this database for insert data, for reading
data, for updating and deleting the data.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.