Now inside this lecture, let's try to create a REST API that will help to fetch the account and customer
details present inside the database by accepting the mobile number as an input.
Any end user or client application, they'll pass the mobile number to our REST API and based upon the
data present inside the database, it is going to send all the customer and bank account details. For
the same
First, we need to create a new method inside the AccountsController.
So the method access type is going to be public and we are going to send the customer DTO as a response.
So let me mention customer DTO inside the response entity and the method name is going to be
fetchAccountDetails().
And to this method we need to pass the annotation which is @RequestParam because since we
are trying to accept only one request value which is mobile number with the help of query params, we
need to make sure we are mentioning @RequestParam here and post that space followed by string,
followed by mobile number which is the field name.
Now inside this method I can write all the business logic, but before that I need to make sure I'm
mentioning the GetMapping annotation on top of this method because this method is going to help you
to fetch the resource details from the database.
That's why we need to use the get mapping whenever we are trying to read the data and the API path that
this method is going to support is /fetch.
So whenever someone is trying to invoke the path, which is API /fetch, this method will be invoked.
Now as a next step, we need to go to the IAccountService and here we need to create one new abstract
method with the name fetchAccount() that is going to accept the mobile number as the input parameter
and going to return customer DTO as an output object.
So once we define this abstract method, the very next step, obviously we need to go to the
AccountServiceImpl  and we need to make sure we are implementing the method.
There will be an error like you can see here.
Let's hover on that and click on this implement methods and click okay.
The empty fetch account method created.
Let me take this method and paste this after this Create new account method.
That's where we have a proper sequence.
So now inside this fetchAccount() method, we need to write a logic to fetch the account details and
customer details from the database.
But when we try to fetch the details from the database based upon a mobile number, there is a good
chance there might be no customer, no account details for a given mobile number.
In such scenarios, we should be able to throw an custom business exception For the same, we need to
go to the exception package and here, just like customer already exception, I'm going to create a
new exception with the name ResourceNotFound exception.
So let me create this class and here instead of bad request, I'm going to mention the Http status as
not found because we are trying to throw an business error saying that so and so resource is not found,
for the given input.
And to this constructor this time I'm not going to pass a one parameter.
I'm going to pass multiple parameters to throw a detail exception to my end user or to the client application.
The three fields are going to be what is the resource name like, whether it is accounts or customer
and what is the field name and what is the field value?
The field name,
Obviously we are trying to fetch based upon the mobile number, so it will throw a detail message to
the end user or client application that you are trying to fetch account details based upon your mobile
number with so and so value,
And we are not able to find that.
That's how we are going to throw an message to the client application.
Now we have a problem here.
The problem is this runtime exception constructor.
It is going to accept only a single string as an input parameter.
So what we have to do is we need to prepare a single string value based upon these three input fields
from the ResourceNotFound exception constructor.
For the same, I'm going to use a string.format() method using this string.format() method.
I'm passing these three strings.
These three strings will be replaced wherever I have mentioned these
%s.
So, so and so resource not found with the given input data field name.
And what is the field value?
So with this we should be good with these exception.
As a next step, we need to go to the global exception handler and we need to make sure we are writing
a method very similar to these handle customer already exist.
Exception So let me copy this method and paste it.
So now we have two methods with the same name.
Let's try to fix this compilation error.
So the very first method I'm trying to change to a new method name which is handle resource,
ResourseNotFound exception.
And this method is going to handle the exception which is ResourceNotFound exception.
So here the logic is going to be the same, but instead of,
bad requests we need to send Not_Found the same I want to send as part of the response entity status
as well.
So with this we are good from an exception handling perspective.
Now let's go to the AccountServiceImpl.
So here we need to write the logic to fetch the account details and customer details based upon the
mobile number.
So I'm going to write a code here first, with the help of customerRepository, I'm trying to invoke
a method findByMobileNumber().
And to this method I'm going to pass the received mobile number.
And if there is no record with the given mobile number, I'm going to invoke orElseThrow() method because
this find by mobile number is going to return a optional of customer inside optional.
We have a method called orElseThrow() using which we can throw an exception if there is no record present
inside the optional.
So here I'm going to write a lambda expression which is not going to accept any input parameter, but
I'm simply going to throw an error which is new
ResourceNotFound exception.
And to this constructor I'm going to pass three parameters.
The very first one is what is the resource that I'm not able to find?
Customer is a resource because with a given mobile number we are not able to find the customer.
And the second param value I'm going to mention as mobile number because using mobile number only,
I'm not able to fetch the resource.
And the third parameter obviously what is a mobile number value.
So with this I should be able to throw an exception whenever there is no customer available with a given
mobile number.
But if there is a customer available, I need to make sure I'm catching that customer, into a variable
called customer.
So now I'm good with this.
I'm able to fetch the customer details post that using the very similar logic, I need to make sure
I'm fetching the account details as well.
Because whenever someone is trying to invoke my rest API, they need all the details.
Like what is the customer details?
What is the account details that got created?
So first, instead of customerRepository, I need to make sure I'm using accountRepository.
Now inside my accounts table there is no mobile number using which I can query and at the same time
I cannot invoke findByID() method because inside my accounts entity the primary key value is account
number.
But I received only mobile number from my client application.
So what should I do here?
I need to create a new method inside accountsRepository just like we created find by mobile number
inside customerRepository.
So let me go to the AccountsRepository here.
I'm going to create a new method.
The method is findByCustomerId(), So based upon the customer ID, it is going to fetch the account
details.
And here you may have a question like how do we know the customer ID?
Because we didn't receive from the input request.
That's where we will use the customer object that we fetched from the database based upon the mobile
number to identify what is the customer ID for a given mobile number.
So first I need to make sure I'm invoking
findByCustomerId().
Once I invoke this, findByCustomerId(), let me replace this customer to account so that I can resolve
the compilation error that I have here.
The variable name is going to be accounts.
Now, instead of this mobile number, I'm going to pass customer.getCustomerId from thisCcustomer
object.
The same logic we are going to follow.
If there is no account with the given customer ID, we are going to throw ResourceNotFound exception,
but instead of customer here we need to mention account because we are not able to identify account
resource for a given customer ID and the value is going to be customer.getCustomerId().toString().
Of course there won't be any scenario in our application if there is a customer exist, definitely there
will be also an account resource will be available.
But this just an in case someone messed up with the data.
Then just a rare scenario that we are trying to handle here.
Now we have customer, entity and accounts entity.
Can we send this directly to the client?
Of course not, because these entities, they have a lot of sensitive information and metadata information
like createdat created by at the same time customer ID, which is unnecessary for my client application.
They only want useful information.
That's why we need to convert these entities into the Dto classes.
But as of now we have these CustomerDto and
AccountsDto as two separate classes like accountsDto
holds strictly the data related to accounts, and similarly, customer data holds the data related
to customer only if you want to send the combined information or aggregated information of both CustomerDto
and AccountsDto
We have two options.
Either we can create one more Dto class where we can try to refer both these Dto classes are inside these CustomerDto
or we can create one more field,
Of type AccountsDto and with the field name as
AccountsDto.
So this way also we can achieve the Dto pattern.
So I'm going to follow this approach, but if you want, you can also create separate Dto class.
But I would recommend that approach only if your Dto has lot number of fields and they are very big
in nature.
But for these smaller application this should be fine.
I'll go to the AccountServiceImpl and here first, with the help of CustomerMapper, I'm going to invoke
mapToCustomerDto() and to this method we need to pass what is the customer along with the new object
of customerDto?
The same
I'm going to catch into a variable of type customerDto for this.
I can go to the next line here.
I'm going to invoke customerDto.setAccountsDto and to this setter method.
I need to pass the Dto of my accounts entity.
So let me invoke the AccountsMapper here and using this AccountsMapper, I'm going to invoke map two
accounts and I'm going to pass accounts to new, AccountsDto.
So with this we should be good and I'm going to return this customerDto from this method.
So now let me go to the controller layer.
Inside my controller layer.
I'm going to write business logic here to invoke my
IAccountService and the method fetchAccount().
And to this method I'm going to pass the mobile number.
And from this method we are going to get the customerDto.
So let me try to catch the same here on the left hand side with the help of this CustomerDto object.
Once I have this CustomerDto object, I can try to write a return statement with the help of
ResponseEntity.status and the status is going to be
HttpStatus.OK.
Okay
means the operation is successful and I'm sending the data to you.
So with the help of body() method, I'm invoking and passing the object of the CustomerDto.
So with this, our method is ready right now.
So let me save this changes and do a build.
Once the build is completed, my server will be restarting.
Like I said before, whenever my server is restarting, my data will be lost inside the h2database.
We can also try to validate the same.
So I'm trying to refresh the page here.
So let me connect again.
I'm trying to search for accounts so you can see the data.
Everything is wiped off.
So what we can do is this is a temporary problem that we are going to face till we migrate to the MySQL
database in the coming sections.
As a workaround, I'm going to invoke this create API.
Again, the account is created successfully.
Now I'll take this mobile number.
I'm going to open this fetch account details request and here I need to invoke localhost8080api/fetch
and mobile number is a query param that we need to pass.
That's why there is a question mark.
What is the query param name, mobile number.
And to this query param I'm going to pass the value of my mobile number.
Please make sure this name is matching with whatever you have mentioned here as a request param.
So now I'm going to click on this Send button and like you can see here, I got a response saying that
that this is the name of the customer, this is the email, this is the mobile number.
And inside this customer details there is an embedded object with the name account and it has details
like account number, account type and branch address.
Now if I try to invoke the same API with a mobile number that does not exist inside my database, I
should get an exception.
I'm getting an exception, but it is not coming the way that I design.
So there is an issue in our code.
Let me check the same,here
we made a mistake.
Like when we build this handle ResourceNotFound exception, we are accepting a customer already exist
exception instead of ResourceNotFound exception.
So let me correct this issue.
Please ignore my mistake here.
Let me do a build.
Sometimes these issues happen regardless how experienced you are.
This kind of small mistakes will always happen.
That's why debugging and unit testing is very important inside any project.
So since I'm doing unit testing, I'm able to identify this issue.
Now, my server might have restarted, but regardless, I can still test this API because we are trying
to test the native scenario only here.
So if I try to invoke here, you can see I'm getting a proper response saying that this is the error
code, this is the error message saying that customer not found with the given input data mobile number.
And this is a mobile number that I sent in the request with this.
I'm assuming your super, super clear about the fetch operation that we have implemented inside
AccountsService.
So please validate your changes inside your local by comparing with the code that you have inside the
GitHub repo.
I'm assuming you're following me and you're having a lot of fun and you're learning a lot of new things
here inside this course.
Thank you.
And I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.