We handle runtime exceptions and custom exceptions inside our AccountsMicroservices.
.
One more standard that we need to follow when we are building microservices and REST APIs is, we need
to perform validations on the input data that we receive from the client applications.
We are right now accepting various kinds of data from our clients.
Like you can see here they are passing the name, email and mobileNumber.
What if someone is sending a nine digit or five digit mobile number instead of ten digit?
What if someone is not following the email format?
What if someone is sending a name with a value of only two characters and three characters?
And very similarly, someone, while trying to invoke these get API, they can send a mobile number
of five digit value or four digit value instead of ten digit value.
Off course, in this scenario you may question me like there's nothing wrong going to happen anyway
the end user is going to get a response saying that there is no such account with a given mobile number.
That's a valid question, but you are unnecessarily firing a DB query with an invalid data.
We should straight away reject such invalid data from our REST APIs.
Same applies for update account details.
If they're trying to send some account number which is not of type ten digit and account type as empty
branch address as empty.
So there are multiple combinations.
The client applications and end users they can miss and they can screw up.
That's why as an developer we need to make sure we are doing enough validations on the input data that
we receive to our REST APIs.
So let's try to perform these input validations inside this lecture.
Any time, whenever we want to perform validations first, we need to make sure we have added relevant
dependency inside the pom.xml like we discussed before, we added this dependency, which is spring
boot starter validation when we are trying to create this microservice with the help of start.spring.io
website.
This dependency has all the annotations and libraries that will help us to enforce the validations on
the input data that we receive from the clients.
So once we validated this step, we can go to the DTO classes.
As of now we have four Dto's First, let's go to the CustomerDto the reason why I open these class
is whatever data that we receive from the clients will get converted into CustomerDto.
So these DTOs are going to hold the data that we are going to receive from clients, which means my
spring boot has to perform the validations on the data stored inside the object of this CustomerDto
or any other DTO like AccountsDto.
So since we want to enforce some validations on the input received from the clients, we need to make
sure we are mentioning all our validation requirements with the help of annotations inside the Spring
Boot framework.
The very first and basic attention that we can use is @NotEmpty.
So whenever we are mentioning this @NotEmpty, we are making that field as mandatory field.
So whenever someone is trying to send this name value, it has to be mandatory, like it should not
be empty or null value.
The same I want to mention for email as well.
So let me mention the same.
Now,
whenever a validation fails due to this NotEmpty annotation that we mentioned here, we want to throw
a custom message to the client application so that they are clear about which data is wrong.
For the same, we need to invoke the message parameter against this annotation and inside this message
parameter. I'm going to mention the message like name cannot be null or empty.
The same I can do for email as well.
I'm going to invoke the message here and mention the message saying that email address cannot be null
or empty.
So we have mentioned this NotEmpty validation on top of this name and email, which makes the fields
as mandatory.
If you see this NotEmpty annotation present inside this Jakarta.validations.constraints package.
If I can open this annotation and go to the same package, you can see there are many other annotations
that we can use to enforce the validations on top of our Java fields like digits will make sure we are
accepting only numeric and similarly, email will validate the format of the email and future, will
make sure that the date that we are accepting is of type future very similarly max, minimum,negative.
NotBlank, NotEmpty, NotNull null past pattern to enforce some rejects patterns.
This way we have a lot of annotations that you can use based upon your business requirements.
Now I want to enforce one more validation on top of my name field with the help of Size annotation using
the Size annotation, we can mention what is the minimum length of value that we are going to accept.
And similarly, using Max, we can mention what is the maximum value that we are going to accept.
If this validation fails.
I'm going to throw a message saying that the length of the customer name
should be between 5 and 30.
This will make sure we are receiving a name value with at least five length characters and at a maximum
of 30 chars.
So we are good with the name.
Now on top of email, I want to enforce email format related validations, so that's why I need to invoke
@Email annotation.
And if these email validation fails, I want to throw a message saying that email address should be
a valid value.
Suppose if I try to forget mentioning @Symbol inside my email value, then I'll get these
validation error message.
Now coming to the mobile number, we want to make sure that we always receive a mobile number in numeric
format and the numeric value also should be exactly ten digit number and it should not be like nine
digit or 11 digit.
I want exactly ten digit numeric value.
But these kind of requirements, we can use a annotation which is @Pattern with the help
of @Pattern annotation, we can invoke rejects expression and to these rejects expression
we can pass what is the expression that we want to follow.
So this is the pattern that I want to follow.
This will make sure that I'm accepting only numeric values with exactly ten digits post that I need
to mention.
What is the message that I want to throw in case of this validation fails?
The message that I want to throw here is mobile number must be ten digits.
So with this, we have mentioned all the validation related annotations inside CustomerDto.
Next, we can go to the AccountsDto here inside my AccountsDto. For the account number, I want to
follow the same pattern like mobile number.
Just like for mobile number, we are accepting ten digit numeric value for account number
also, we should follow the same pattern.
So here for account number also I'm going to mention these annotations like @Pattern and
@NotEmpty that will make sure that my account number is going to be a mandatory value.
Similarly, for account type, we can mention @NotEmpty, the same I can mention for branch
address as well.
So let me pass the message values.
So the message value that I want to pass here is account type cannot be null or empty.
Similarly, I want to follow the same for branch address as well.
The validation message that I want to throw here is branch address cannot be a null or empty.
So with this we have mentioned all the validation related annotations inside our DTO classes like Accounts
and Customer.
We don't have to mention inside ResponseDto and ErrorResponseDto.
The reason is these two DTOs we don't get as an input from the client applications.
We always use these DTOs to send the response to them.
That's why we don't have to perform validations or we don't have to mention any validations inside these
DTO.
Now as a next step, we need to go to the place where we are trying to use these AccountsDto and CustomerDto,
like you expect we are accepting them as an input inside our AccountsController.
So you can see here I'm accepting the RequestBody in the format of CustomerDto and the same for the
update operation as well.
So here also we need to mention some annotations.
The very first annotation that I want to mention here is @Validated on top of my AccountsController
class.
So this annotation will tell to my spring boot framework to perform validations on all the REST APIs
that I have defined inside these AccountsController.
.
Now, as a next step, we need to mention an annotation which is @Valid just before the RequestBody
The v should be capital V, so this is the annotation which is @Valid.
We need to mention just before the RequestBody annotation to communicate to the spring boot framework
to perform all the validations that we mentioned inside this duo.
So the same I have to mention for my update operation as well just before this RequestBody annotation.
So we are good right now for create and update operations.
What about these fetch account details and delete account details.
Here we are not accepting the input data with the help of DTOs.
We are directly accepting them with the help of query parameters.
So to perform validations on these mobile number, what we can do is just after this request param,
we can mention @Pattern validation, very similar to what we have mentioned inside the dto
class.
So with the help of @Pattern, I'm accepting a reject expression that will make sure that
I'm receiving only ten digit numeric value.
The same I can mention for deleteAccountDetails method as well.
So here also I'm going to perform the same validation ten digit numeric value.
So now we have mentioned all the input validations that we want to perform. As a next step
we should let spring boot framework what it has to do whenever these validations fails, it knows what
validations it has to perform.
.
The framework also knows what message it has to throw to the end user or client application, but it
does not know how to send that inside the error response or inside the body of the response.
For the same, what we have to do is we can go to the GlobalExceptionHandler.
Here we need to extend a class with the name ResponseEntityExceptionHandler After extending this class,
if you go to this class, there is a method inside this class which is handleMethodArgumentsNotValid()
.
So we need to override this method inside our GlobalExceptionHandler.
If you see it is going to get all the validation exception details as the first parameter and header
details, statusCode and WebRequest.
We need to override with the same method parameters.
So let me try to create this method and you can see this has right now empty method.
The method name has to be same and it needs to accept these four method parameters.
Now we need to write a small logic inside this method which will process all the validation exceptions
that failed and the same we need to send as part of the response with the help of this Response entity
of object.
So here I'm going to paste few lines of code.
The code is going to be super, super simple.
I'll explain line by line just to save some time.
I have pasted the code here.
So first I'm trying to create an empty map with the name validation errors and it is going to hold the
key and value of type string. Post that what I'm doing is using this exception parameter I'm invoking
getBindingResult().getAllErrors().
So this will give me all validation errors failed in the input data that I receive.
Using this list I'm trying to iterate one by one and from each error I'm trying to get what is the field where the validation
failed and what is the validation message related to the field?
If you recall, in all the places we have mentioned validation message, the same message will appear
inside the error default message.
Post that the same field name and validation message I'm populating into the HashMap validationErrors.
Once we populate all the validationErrors, I'm trying to send the validation errors as part of Response
entity with a status as BAD_REQUEST.
With this, we all set.
Let me save these changes.
Do a build once the build is completed inside the postman,
first I'll try to invoke the Create API, but before that I'll try to screw up some data
here,
I'm just removing these .com and also I'm trying to make my mobile number as nine digit.
Similarly, I'm going to make my name as only one char.
So let me click on the send button.
You can see I got the two validation errors like mobile number and name.
So for mobile number, this is the validation fail.
And for the name also this is the validation fail for email I didn't receive
maybe because I have this @ so let me remove this and try again.
So this time I'm also getting the validation error message for email as well.
So this confirms my validations are working on my create operation.
So let me roll back all these inside our AccountsController.
We need to make sure we are mentioning the annotation
AllArgsConstructor.
Previously, if you recall, we reverted these annotation to create a RuntimeException.
Right now we don't want that RuntimeException.
With that, let me save changes and do a build.
Now what I'm going to do is I'm going to invoke the Create account API with a valid data.
So let me click on the send button.
You will see the operation is successful right now because I'm sending a valid data, so I'll go to
fetch account here instead of ten digit, I'm going to send the nine digit mobile number.
You see that my API failed because mobile number must be ten digit due to this validation, my API failed.
So if I try to mention the ten digit mobile number, I'll get a proper response.
Now, if I go to my update for update, also what I'm going to do is I'm just going to remove these
@ and simply invoke these send.
I'm getting a proper error response saying that email address should be a valid value.
So for my update also it's working fine.
Now I'll go to delete. For delete
also, I'll make this mobile number as a nine digit number and click on the send button.
You can see I'm getting the same validation error.
If I try to send a valid mobile number and click on the send button, I'm getting a successful response.
This way we are performing input validations on top of all our REST APIs.
This is the standard approach that you need to follow.
Off course you can enhance this further based upon your business requirements.
I hope this is clear.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture.