In all the tables of AccountsMicroservices
we are maintaining these four metadata columns which will tell us when a record is created
by whom and when it is updated and by whom.
As of now, we are manually updating these CREATED_AT and CREATED_BY and there is a pending defect also
where we are not updating these UPDATED_AT and UPDATED_BY whenever an update operation is happening.
With the help of Spring Data JPA, we can update these metadata columns automatically, which means
we can give this responsibility to the spring data JPA because anyway, the framework is going to take
care of creating all the insert scripts, update scripts or delete scripts or select scripts, all kind
of SQL scripts
right now, everything is in the control of Spring data JPA framework.
We have not written any single SQL query inside our application. Since spring Data
JPA is taking care of all SQL interactions and database interactions.
We can hand over this responsibility of updating these four metadata columns. And spring data
JPA also support these auditing feature.
So in order to achieve these auditing by spring data JPA first we need to go to the entity class where
we have these four metadata columns.
So inside this BaseEntity we are mentioning these four metadata columns.
So here on top of these createdAt, we need to mention an annotation which is CreatedDate and very
similarly on top of createdBy we need to mention an annotation which is CreatedBy and on top of updated
at field we need to mention an annotation which is LastModifiedDate and for updatedBy
also we need to mention an annotation which is LastModifiedBy.
So these are the four annotations supported by the spring data framework itself.
With these annotations we are telling to the spring framework.
Whenever you see these fields inside a table or an entity, please make sure you are updating the date
time based upon when the record is being updated or inserted.
The same applies for last modified date as well, and with the help of createdBy and last modified
by, we are telling to the Spring data JPA framework like who is trying to create or update the records
inside the database table.
But here there is a problem.
My spring data framework can get that date time from the server or from the local system.
How about who is creating or who is updating that data?
It does not have any clue.
For the same, we need to write a small logic in order to write the small logic.
Let me create a new package with the name audit.
So inside this audit package I'm going to create a new class with the name AuditAwareImpl.
.
So this is the class that I want to create.
And this class should extend a class called AuditorAware since our createdBy and updatedBy are of
type String, we need to make sure we are mentioning this String here.
So whenever we extend this class we need to override a method so for the same, let me click on this
more actions and implement methods.
So this is the method that I need to implement.
The method is getCurrentAuditor().
So I need to write a logic inside this method to make sure I am returning
who is the current auditor so that my spring data JPA framework can leverage it to update the createdBy
and updatedBy whenever is needed.
I think this is an interface.
We should use implements here, so let me use the implements.
So now inside this method I'm going to write a small logic.
The logic is instead of returning a empty value, I'm going to return an hardcoded value which is
ACCOUNTS_MS.
MS means micro service.
So this is the value that I want to be considered by the Spring Data JPA framework whenever it is trying
to populate the columns createdBy and updatedBy later on when we integrate our micro services with
the Spring security framework to enforce security on micro services, I'll be showing you how to populate
the logged in user or logged in client application till to the point we integrate to the spring security
framework.
We need to continue with this hardcoded value.
So now I need to make sure that I'm mentioning @Component annotation on top of this and giving
a name AuditAwareImpl.
So this is a bean name that I want to consider.
This name can be anything.
I'm just trying to match with this class name.
So once we define this component, we need to go to the BaseEntity and here we need to mention an annotation
which is @EntityListeners.
And to this annotation I need to pass a class name which is AuditingEntityListener.class.
So this is a class present inside the spring data framework.
Now we have established all the details in order to perform the auditing by the Spring data framework.
As a last step, we need to activate this feature provided by the Spring Data Framework.
For the same, we need to go to the main class, which is
application after the spring boot application, we need to mention an annotation which is @EnableJpaAuditing
and using this EnableAuditing annotation.
We need to invoke the param which is AuditorAwareRef to this AuditorAwareRef.
We need to pass the bean name of the AuditoAwrae I am, so I need to take this post that I need to
mention.
The same here.
This way we are telling to the spring boot framework.
Please activate the JPAAuditing and please leverage the bean with the name audit aware to understand
the current auditor.
And apart from that, inside the BaseEntity we already mentioned these annotations like entity listeners
createdAt, createdBy, lastModifiedDate and lastModifiedBy.
So we are good.
As a next step, we can go to the AccountServiceImpl and delete the manual code where we are trying to
populate these createdAt and createdBy.
So this is the place
I have written two lines of code, so let me remove that.
And very similarly here also I have two lines of code.
I'm just removing them.
I'm saving the code and doing a build.
I'll go to the postman and try to test these changes.
First, I'll try to create a new record.
So let me validate my database tables now so you can see first I'm trying to run the accounts related
and as of now you can see createdBy these ACOUNTS_MS  and this is the date.
And let me check for customer as well.
The same is being updated right now.
So as a next step, we can validate whether this is happening for updated columns as well.
For the same, what we have to do is first we need to fetch the account details with the fetch operation.
So these are the account details.
So let me take this response and mention inside the RequestBody of the update account details and instead
of ready, I'll mention Mohan.
And very similarly, instead of one, two, three, I'll mention one, two, four.
Now let me click on this send button.
You can see the operation is successful.
I can go to the database now.
I'm trying to rerun this query and you can see the updatedBy and updatedAt is automatically coming.
The same will happen for accounts as well.
So this is working perfectly.
So we right now gave the responsibility of auditing to the spring data framework.
This is great and this is one of the standard that you can also follow inside your REST APIs and microservices.
I hope you are clear about what we have done inside this lecture.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.