As a next step, we need to implement one more standard inside our AccountsMicroservice, which is
documenting all our REST APIs that we have developed so far.
Here you may have a question like why should I document my own REST APIs?
I know everything about them.
I built my own REST APIs.
I don't want to again document my REST APIs.
To some extent you can live with that argument, but as soon as you start exposing your REST APIs and
microservices for external agencies or to some other team inside your organization who are supposed
to consume your microservices or REST APIs, think like there is an UI team or there is a mobile application
team.
They want to consume your backend logic with the help of your REST APIs or microservice.
These kind of scenarios, they will have lot, many questions.
The questions are like what is the request format that you are going to accept?
What is the response format that they are going to receive?
What are the validations that you have enforced inside your REST APIs?
To some extent you can answer these questions by scheduling a meeting, and inside the meeting you can
discuss everything about your REST APIs and you think you are good with that.
But in long run, think about the pain process that you have to go through.
If more and more third party applications are more and more other developers, they are trying to consume
your REST APIs and even you may receive such requests from the testing team
also. What is the request format?
What is the response format?
What is the validations that you have?
So all these questions will make your life tough and you need to repeat and share this information every
time someone asks you.
Instead, it will be a good idea to document our REST APIs by following a industry standard.
Let's try to understand how to document our REST APIs.
The standards that we need to follow here is Open API specification.
Open API is a open source community who maintain how to document our Http APIs like REST APIs that provides
a standardized means to define your API to others.
So whoever is trying to consume your REST APIs or whoever is trying to test your REST APIs, they can
quickly discover how an API works.
They can configure infrastructure, they can also generate client code, server code and create test
cases from your APIs quickly.
Whenever you document your REST APIs by using these open API specification. Here you might be under
the assumption this is a very complex task and to document my REST service it need a lot of time.
That's not correct.
It is going to be super, super easy.
With the help of the library called Spring Doc Open API.
If you go to this website which is springdoc.org, it has all the details and it has all the steps
that you need to follow to get started with documentation of our REST APIs.
oSo let's try to explore more about these springdoc-openapi.
If you can scroll down, there is a getting started page where you can simply add a maven dependency
into your spring boot web application or microservice web application.
And behind the scenes it is going to scan all your REST APIs and prepare the documentation for your
rest APIs based upon the open API specification.
And it is also going to provide you an swagger UI using which anyone can understand your REST
APIs, the details about your REST APIs and the validations that you have enforced everything.
As a next step, let's try to add this dependency into our pom.xml, let me copy this dependency and this
dependency is going to work only if you are using a spring boot version which is greater than or equal
to 3.0.
For some reason, if you are building your microservice with an older version of spring boot, then
you need to use a different version of Openapi specification, which is spring.openapi v1.7.0.
So you can see this version is going to support all the spring boot versions, which has a version of
2.x and 1.x.
Since we are using a spring boot three c.x version, we need to make sure we are using this dependency.
So let me take this and I'll go to the pom.xml inside my pom.xml just after this Lombok related dependency,
I'm going to add my new dependency related to springdoc-openapi-starter-webmvc-ui.
Please make sure you are validating this version number with the code present inside the GitHub repo.
In future,
If there is a new version released for spring doc Openapi.
I'm going to update the same inside the GitHub repo.
So once we add this dependency please load the maven changes which will download these new dependencies
that we have added.
With this we should be good,
let me save these changes and do a build.
Once the build is completed, we can try to start our application.
Since we added a new dependency, please make sure you are restarting your application.
So let me click on this debug icon that I have here.
Which will start my application at the default port
8080.
So as a developer, I have not done anything.
I simply added a springdock-openapi dependency inside our pom.xml.
So now let's try to see the magic that it is going to do behind the scenes.
I'm trying to open a path which is localhost:8080/swagger-ui/index.html.
So as soon as I tried to access this page, you can see this is a beautiful documentation about my REST
APIs that I have built inside the AccountsMicroservice, the server URL populated from the root of
our application.
So you can see inside AccountsController.
We have defined four different type of REST APIs and these are the REST API paths for all of these APIs
that we have inside controller.
This supports put operations similarly post, get and delete operation.
If you try to open these any of these operation, you will be able to see here that for the put operation
there are no parameters which is going to accept it is only going to accept a body which is a mandatory
and it is going to accept a Json type.
And this is the format that it is going to accept.
Someone has to send what is the name, what is the email, what is the mobile number, what is the account
number, account type and branch address.
By using an separate embedded object which is AccountsDto, you can also click on the schema which
will show you the input object schema.
If you recall, inside our update operation, we are using CustomerDto as an input object.
The same is getting reflected here.
Like the name is going to be mandatory and it has a min length and a max based upon our annotations
that we have defined and email is going to be mandatory for mobile number the patent is going to support
is this is a pattern and similarly it has an embedded object with the name account and it has so many
other inner fields.
So all this information is coming from our DTO object.
If you can open the any of the object like AccountsDto or CustomerDto inside these DTOs, we have
defined all these annotations using which we are trying to perform input validations.
The same information is being converted into the documentation so that anyone right now can understand
about my REST APIs so they will know which fields are mandatory, what is the format, what are the
validations that we have?
And very similarly, they will also know what is the response they can expect when these operation invocation
is successful.
Like for this update operation, we are going to return a code 200 with the description
okay.
And the ResponseBody going to have statusCode and statusMessage.
So very similarly, you can also validate post operation, which is going to accept a schema of type
CustomerDto and here also we are going to return a sample status code and status message.
Now coming to the API fetch, which is a get operation for these, we are going to accept the request
with the help of a query param which is of type mobile number and mandatory.
And you can see this is a mobile number.
And very similarly we also have the what is the response format.
Here the response format,
you can see we are going to send with the help of the schema, which is CustomerDto and the same example
structure is populated here.
Very similarly for delete
also we are going to accept a query param with the name mobile number and the response is going to be
simply status code and status message.
Towards the end you are going to see a schema section where you can see all the request and response
objects that your Rest API is going to use inside a microservice.
So here AccountsDto we know what is the structure and similarly CustomerDto we know what is the structure.
And ResponseDto
we also know what is a structure.
So based upon all these documentation, anyone can easily understand about my REST APIs, you can simply
give this URL to them.
They can analyze if needed.
They can also use this try it out option here like they can directly test by sending some mobile number
and clicking on execute.
They'll get a response saying that so-and-so is invalid because there is no customer found with a given
input mobile so they can actually test from this page itself on a high level.
You can see there are many advantages documenting your REST APIs.
So this is enough to get started with the documentation of your REST APIs and microservices.
So please, please make sure at least your documenting by simply adding this maven dependency inside
your microservices.
I see many times even senior developers, they ignore this important step and they will struggle a lot
when they deploy their microservices into production and someone is trying to consume their services.
After going through all this pain process, they will come to know about this open API specification
and swaggerui.
Then only they are going to add these dependency.
You don't have to follow that pain process.
You are my student.
You are taking this course and you have that advantage and you have all the
knowledge how to achieve this.
So this is a very quick way of getting started.
But sometimes we want to be more professional about our spring boot REST API documentation.
Like you can see a lot of information is missing.
Like we are displaying all technical information like controller name and similarly we are displaying
the CustomerDto, which is a technical name of our object and there are no example values
like we are just saying the name can be String, email can be String, AccountType can be a String branch
address can be a String.
We are not providing any example data to the clients.
When you provide the example data, it will be more clear to the developers and client applications
who are trying to consume your REST APIs.
That's why we should use few of the annotations available inside the Spring Doc Open API Library.
Using these annotations
we can try to enhance this documentation further and will make it look very professional and production
ready.
So that's a target that we have for the next lecture.
I hope you are enjoying this.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.