As of now, we completed the development of
Accounts Microservice.
And inside this Microservice we have built 4 different type of REST APIs in the same process.
We have used many annotations provided by the Spring boot framework inside this lecture.
Let me revise all those annotations very quickly so that you have these annotations at Handy.
Since I'm going to share these slides with you in a PDF format, you can always refer them whenever
you are going for an interview or whenever you are trying to build REST services with these annotations.
The very first annotation that we have used is
RestController.
Whenever we try to build REST APIs with the help of Java methods and Http annotations like
@GetMapping, @PostMapping, we need to make sure we are putting  @RestController
on top of the class.
This way we are communicating to the Spring boot framework to expose all your Java methods as a REST
APIs.
You will be seeing some people they will not use
@RestController.
Instead they will use @Controller annotation.
If you ever be in a scenario where inside your Controller you want to write both REST APIs and spring
MVC related methods, then mentioning RestController is not a good option.
Instead, you should mention @Controller annotation on top of your class and whatever Java
methods which you want to expose with the help of  REST APIs on top of them, you can mention response
body annotation.
So a combination of Controller annotation and
ResponseBody annotation will provide the same behavior
of RestController.
The next important annotation that you need to aware is @ResponseBody.
Like we discussed,
whenever you are into a scenario where you are using the @Controller annotation on top of your
Java class, you need to mention these  @ResponseBody annotation to tell to the spring boot
framework that you are expecting the response to be in a Json format but not in the spring MVC style
like HTML format or any other UI format.
Since we don't have any Java methods which we are trying to expose with the help of Spring MVC pattern,
we didn't use this ResponseBody annotation and   @Controller annotation instead we used
@RestController annotation.
Moving on to the next important component whenever you are trying to build REST services is
ResponseEntity.
This is not a annotation, this is a class available inside the spring framework.
Whenever you are trying to send all kind of information like headers, status and body inside the response
to your clients, then it is a good idea to use this ResponseEntity and this class will have these
generics with the help of these generics.
We need to tell what type of object that I'm going to send inside my ResponseBody.
If you are sending customer information, we need to mention the customer DTO and similarly you can
mention any type of object whenever you are trying to mention this ResponseEntity in the return type
of your Java method, The next important component that you need to aware is @ControllerAdvice
annotation using this annotation along with the ExceptionHandler annotation, we can write global
exception logic.
Whatever logic you have written inside a Java method that is annotated with @ExceptionHandler
and tag that too against a exception type.
Then, whenever that exception occurs inside your controller layer, the logic that you have written
inside this ExceptionHandler methods will get executed.
So to activate that behavior, we need to make sure we are using @ControllerAdvice annotation.
We have another similar annotation also with the name
@RestControllerAdvice.
You can use this as well.
This RestControllerAdvice annotation is a combination of
@ControllerAdvice
and @ResponseBody.
Just like how we have the relationship between
RestController and Controller.
The same relationship works here between the
ControllerAdvice and the RestControllerAdvice annotations.
In our scenario, I have used @ControllerAdvice and it worked perfectly.
But if you ever into a scenario where you want strictly your exception methods return the Json as an
output, then please feel free to use
@RestControllerAdvice,
as of now, for me it worked perfectly inside our
AccountsMicroservice
With the help of ControllerAdvice, I'm able to achieve my functionality perfectly.
That's why I have not used this @RestControllerAdvice.
Even if you use this, you will get the same behavior.
The next important class that we have here is
RequestEntity, just like how we have ResponseEntity.
Very similarly, we can also use this RequestEntity.
Whenever you have a scenario where you want to receive both requestBody and requestHeader as a
method parameter inside your REST APIs.
We have not used this inside our Microservice because we don't have a scenario where we want the
requestHeader and requestBody.
We always had a scenario where we want only
requestBody but not the requestHeaders.
That's why I have not used this.
But if you ever have such scenarios, feel free to use the RequestEntity.
Once you receive this RequestEntity object, you as a developer can extract all the requestHeaders
and the requestBody post that you can execute your business logic.
The next set of annotations that we have here is @RequestHeader and
@RequestBody.
Using these individual annotations, you can receive a header inside the request as a method parameter,
or you can also receive the entire request body as a method parameter.
I hope this is clear.
Please make a note of all these important annotations and classes that supports building REST services.
So these are very, very important.
If you go to any interview, they can simply ask you a question like how you are going to build REST
APIs with the help of Springboot.
In such scenarios, you can take these annotations and important classes and try to explain them as
a sequence.
First, I will create a class.
On top of that, I'll mention other RestController class post that I'll create Java methods.
On top of them, I'll keep the annotations like GetMapping, PostMapping followed by We'll use this
RequestEntity, RequestHeader, RequestBody,
ResponseEntity.
And once I have written all the business logic, I can also define the global exception logic.
With the help of this ControllerAdvisor, annotation and ExceptionHandler annotation.
So if you try to explain this as a flow and as a story, definitely your answer will impress the interviewer.
That's why always have these annotations and classes handy.
They'll also help you whenever you are trying to develop Microservices or REST services.
I hope this is clear.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.