In this lecture,
let's try to explore further about the retry pattern.
As of now, you can see we are trying to attempt the retry operation whenever there is an issue inside
our getBuildInfo() method.
So regardless of what type of exception happening inside your method, in all such scenarios, the retry
attempt will happen.
What if there is a business requirement saying that please don't retry whenever there is a NullPointerException
because if there is a NullPointerException with a given input data, regardless of how many
times you retry, you will always get a NullPointerException. In such scenarios
we don't want our retry to happen.
So how to achieve this?
For the same, we need to go to the application.yml of accounts microservice because we have implemented
these retry inside the accounts microservice. So here under the retry configurations I need to define
a new property.
The property is ignoreExceptions and these ignoreExceptions
we can define any number of exceptions with the help of this hyphen inside Yaml
whenever we use this hyphen or dash symbol that indicates it is one of the element inside the list.
Suppose if you want to define one more exception, you can try to copy the same code under the same
location.
And in the second element you can try to mention your second exception.
But here I'm fine with the one exception which is of type NullPointerException.
You need to mention the complete name, including the package name.
So with this I have configured saying that please ignore exception of type NullPointerException in
such scenarios,
please do not retry the request, so let me save this changes.
Do a build.
Once the build is completed, I will stop my AccountsApplication and gateway server application post
that I'm going to start my AccountsApplication.
Once the AccountsApplication is started, I'm going to start my Gateway server application.
Now we can go to the postman and try to invoke the request this time they should not be any retry attempt
happening.
So let me go to the AccountsApplication and clean the console here.
Here inside the postman
I'm trying to invoke this API.
You can see we are getting the fallback response from the retry pattern.
The retry pattern is activated, but behind the scenes it is not going to make the multiple retry attempts.
We can confirm the same inside the console of the AccountsApplication.
Here you can see there are two statements.
The very first one is from the get build info and the second one is from the get build info fallback,
which means with a single execution, the fallback mechanism came into picture and this is what printed
on the console.
So the retry is not happening whenever there is a NullPointerException.
So this is one type of requirement
you may have.
The other kind of requirement that you may have is to retry only for a set of specific exceptions.
So let's try to see how to define that.
Just like how we have ignore exceptions, we can also define one more property, which is retry exceptions.
And these retry exceptions we can define any number of exceptions.
So as of now, I have mentioned please retry the request only in the scenario of timeout exception.
I also want to highlight you that whenever we are defining these retry exceptions, then we don't have
to define these ignore exceptions because when are we define an exception
under these retry exceptions, the retry will happen only for these kind of exceptions, which is like
timeout exception and all the remaining exceptions automatically will be ignored by the resiliency4j.
So that's why please note that whenever you are defining retry exceptions, you don't have to mention
the ignore exceptions.
Now, after making these changes, let me go to the AccountsController.
Inside the AccountsController
as of now we are throwing NullPointerException.
So here I will change this to timeout exception and since the timeout exception is a checked exception,
we need to make sure we are adding the throw statement to the method signature.
So let me try to add the throw statement to the method signature.
So now we should be good.
Let me save these changes.
Do a build.
Once the build is completed, I can go to the postman inside my postman.
I'm going to invoke this build-info API one more time and this time since we are throwing TimeoutException
behind the scenes, my resiliency4j framework might have retried multiple times based upon our
configurations.
So let me confirm the same by going into the accounts microservice console.
So here inside the AccountsApplication console, you will be able to see three log statements with
a output saying that getBuildInfo() method invoked even after three attempts.
Since we are not sending a successful response at last the fallback
method will be invoked.
I hope now you are clear how to configure, ignore exceptions and retry exceptions whenever you are
trying to configure retry pattern inside your microservices.
You may have a question here how to achieve the same
whenever we are trying to implement retry pattern with the help of Gateway server, we can also achieve
the same inside Gateway server. For the same,
if you go to the retry configurations here and try to invoke some methods with the prefix set, you
should be able to see some methods with the name like set exceptions where you can try to mention the
list of exceptions.
The retry attempt will happen, so there is no option of ignore exception here.
And very similarly, you can also mention Http status based upon some Http status code you can retry,
otherwise you can simply ignore the retry attempt.
I hope you are clear with this. As a next step
I want to fix a small bug that we have inside our GatewayServer application to explain you about this
defect.
Let me go to the postman.
Previously when you are trying to test the retry related changes inside the Gateway server, we invoke
these loans
contact-info.
Here if you see inside the header, we have easy correlation ID multiple times populated with the same value.
So why this is happening?
This is because whenever there is a retry attempt is happening on the Gateway server, the response
filter that we have written to populate these easy correlation ID is going to be executed.
So let me open the ResponseFilter inside the GatewayServer application.
Under these filters there is a filter with the name TesponseTraceFilter.
Whenever a response comes, regardless of an exception, response or a retry response, we are always
simply trying to add the header with the name present inside this constant along with the correlation
ID value.
Due to that, the header is getting populated multiple times inside the response.
So this is not correct.
We can try to add some if statement here. Inside the if statement
we can mention this logic.
We can add some conditions to this if
block. But before that, let me copy these two statements into the
if block. Now, I'm going to add a condition inside the if
Block. You can see here with this check
first, I'm trying to check if there is any header inside the response with the same name.
If it is there, then this value is going to be true.
The not condition of true will be false.
In such scenarios, my if block is not going to be executed, whereas if there is no header inside the
response, this will be false and not a false will be true.
And in such scenarios the if block will be executed.
So this is the small fix that I want to provide to handle the defect that we saw previously.
With this, we have completed all the discussion around the retry pattern.
I can go to the AccountsController and try to revert this code which is related to throwing RuntimeException
and post that I'm going to uncomment this code.
So now we should be good as a last step, let me show you the slides.
Here you can see I have mentioned the list of steps that we have followed to configure the retry pattern
inside the normal microservices like accounts
microservice.
First with the help of retry annotation, we need to mention what is the name of the retry pattern and what
is the fallback method and post that we need to create the fallback method by following the rules that
we have discussed.
And after making these changes, we need to mention the list of properties inside the application.yml
file like you can see on the screen.
So I'm just trying to mention all these steps inside the slide so that you can use them as a reference
in future
whenever you want to quickly refresh all the topics that we have discussed inside this course, I hope
you are super, super clear about the retry pattern.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.