Now is the time to implement the RateLimiter pattern inside the gateway server. For the same
first we need to add the dependency related to Redis.
So here I'm trying to add a dependency.
The artifactId of this dependency is spring boot starter data redis reactive.
So let me save this and do a maven load.
After this we can go to the GatewayserverApplication.
And here first I'm going to create two beans.
So let me paste few lines of code here.
Like you can see, I have created two beans.
The very first one is of type KeyResolver. Inside this method, which is userKeyResolver.
I'm trying to provide a key based upon which my RateLimiter pattern has to work.
So I just copied this complete code from the official documentation.
If you try to understand the logic present inside this method first, I'm trying to get the header inside
the request with the name user.
So based upon that header value, I'm going to create a KeyResolver.
If someone is not sending any header inside the request with the name user, then I'm going to assign
a default value which is anonymous.
So this is the logic that I have written.
But in real projects you can change this logic based upon your requirements.
And the second bean that I'm trying to create is of type RedisRateLimiter. Inside this method, I'm
trying to create a new object of RedisRateLimiter and I'm trying to pass three different values like
replenishRate, burst capacity and default requester tokens.
With these configurations, we are going to add one token in each second and burst capacity also going
to be one.
And the cost of each request is also going to be one.
With this, it is pretty clear for each second my end user can only make one request.
After defining these two beans, we can go to the routing configurations that we have defined here.
As of now we have implemented  circuit breaker for accounts, retry for loans, maybe for cards
we can try to implement the RateLimiter pattern.
So here, just after the Add response header, I'm going to invoke a new filter with the name
RequestRateLimiter.
And there are two types of filters.
I'm trying to invoke the filter which is accepting some configurations.
So let me invoke the same.
And here using the lambda expression, I'm going to invoke setRateLimiter() method to this setRateLimiter().
.
I'm going to pass RedisRateLimiter method.
That means this RedisRateLimiter method is going to return a bean of RedisRateLimiter.
So the same I'm going to set with the help of this setRateLimiter.
After this, I'm going to invoke one more method which is setKeyResolver() to this setKeyResolver().
I'm going to pass what is a bean of KeyResolver.
So where we have defined the KeyResolver bean inside the method userKeyResolver.
So let me invoke the same here. With this
we have added the RequestRateLimiter pattern for all the APIs inside the cards
microservice.
As a next step, we need to start the Redis database or Redis container so that it can maintain creating
the buckets with the usernames and maintaining all these configurations. For the same,
we need to start the Redis container with the help of Docker.
Please make sure your Docker server is running and post that you can try to open the terminal.
I open my terminal and here I'm going to run a Docker command, which is docker run -p 6379.
This is the default port of Redis, so I'm trying to mention the same and I'm trying to give a name
to the container with the name eazyredis.
And since I'm trying to start in detached mode, I have given this flag -d and at last, what
is the image name of Redis?
The image name of Redis is Redis itself.
So let me execute this command.
This will start Redis container behind the scenes.
Now as a next step, we need to provide the connection details of this redis container inside the application.yml
gateway server.
Here I'm going to open the application.yml which is present under the resources folder and the properties
that we need to add will have a parent key which is spring.
After spring it is going to have data.
So what I can do is just under this spring inside the same location where we have application config
and cloud, I'm going to add few new properties.
So you can see the property name is going to be sprin.data.redis.
what is the connection timeout?
What is the host?
What is the port number?
What is the timeout?
So these are the Redis related configurations.
So let me make sure that these data element is present as a child under the spring.
So this looks good.
Let me save this changes do a build.
Once the build is completed, I'm going to start my
our application.
Before that you can see I have my config server Eureka Server and CardsApplication running behind the
scenes.
We don't need accounts and loans microservice for this demo because we have implemented RateLimiter
only for cards
microservice.
So let me start my GatewayserverApplication.
Now
my Gatewayserver is started successfully in order to test my RateLimiter pattern.
I want to send a lot many requests within a single second so that I can see what is happening behind
the scenes.
To perform some load testing, we can use Apache Benchmark server.
So this is the official website of Apache Benchmark project.
So if you can click on this download, there are some options on how we can download and set up this
server.
Since I'm using Mac, for me it is going to be super, super easy.
But if you are using Windows laptop, you need to click on this link where they have highlighted from
number of third party vendors.
So if I click on this, you can download this project and set up this.
So here I'm not going in detail about how to set up this server inside Windows or inside any other operating
system.
You can go to the YouTube and try to look for the videos related to Apache Benchmark and there are good
amount of YouTube videos explaining about this since we are going to use this only for this video.
I'm not talking about this in detail.
You can also Google on how to set up Apache benchmark and you will have good amount of blocks explaining
this.
So if you see here, here there is a blog explaining the same how to perform load testing with the help
of Apache bench.
So these are the instructions if you are using Unix based or Mac based operating system, the installation
is going to be easy for them.
But for Windows you need to follow a lengthy process like where you need to download these from the
given links and post that you need to set up the server.
But don't worry, since you are already seeing the demo with me, I'm assuming you're fine with that.
So let me go to the terminal and run a command related to the Apache benchmark.
Here I'm going to run a command which is AB, AB indicates Apache benchmark -n ten.
So I'm trying to send ten requests.
That's why I'm trying to go -n 10 and -c 2 means I want to maintain concurrency as two.
That means I want to send two concurrent requests every time.
Whenever my Apache benchmark is trying to send these ten requests, that means instead of sending these
ten requests one by one, I want my benchmark concurrently by taking two requests at a time and post
that -v indicates verbose when I give three value for these verbose flag that indicates to this
Apache benchmark server that I want to see the detailed report in the output. After this verbose related
flag configurations we need to mention what is the endpoint URL that we are trying to invoke.
You can see here, I'm trying to invoke one of the cards microservice API, which is contact-info
but I'm not trying to invoke directly, I'm trying to invoke with the help of Gateway URL.
So now I'm going to execute this command.
Are you ready to see the magic?
So let's see the magic so you can see I got a report and inside this report there is a detailed explanation
what is happened for each second.
First, let's try to read the summary.
If you read the summary, all the requests are processed within 0.5 seconds, which means in a half
second, my benchmark sent all the ten requests to the backend server with the concurrency level as
two out of these ten requests, nine of them are failed.
Only one is processed because based upon our RateLimiter configuration for a user, we have assigned
only one token for each request.
So let's see what happened to the remaining nine requests.
What is the error that is coming on this console?
So first let me go to the very first request.
Very first request
you can see we received the 200 and post that we started receiving 429, which is too many requests.
So for all the remaining requests we receive the 429. This means the RateLimiter pattern that we have
implemented is working perfectly.
We have configured this logic for the KeyResolver.
Since we are not sending any header inside the request with the name user, it is going to consider
the KeyResolver value as anonymous.
If you want, you can try to test by sending the header inside the request, but that is not going to
make any difference in the demo because inside the local system there will be always a single user.
I hope you are clear with the RateLimiter pattern that we have implemented with the help of Gatewayserver
.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.