Inside this lecture, let's try to discuss on how to implement RateLimiter pattern inside normal spring
boot microservices.
Previously, we explored how to implement RateLimiter pattern inside a gateway server.
Now we can try to implement the same inside accounts microservice. For the same,
I selected these method which is getJavaVersion().
I want this method to be invoked based upon the rate limitations that I have defined.
For the same, we need to mention an annotation which is @RateLimiter pattern.
And to this annotation I want to pass what is the name of this configuration?
So the name I want to give as the same as method name, which is getJavaVersion().
For now, I will not give any fallback.
We can see how the behavior is going to be without fallback and with fallback.
After mentioning these RateLimiter annotation, we need to mention RateLimiter properties inside the
application.yml.
As of now we have circuit breaker retry related configurations.
So very similarly, I'm going to mention RateLimiter related properties.
Here I'm going to paste few properties like you can see resilience4j.ratelimiter and I'm trying to provide
these properties for all RateLimiter configurations inside my microservice.
That's why I have mentioned these default.
Now here we have mentioned three important properties.
First, let's try to understand what is this limit refresh period. For this property
I have mentioned 5000 milliseconds.
That means for every five seconds I want to renew the quota.
So what is our quota that I have set for each refresh period?
You can identify the same with the help of limit for period, which means for every five seconds I have
configured, only one request is allowed.
But in real production applications the number will be in thousands.
And the next property that we have here is timeout duration.
Think like one of the thread came and it is trying to invoke this specific API, but the RateLimited
did not allow it because the number of requests allowed during a particular period is exhausted.
So in such scenarios, with the help of this timeout duration, we are telling what is the maximum time
that my particular thread can wait for the new refresh period to arrive with the new quota.
So with this configuration my thread is going to wait for a maximum of one second. Within one second
if my RateLimiter is not allowing the request, then simply it is not going to wait further and return
back with the error.
You might have observed this, that this is something different from what we have discussed in the GatewayServer
.
I agree with you both has different approaches with a gateway server and Redis limiter and the KeyResolver,
we can enforce the quota limitations based upon our criteria like user or IP address or server.
But here, whenever we are trying to implement RateLimiter pattern without spring cloud gateway server,
then this is going to be a different approach.
Whatever configurations that you are going to provide here, this is going to apply for all type of
requests coming towards your API.
This we can use in a scenarios where you might have a infrastructure that can only handle 10,000 requests
for each second.
So beyond 10,000 requests you don't want to accept, then in such scenarios, this approach is going
to be super helpful
or you may also have different requirement where you want a particular low priority API to process less
number of requests so that other high priority APIs they can process without any issues.
All such kind of custom requirements you can achieve with this pattern.
So after making these changes, we can save these and do a build.
Once a build is completed, we can go ahead and start the accounts
microservice. Let me start the AccountsApplication and with this approach we don't need any reddish
container.
Once the AccountsApplication is started, I will restart my GatewayserverApplication because my
AccountsApplication is registered with the Eureka server
the same details I want my gateway server to fetch during the startup.
Now I'm going to start my GatewayserverApplication again. To demo these changes to you
I will go to the postman.
Inside the Postman there is a new request that is going to invoke the Java version API.
So let me first try to invoke this with the help of the send button so everything is happy we are getting
an output.
Now I will try to click on this send button multiple times so that I'm trying to send a lot of requests
to these API.
So let me click on the send button.
So at some point of time you should be seeing the error saying that internal server error and the error
message is RateLimiter does not permit further details.
Since inside the accounts
microservice we have a GlobalExceptionHandler.
It is throwing these internal server error 500.
But behind the scenes, the reason why we are getting is due to this RateLimiter. In the browser
also we can validate this.
So first I'm trying to invoke this.
You can see I'm getting the message.
So this is the output.
Please ignore this error.
If I try to refresh my browser multiple times at some point of time we will get an same error here.
As a next step, we can try to define the fallback mechanism for this RateLimiter pattern. For the same
inside the AccountsController.
I'm going to mention the parameter fallback method.
And to this I'm going to give the name as getJavaVersion() fall back.
So let me create the same kind of method as a fallback method, because whenever we are trying to create
the fallback method, we need to make sure the method signature is same as the original method.
So let me replace the method name post that we need to make sure we are passing one more method parameter
which is Throwable.
Once I have mentioned this parameter as a next step, I'm going to write the fallback logic.
So here the fallback logic that I want to write is I'm going to simply return the output, which is
Java 17.
So in the cases where my original method is not able to process the business logic, I have written
a fallback mechanism which is going to return the Java 17.
Think like in the real projects you have an original method which is going to do a lot of heavy operation
and this method supports a low priority API. Based upon your configurations
if you are not allowing any further requests to this method within a time frame, then you can simply
write a simple logic inside your fallback saying that please try again after some time or you can send
some information from the cache.
So it's up to you what kind of business logic that you want to write here.
So let me save this changes.
Do a build.
Once the build is completed,
as usual, we need to stop the AccountsApplication post that I'm going to stop GatewayserverApplication
as a next step, I will first start my AccountsApplication.
Once my AccountsApplication is started, I'm going to start my GatewayserverApplication.
So this will start my GatewayserverApplication in few seconds.
Like you can see now, it is started successfully.
I'll go to the browser, I will try to invoke the same API.
You can see we are getting the output from the original method.
If I try to refresh this multiple times at some point of time you will get the fallback method output
which is Java 17.
With this, I'm assuming you are super, super clear on how to implement RateLimiter pattern inside your
normal microservices.
So every pattern I'm trying to show you two different approaches.
One is with the help of Gateway pattern and the other one with the help of resiliency4j library
and the annotations provided by the same.
Using these two approaches.
Now you have flexibility to implement these patterns either in the Gatewayserver or inside your microservices
based upon your business requirements.
I hope this is clear.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.