As of now, we are trying to interact with our Kubernetes cluster only with the help of kubectl commands
from our local terminal.
But like I said before, we also have other approach, which is with the help of admin UI, we can also
interact with the Kubernetes cluster.
We can see the overall status of the Kubernetes cluster.
So having an access to the UI for your Kubernetes cluster is going to make your life super, super easy.
That's why inside this lecture I'm going to show you how to set up Kubernetes Dashboard, our Kubernetes
admin UI. For the same,
I came to this official website which will guide us on how to set up a Kubernetes dashboard inside a
Kubernetes cluster.
So this is the URL, the same URL I'm going to mention inside the GitHub repo as well for your reference.
Now let's try to explore this page and try to understand how to set up these Kubernetes dashboard.
So if you can scroll down, this is how the Kubernetes dashboard is going to look like in very few minutes
we're going to set up this kind of Kubernetes dashboard inside our local Kubernetes cluster as well.
So let me scroll down on this page so you can see there is a note here saying that that dashboard UI
is not deployed by default inside any Kubernetes cluster.
So we need to follow certain steps to install these Kubernetes dashboard inside our local Kubernetes
cluster.
Based upon the instructions
here you can see we can install the Kubernetes dashboard only with the help of helm.
So what is a helm?
Helm is a package manager for Kubernetes.
So just like how we have node for JavaScript world.
Very similarly for Kubernetes related installations, helm is a package manager using which we can install
any kind of components inside a Kubernetes cluster.
So there is a dedicated section regarding helm is available
inside this course we are going to discuss in detail about helm in the next section.
For now, let's not worry much about helm.
Let's try to set up the Kubernetes dashboard with the help of this helm.
So you can see here we have certain commands that we need to execute in order to set up the Kubernetes
dashboard.
But in order to execute these commands first we need to make sure we are installing the helm inside
our local system.
So to install the helm, we need to go to a website which is helm.sh.
Inside this website we can click on this get started and post that
on the left hand side there is an option which is installing helm.
If you can click on this
here we have details on how to install helm in various operating system.
And there are multiple approaches that they have provided the most easiest way
and the recommended approach from my side is, with the help of package managers.
So helm is a package manager, which we can install with the help of other package managers.
So for Mac OS, you should already have home brew, which is a package manager.
Using home brew you can install this command which is brew install helm and this is going to install
helm inside your local system.
Coming to the windows operating system users, first you need to install Chocolaty Package Manager.
If you can click on this chocolaty link, it will take you to this website.
So here there is an option of install.
So please try to follow the instructions present inside this page
to install chocolaty inside your system you need to select these individual option.
If you are looking for a detailed lecture on how to install helm, there is a lecture in the next section
on how to install helm in the local system.
You can look into that lecture as well, but I think this should be very easy.
So once you install this chocolaty inside your windows operating system you need to install these Chaco
install Kubernetes hyphen helm command.
So it's pretty easy to install helm Mac OS users
you can use this command which is brew install helm, whereas windows users
I would recommend you following installing helm with the help of chocolaty.
Once you install helm, you need to verify whether the installation is successful or not.
So how to verify it?
It's very simple.
We just need to execute a command which is helm space version.
As soon as you press enter, you should get a proper output which is going to convey what is the current
version of helm installed inside your system.
If you are able to see this kind of output inside your system, then it conveys that the helm installation
is successful.
As a next step, we need to take these very first command.
For now don't worry about what are these commands we are going to discuss in detail about helm in the
next section.
So I'm just trying to paste this command and execute inside my system.
Since I already executed this command previously.
I'm getting this output.
But for you, since you're going to execute this command very first time, you should get some other
output which conveys that adding a helm repo inside your system is is successful.
Now let me take the second command, the same command I'm going to paste inside my terminal and execute
this command.
So this is going to install Kubernetes dashboard inside my local Kubernetes cluster.
Once the installation is successful, you're going to get this kind of output saying that congratulations
you have just installed Kubernetes dashboard inside your cluster.
If you are getting any warnings or errors, please make sure you're having latest Docker Desktop.
On top of that, you should have a local Kubernetes cluster running inside your system.
And that is what we set up in the previous lecture.
So the installation of Kubernetes dashboard is going to take 2 to 3 minutes time.
So please wait for a couple of minutes.
Post that
in order to access that dashboard you need to run this command.
So we need to copy this entire command and run it here in the same terminal.
So as soon as I execute this command you will be able to see right now my Kubernetes cluster
it exposes that dashboard to the outside world at the port 8443.
So once you execute this command, don't try to disturb this terminal.
Because if you try to close this terminal or if you try to execute some other command, then this exposing
of the traffic is going to be stopped
and with that, you will not be able to access Kubernetes dashboard inside your system.
So once this command is executed, you can see this is the URL that you can use to access the Kubernetes
dashboard inside your system.
So let me copy this and paste it inside my browser.
So as soon as I press enter, since my connection is Https with a certificate which is generated by
my Kubernetes cluster, my browser is not considering that as a valid certificate, but for our local
testing this should be fine.
We can click on this show details and I can click on this link which is visit this website.
And with that I'll be able to see the login page for my Kubernetes dashboard.
So here it is expecting a token as an input.
So once we enter that token inside this page we'll be able to see that dashboard UI.
I'm going to show you how to get this token in few minutes.
But before that I just wanted to highlight one important note.
As of now, you can see I'm able to access the dashboard with 8443.
But in the videos that you're going to see in future, inside this course, you'll be able to see a
different port which is 8001.
So don't worry about the port number.
When I created this course very first time to set up the Kubernetes dashboard, we used to have a different
lengthy approach.
And in that legacy, our deprecated approach, the dashboard used to be deployed at 8001.
But with this latest approach or with the helm approach that we discussed so far, the Kubernetes dashboard
is going to be available at the port 8443.
So that's why my humble request is don't worry about the port number.
Whenever you are seeing the Kubernetes dashboard in the coming lectures.
I hope you're clear.
Now let me go to this official website.
Here we have a hyperlink which is going to help us on how to create a sample user.
So let me click on the same.
And this will take me to a GitHub page.
And here we have clear instructions on how to create a sample user.
So let's try to understand what are these instructions and follow the same inside our local system as
well.
So here first you can see we need to create a service account inside Kubernetes
we have a concept like service account.
So service account is nothing but is a credential that you are trying to create for a particular user.
So how to create this service account.
You need to write these Yaml configurations in one of the file.
And the same you need to provide to the Kubernetes cluster with the help of kubectl apply - f.
And what is a file name?
Here you can see the instructions are pretty clear.
First we need to mention what is the API version, which is v1.
So using this API version, we are telling to the Kubernetes cluster that we are trying to use the version
one of API to create an service account.
So under the kind I have mentioned, the service account service account is a predefined object inside
the Kubernetes.
So whenever my Kubernetes cluster see the value service account after the kind, it is going to create
a service account for me and the metadata we need to provide.
What is the name of the service account.
So the name of the service account that I want to create is admin hyphen user.
This is very similar to your username.
And by default if I don't mention the namespace where the service account has to be created, my Kubernetes
cluster is going to create it inside that default namespace.
But since we don't want the service account to be created inside a default namespace, we
need to provide what is the namespace and the namespace that we are trying to give here is Kubernetes
hyphen dashboard.
So what is the namespace inside Kubernetes cluster?
It is a kind of boundary or an isolated area inside your cluster.
So just like how we have dev environment QA environment or production environment, very similarly inside
the Kubernetes, also with the help of namespaces, we can create separate, separate isolated areas
under which we can try to create various objects like service account.
As a next step we need to copy these instructions.
And let's try to create a Yaml file with the name dashboard-adminuser.yaml. For the same,
inside my terminal, I'm going to open a new tab.
I'm not going to disturb this existing terminal because it is right now opened a proxy port using which
I can try to access my dashboard of Kubernetes.
So let me create a new terminal here inside my terminal
first I'll navigate to a folder inside my desktop.
So for the same I'm going to give a command which is cd /Users/eazybytes/desktop.
And inside my desktop I have created a folder with the name K8S which means Kubernetes.
Inside this I'm going to create a file with the name dashboard-adminuser.yaml.
So let me copy this value and mention the same here and post that I'm trying to execute this command.
Inside Mac,
whenever I try to issue this touch command, it is going to create a new file based upon the name that
I have given.
You can see here a new Yaml file is created.
Let me try to open this in text editor.
As of now it is empty
let me try to copy all the configurations from the GitHub repo.
So this is the Yaml configurations that will help us to create a service account with the name
admin-user.
Now as a next step, I need to provide these configurations to the Kubernetes cluster.
For the same,
we need to run the command which is kubectl
apply - f, f indicates what is the file name, and the file name is dashboard-adminuser.yml.
.
So let me try to execute this command.
You can see behind the scenes a service account with the name admin user created.
You can see here
for me it gives an output saying that unchanged that means nothing new happened.
This is because I already executed this command behind the scenes before recording this lecture.
But if you are trying to run this command very first time, you should get an output saying that so-and-so
admin user is created.
Now as a next step, we need to create a cluster role binding.
So as of now we have a service account.
But we need to provide privileges to this account with the help of this cluster role binding. For the
same,
first we need to create a new file.
So let me try to run the command which is touch dashboard-rolebinding.yaml.
The file name can be anything.
I'm just trying to give some dashboard-rolebinding.yaml.
As of now this file is empty.
Let me try to copy the content from the GitHub repo.
So here I'm trying to copy this content and paste the same here.
And this time you can see the kind is going to be cluster role binding.
Because we are trying to bind the cluster role to the service account that we have created previously.
Under the API version,
for this kind of cluster role binding, we have to mention this value.
Whereas for the service account it is going to be simply v1.
So all these values are going to be available inside the official Kubernetes documentation.
Please refer to the same if you have any questions after the kind
under the metadata we need to mention what is the name of this cluster role binding.
So the name I want to give here is, admin - user, just like how we have given for the service account.
So once we have defined this admin-user your cluster role binding will expect two information.
What is a cluster role that you want to bind and to which user or to which service account you want
to bind.
So that's why under this role ref we need to give this API group.
This is going to be always constant value.
You can see this is same as like what we have given under the API version.
The kind has to be cluster role because we are trying to bind a cluster role inside the Kubernetes cluster
all roles we should call it as cluster role and the name of the cluster is cluster-admin.
That means we're trying to assign a role cluster-admin.
So this is a predefined role inside the Kubernetes cluster.
So whoever has this role they will become an admin of the Kubernetes cluster.
So now I have mentioned which role I want to bind.
As a next step we need to tell to whom we want to assign this role.
That's why under the subjects we need to start a new array element inside Yaml
whenever we want to start an array element, our list element, we need to mention this hyphen.
So under subjects we can define any number of service accounts
or we can define any number of user
details.
But in our scenario, since we only have one account, we are mentioning only a single element under
the subjects.
So under each element of the subjects, we need to mention what is a kind, what is a name,
what is a namespace?
So the kind of user that we want to assign this role is service account.
That's why we need to mention the same.
And what is the service account name.
The service account name that we have given here is, admin-user.
The same we have to mention there.
And apart from that we should also mention the same namespace which is Kubernetes-dashboard.
So the same I'm trying to mention here.
So now our file is ready.
Let's try to apply this file also so that the role of cluster-admin will be binded to the user-admin
-user.
So here I'll try to run the same command which is kubectl apply - f.
And what is the file name.
The file name is going to be dashboard-rolebinding.yaml.
You can see here,
for me I got output as unchanged because I already executed these configurations for you
you should get an output saying that so and so role binding is created. As a next step,
we need to run this command to get a token for the admin user.
So let me try to run this command.
So kubectl - n, -n indicates what is the namespace.
The namespace where we have a service account is kubernetes-dashboard and create token.
And what is the service account name.
So this will create a token for my admin user.
So let me copy this value and mention the same inside my dashboard by selecting this option which is
token.
Once I pasted this token, I'm going to click on this sign in button.
So you can see
now I'm able to access my Kubernetes dashboard.
By default the namespace selected is going to be default.
If you go to the other namespace like Kubernetes dashboard.
As of now, you can see under the Kubernetes dashboard there are two deployments running with the two
different parts and two different replica sets.
Because even to see this dashboard behind the scenes, some code has to be deployed.
That's why we're able to see these deployments
pods and replica set.
Using this dashboard, we can explore a lot of information.
We're going to explore the same in the coming lectures.
Whenever we are trying to discuss about a particular topic.
As of now, we created a service account and a cluster role binding under the namespace Kubernetes dashboard.
So that's why I have selected the same namespace inside the same namespace
only the deployments related to this UI is created.
So that's why you are able to see these deployments, parts and replica set here on this page
if I can scroll down, there is an information which is related to the service account.
So let me try to click on the service accounts.
So like you can see here, there is a service account that we have created with the name admin - user
.
So to understand what role we have binded for this admin-user you can go to the cluster role bindings.
So here also we have given the same name which is admin-user.
If you try to open that here it is clearly highlighted for so-and-so subject which is admin-user
and the namespace which is of kind service account.
We have assigned a role with the name cluster-admin.
So if you try to click on this, you will go to the page related to cluster roles.
So whoever has this role assigned which is cluster-admin they will have these rules applicable.
So here under the rules you can see they can invoke all kind of resources with all kind of verbs and
API groups.
Very similarly under non resource URL
also there are asterisk marks mentioned.
This user is a super user.
He can perform any kind of operation inside Kubernetes cluster.
I hope you are clear here
you can see with this approach whenever you want to get a bearer token you need to run this command
and this token is going to be short lived.
That means if you don't use your dashboard, it is going to expire.
And every time you want to have an access token, you need to run this command.
Otherwise, if you are looking for a long lived bearer token, then you need to create a secret by using
these configurations.
So you can see the kind is mentioned as secret here.
So secret is a concept inside Kubernetes using which we can store our sensitive information like passwords.
So let's try to explore on how to create these long lived bearer token so that it will make our life
easy. For the same,
I'm going to copy this content, and here I'm going to create a new file by executing the command which
is touch secret.yaml.
So now I'll open my secret.yaml file.
And I'm going to paste the content that I have copied from the website.
So here you can see we are trying to create a secret with the name admin user and the namespace Kubernetes
- dashboard and whatever secret that we are using, we assigned to the service account with the
name admin-user.
That means we are creating a secret for the admin user that we have created previously.
Under
the type, you just need to mention these constant value which is kubernetes.io/service-account-token
.
Because what we're trying to create with the help of the secret, we're trying to create a token for
the service account.
That's why we need to mention this type value.
So let me save this file.
And I'm going to execute the command which is kubectl
apply - f and the file name is going to be secret.yaml.
Now you can see the secret is created successfully.
As a next step I can try to run this command.
And this is going to give me what is the token that it is generated behind the scenes.
So let me try to run this command and it will give me a token value.
And this token, whatever I received it is going to be the constant token all the time.
And with this approach, I don't have to get a new token every time with the help of this command,
which is create token for the admin user.
Since this is going to be super convenient, I'm going to use this token and use the same inside the
dashboard. For the same,
first, let me log out here and post that
I'm going to select the token and mention the same token value and click Sign in.
But here I'm getting an unauthorized error.
Let me see why I'm getting this error.
So inside the terminal whenever we try to run this command which is kubectl get secret in the output,
we are getting an percentage towards the end for some reason.
So whenever you try to copy this token, don't copy the last character which is percentage.
So without percentage please copy this value and mention the same
and with that we should be able to sign in.
So please make a note of your token in some place like you can see I'm trying to paste my token here.
So whenever my dashboard is going to ask me the token value, I'm going to give this
always.
If you don't follow this approach, you should always execute this command, which is create token command.
And it is going to give you different, different token at different, different times.
With this, I'm assuming your super, super clear on how to set up the Kubernetes dashboard.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture, bye.