Now, inside this lecture, let's try to deploy all the remaining microservices into the Kubernetes
cluster. For the same,
first, we need to prepare the Kubernetes manifest files for the remaining microservices.
Since we are already familiar with this process.
Behind the scenes, I have created all the required Kubernetes manifest files. The same
you can identify them under the Section 15 folder and post that
you can go to Kubernetes.
And here I have mentioned all the manifest files required.
Previously we used to have config maps and config server only.
I have renamed them by adding a prefix value two and three with the help of this prefix like 1234
5678.
I'm giving a order that you need to apply these Yaml files inside your Kubernetes cluster.
So in future whenever you want to deploy all our microservices into a brand new cluster, first we need
to create the keycloak service post that we need to create the config map followed by config server,
Eureka server, accounts, loans, cards and Gateway.
So these are order that we can follow to make our life easy.
As a next step, I'm going to show you what I have written in all these files except configmaps and
configserver because you're already familiar with the content that we have written in these two files.
So let me go to the text editor and open all the Kubernetes manifest files.
Here first i will show you what is there inside keycloak.yaml file.
So here nothing new for every microservice or any service that we want to deploy into Kubernetes.
We need to first create a deployment object followed by what is the service object.
If you see under that deployment object, I'm trying to give a label name as Keycloak, the same label
app name we should mention under the services label apps.
That's how the Kubernetes is going to connect to this service with the deployment object of Keycloak
service.
So after this metadata name labels app under the specification, I'm mentioning the replicas as one
selector match labels app as keycloak under the specification.
If you see the container name is going to be keycloak.
And this is the image and these are the arguments that I want to consider while starting my container.
So since we want to start our Kubernetes cluster in a dev mode, we need to provide these args with
the value start - dev.
Now the new information that you may find here compared to config server is, we are trying to pass the
environment variables to this deployment instructions.
So to pass the environment variables, we need to mention the element E and V and this we can define
any number of environment variables. With the help of this hyphen.
So after hyphen we need to mention what is the name of your environment variable that you want to inject
to your container.
So the name of the property is KEYCLOAK_ADMIN to this environment variable.
I want to provide the value that I stored inside the config maps. For the same,
we need to mention this value from, but there is an error here.
We need to make sure that value from is just below the name.
So let me try to correct this in the remaining property as well.
So now this looks good.
And similarly this entire name has to come
exactly
under the env, just like other environment.
So if I try to see here, this is present at the same location where my previous environment variable
is started, this looks good.
Now you can see under the name I'm trying to use value from.
So from where I want to fetch the value under this value from, we need to mention config map key ref
and what is a config map where we stored this value?
So the config map name is easybank - configmap the same name we have to give under the
configMapKeyRef name element and at last inside our config map we may have many environment variables.
So which environment variable it has to consider.
That's why we need to give the key value so it will go and look for these key value inside the config
maps
and this is the  property.
So against this there is a value which is admin.
The same will be injected as a value to this property with the name KEYCLOAK_ADMIN. If needed,
here we can mention any property name here,
like I can mention something like username.
The same name I have to use inside the key of config map key rev.
But please don't mention this username here under the environment name because whatever you have mentioned
inside the environment name that will be feed as an input to your container or your spring boot applications.
So if you give some random property name, it is not going to work.
That's why always make sure you are giving the correct environment variable name under the Env, but
you have a flexibility to maintain any
nickname inside Configmap and under these configmap.
But to be consistent and to make our life easy, I'm going to maintain the key as same as property name
inside my configmap and inside my config map file as well. As next step,
I also injected one more environment variable with the name keycloak admin password and the same syntax
we have to follow here.
And at last I also provided what are the port configurations?
It has to start at the container port 8080.
After the deployment instructions, we have service related instructions as well.
Here also, we are trying to expose our keycloak service as a LoadBalancer.
That means anyone can access my keycloak server at the port 7080.
But please make sure that you are mentioning the target port as same as your container port because
under container port and target port we need to mention what is the port where your container is going
to start internally inside your Kubernetes cluster.
Now let me go and check what is present inside the EurekaServer.yaml.
Here also we followed the same syntax.
First we are going to provide that deployment instructions.
You can see here the image name
I have mentioned the Eureka Server, but the tag name I have mentioned that S12, but not the S14.
Do you know what is the reason?
The reason is, as of now, we decided to not go with the Kafka setup inside this section because there
is an easier approach that we can follow once we discuss about the helm charts in the coming sections.
And since my Section 13 and Section 14 has the changes related to event driven microservices, they'll
expect an Rabbitmq setup or Kafka setup.
So since I want to avoid that inside this section and focus on deploying our own developed microservices,
I'm trying to mention section12 tag name, which is S12, the same tag name I have mentioned inside
the config server as well.
As you can see here, the config server is going to use that tag name S12.
Now if you go back to Eureka Server here for Eureka Server, we need to feed the two environments.
One is what is the application name of Eureka Server?
So the Eureka server application name is present under the key name, which is Eureka application name.
So the same I can go and check inside the config maps.
So the value is going to be Eureka server.
The same will be injected into my Eureka server container.
Do you know why I'm not using the same key name which is spring application name under my config maps?
Because we need to define the same environment variable for all the remaining microservices.
With that reason I have mentioned different, different key names inside the config map.
The same I'm going to refer inside my Kubernetes manifest files. At last,
I'm also injecting what is a config server endpoint URL.
The config server endpoint URL is going to be config server 8071.
After the deployment instructions, we have service instructions also with the LoadBalancer.
This you are already familiar.
Now let me go and check what is present inside the accounts.yaml. So inside accounts.yaml,
nothing is new,
everything is same.
Like so we're using s12 tag for accounts microservice compared to Eureka Server,
there is a new environment variable that we are trying to inject, which is what is our Eureka client
service URL default zone.
Because my accounts microservice has to register itself with the Eureka server.
That's why we are trying to provide these environment variable and after deployment we also have service
instructions.
The same kind of setup you'll be able to see inside the loans and cards microservice and Gateway server
as well.
So for Gateway Server also here we are going to use S12.
If you can scroll down for Gateway Server, we are going to inject one more environment variable compared
to other microservice, which is what is the keycloak server URL where my resource server has to fetch
the certificate.
So the same I'm trying to fetch from the easybank config map.
So with this I'm assuming your super clear with all the Kubernetes manifest files that we have created
for the remaining microservices. In the next lecture, let's try to apply them into Kubernetes cluster
so that all our containers will get deployed into the cluster and post that we can also validate the
same.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.