As of now, we deployed all our microservices into Kubernetes cluster with the help of Kubernetes manifest
files.
By following the same steps, you can always deploy any number of microservices inside your real projects
as well.
With that as a developer, you will be happy and your DevOps team members will also happy with the successful
deployment of your microservices.
But there are few problems if you try to follow these basic approach of deploying microservices into
Kubernetes cluster.
So let me try to explain you what are those problems?
And I'm also going to give a quick introduction about what is the solution that we are going to use.
As of now,
if you go and see inside the Kubernetes folder that is available inside the Section15, inside this
folder, we are maintaining all the Kubernetes manifest files.
So there are eight different Kubernetes manifest files which will help us to create the config map to
deploy our microservices, to expose our microservices.
But don't you think there is a problem here as of now
think like I have only seven microservices or six microservices.
That's why I'm able to achieve this job very quickly by creating these manifest files inside these Kubernetes
folder.
But think like inside real projects, you may have hundreds of microservices preparing Kubernetes manifest
files and maintaining the same for all
your microservice is going to be a nightmare. For some time,
let's assume that you are somehow able to create manifest files for all your microservices and you are
able to proceed with your Kubernetes deployment.
But the problem is not ended there.
We have one more problem.
Once you have created all these Kubernetes manifest files to deploy your microservices into Kubernetes,
you need to apply all these manifest files one by one.
Like, you know, previously, whenever we are trying to deploy a particular microservice, we ran the
command, which is kubectl apply -f and what is a Kubernetes manifest file?
This way I need to apply all the manifest files for all my 100 microservices.
Let's assume you are also fine with this problem.
You are super patient to apply all the files one by one, but the problem is not going to end there.
We have more problems.
The problem is you may have multiple environments inside your organization development, qa, production.
So for all these environments you may have Kubernetes cluster and for different, different environments,
you may have different, different requirements.
Like inside Dev, you may want to have only one replica of accounts microservice and other microservices,
whereas in QA you want to have three replicas and inside prod you may want to deploy five replicas,
ten replicas based upon your incoming traffic.
So in such scenarios you need to maintain your Kubernetes manifest files according to your different
different environments that you may have.
So now imagine you have hundreds of manifest files which are going to be multiplied by number of your
environments that will triple or double your Kubernetes manifest files.
So are you fine facing these challenges?
Off course, no one will use this approach because this takes a lot of effort.
On top of that, even whenever we want to uninstall your microservices in such scenarios.
also, we need to run the commands like kubectl delete and provide the Kubernetes manifest file.
I can also show you that in the demo.
So here first I'll try to delete the gateway server.
So for the same I'll try to run the command, which is kubectl delete hyphen -f and what is my gateway
server Yaml file?
So this will delete my deployment and services of gateway server.
So the same I need to run for all the remaining microservices like for cards I have done just now.
And very similarly I'm going to do for loans,
now let me do the same for accounts microservice and post the accounts microservice,
I'm going to delete Eureka server followed by config server and after the config server I'm also going
to delete the config map that I have created and post that I'm also going to delete the keycloak as
well.
So if you see here how painful it is for me if I want to empty my cluster or if I want to uninstall
my applications from the Kubernetes cluster, think like if you are having hundreds of microservice,
then you need to run this command 100 different times, which is a challenge for anyone.
Now, if you see here inside my cluster, all of my deployments, parts, everything got deleted because
we deleted all our deployments and services with the help of this delete command.
Now, going back to the problems or challenges that we have with this approach, so how are we going
to solve these problems or challenges for the same we have a solution.
Let me show you the solution.
The solution is Helm.
So Helm is a package manager for Kubernetes.
So
it is a very quick introduction.
Inside the next section, we are going to focus on Helm how to set up our microservices with the help
of helm.
I'm sure you're going to like Helm because it is going to make our life super, super easy.
Before I try to close this section, let me confirm you that I'm going to check in this entire section15
folder inside which you will be able to see the Kubernetes manifest files.
So please refer them if you have any questions.
I'm not going to check in any microservice related code inside the section 15 because we didn't make
any code changes.
Throughout this section, we are exploring more about Kubernetes, so please refer to these files if
you have any questions inside the GitHub repo, please take a break.
After taking a break, come back and we can continue the discussion about Helm.
Thank you.
Bye.