We have our Eureka Server running successfully.
As a next step, let's try to make the changes inside the accounts microservice to connect with the
Eureka Server.
So with the changes that we are going to make my accounts microservice during the startup, it is going
to register with the Eureka Server and at the same time it is also going to send the heartbeats regularly
by default every 30s.
Please follow the steps that I'm going to discuss because I want you to try the similar changes inside
the loans and cards
microservice. So the very first change that we need to do inside the accounts microservice is, to add
the dependency related to the Eureka client.
So for the same, let me go to the pom.xml.
So here I need to add a dependency.
So to understand what are the dependency details, you can click on these, add dependencies and search
for Eureka.
And this time please select Eureka Discovery Client.
Please do not select Eureka Server.
So let me add this dependency and before that I will try to delete all other dependencies that we have
here.
Now I'll click on this explore button and with that there will be only a single dependency with the
name Spring Cloud starter Netflix Eureka Client.
So let me copy these values.
And the same I'm trying to mention here just after the spring cloud starter config.
So let me save these changes and load the maven changes.
Now as a next step, we need to add few set of properties inside the application.yml of accounts
microservice.
So let me open the application.yml file here inside my applications.yml file.
First, I need to provide the eureka related properties like what is the URL of Eureka server to which
my accounts microservice can try to communicate with?
So for the same, most of the properties are going to be very similar to what we have mentioned for
the Eureka Server.
So for the Eureka server inside the eazybytes-config, we have mentioned these properties,
so let's copy these properties the same I'm going to mention here, but here instead of false, we are
going to mention true.
Just to make sure our accounts microservice will try to fetch the registry details whenever it is trying
to connect with other microservices.
And very similarly, since we want our account microservice to be registered with the Eureka server,
I'm trying to mention the value
true.
Now under the service URL we can mention the hardcoded value like localhost and the port number of Eureka
server is going to be 8070 slash Eureka, the same URL we have mentioned inside the Eureka server as
well.
We need to make sure we are using the same URL here.
After mentioning these properties, we don't need to mention these hostname as localhost here because
this is not the Eureka server, this is the client microservice which will connect with the Eureka server.
With that reason we don't need these property, but after removing the property we need to mention a
new property here which is prefer IP address and the value I'm going to mention as true.
So we are trying to create a property which is eureka.instance.prefer IP address as true.
The reason why I'm setting this prefer IP address as true is whenever my accounts microservice is trying
to register with the Eureka server by default, it will try to register with the host name.
The host names will make sense whenever you are trying to use DNS mappings inside your microservices
network.
But inside our local system, we don't have any DNS mapping set up.
We should use prefer IP address as true so that my accounts microservice will register with my Eureka
server by using the IP address.
So behind the scenes, whenever my other microservice, they are trying to connect with the accounts
microservice.
My Eureka server is going to share the IP address details of accounts microservice so that the other
microservices, they can connect with my accounts
microservice. So that's the purpose of this property.
Once we mention these properties, now my accounts microservice can connect with my Eureka server.
Apart from these properties, we should also add some other properties related to the actuator and info.
So let's try to understand what are those.
Here I'm going to create new property with the parent element as info, Under the info element, I'm going
to mention one more element, which is app.
And inside this app I'm going to mention an element which is name to this name, I'm going to give a
name value, which is accounts because this belongs to the accounts microservice and post that I'm going
to mention the element which is description. To this description element,
I'm going to mention the value as EazyBankAccounts application.
It is just a description that we are trying to use to explain about this app.
And at last we can also mention one more element here, which is version and the version I'm going to
mention values something like 1.0.0.
So the purpose and why we are adding these info related information is the same information we can see
inside the Eureka dashboard.
Because there will be multiple microservices will be registered with the Eureka dashboard.
If you want to know some details about those microservices, this info information will be useful and
the same we can try to understand with the Eureka dashboard.
When I show you the Eureka dashboard, it will make more sense to you how these info related information
is being displayed and these info information will be exposed as part of an actuator endpoint url.
And by default the info related actuator URL is not enabled.
We need to enable the same by adding a property under management followed by info.
So just under the management, I'm going to create one new element which is info under this info I'm going
to mention env environment and post that enable followed by what is the value which is true.
So I'm trying to enable the environment info related information with the help of this property.
As a next step, I'm going to add the properties related to the shutdown.
Like I said before, whenever the account's microservice is trying to shut down, it will deregister
the details from the Eureka server to demo you the same in the coming lectures.
I need to enable an actuator URL which will allow me to shut down my accounts microservice gracefully.
So for the same I'm going to mention a new element under the management.
So just under the same position where we have endpoints.
I'm going to mention a new element which is endpoint, singular form.
And at this endpoint I'm going to mention shutdown.
Under the shutdown, I'm going to mention enabled as true.
Once we enable these shutdown related endpoint, we should also expose the shutdown related APIs by
mentioning a property to mention the same property,
I'm going to mention a new element at the root location.
You can see this is the starting element.
Here I'm going to mention end points under end points
I'm going to mention shutdown and post that I'm going to mention enabled as true.
So please make sure these end points is different from what we have under management.endpoints.
So this endpoints should be at the starting position of your line.
So please make sure this portion is very important.
You can refer to the GitHub repo if you have any questions.
So we have made all the required changes.
Now I can save these changes and do a build.
Once the build is completed, I can try to start my accounts microservice. So for the same I'm going
to open the accounts application class and try to start the application in debug mode.
But please note that before you try to start the accounts microservice, please make sure config server
and Eureka server is started inside your local system.
Now here you can see my accounts
microservice started at the 8080 and immediately it registered itself with the Eureka Server.
That's why you're able to see these registration status as 204.
That means it tried to register with Eureka Server and it got a response 204 from the Eureka Server.
You can also see other kind of information like starting Heartbeat Executor renewal interval is 30s,
which means my Eureka server by default, it is going to expect a heartbeat every 30s from my accounts
microservice.
Now let me go to the Eureka dashboard and confirm if my accounts microservice is registered with the
Eureka server.
The URL that we need to access here is, localhost 8070 which will display the Eureka dashboard.
You can see here right now, under the instances currently registered with Eureka, there is an application
with the name accounts.
So whatever name you have defined inside the application.yml file under the property which is
spring.application name, the same name is going to be considered and registered with the Eureka Server.
So as of now we have only one instance.
That's why you're able to see only one here in the Eureka dashboard and the status of these one instance
of accounts
microservice is up.
If you try to click on this link, it will show you the more details about these accounts
microservice like what is the app name, what is the description and what is the version?
Now I'm assuming you are clear on how the info related information that we have configured inside the
application.yml.
The same is linked inside our Eureka dashboard and whenever we click on this you can see against the
accounts microservice instance it is trying to invoke actuator/info path at the port 8080 and
since we registered our accounts microservice using IP address it is using my local IP address.
But here you can see it is showing some different hostname.
This is because inside our local system, whenever we install Docker and other type of softwares, they're
going to make some host entries against the local host IP address.
So that's why instead of local host it is showing some other hostname.
So don't worry about this host name now here
you see, we are able to see an error, which is like emergency
eureka may be incorrectly claiming the instances, so there is some error.
Don't worry about this error.
We are going to discuss about this beautiful concept why we are seeing this error in the coming lectures.
But for next few lectures, please ignore this error.
This is not an error.
It's a warning about the Eureka dashboard.
So with this we are able to successfully connect our accounts Microservice to the Eureka server with
that.
Now my accounts microservice.
During the startup it resisted itself with the Eureka server and at the same time it is also going to
send the heartbeat signal every 30s.
I hope you are clear about all the changes that we have done inside this accounts
microservice I'm giving an assignment to you here.
By the time you come to the next lecture, please make the similar changes inside loans and cards.
microservice.
If you are facing any issues, don't worry.
I'm going to show you a demo quickly about loans and cards changes inside the next lecture.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.