Hope you are successful at making the Eureka related changes inside the loans and cards microservice.
If not, don't worry, we are going to revise again very quickly the very first change that we have
to make inside cards and loans
microservice is and the pom.xml.
Please make sure you are adding a new dependency which is spring-cloud-starter-netflix-eureka-client.
So please make sure you have added this.
I have added this inside the cards very similarly, if we can validate inside the loans microservice
also I have added the same inside the pom.xml as a next step we need to go to the application.yml
file of cards microservice.
So if I can open the application.yml file here you can see I already added all the required dependencies
like shut down enable, info env enable true, endpoint shut down enable true.
And after that eureka instance prefer IP address as true, client fetch registry as true, register with
Eureka as true and service url
I have mentioned the localhost 8070 Eureka. And at last I also mentioned the info related properties,
but here there is a copy paste mistake.
The name should be cards and description should be Eazy Bank Cards Application.
So with this I should be good.
Now let me validate the changes I have done inside the application.yml of loans microservice.
So inside this application.yml file also
I have added very similar properties and here the info name looks good like loans and description
also looks good like Easy Bank Loans Application.
So after making these changes, save all your changes and do a build.
Once the build is completed, start your loans microservice and cards microservice.
So before you try to start this applications, please make sure your config server Eureka Server is
running inside your local system. So they are already in running status inside my system.
Now I will also go to the cards microservice and try to start the same.
So let me open the cards application that I have here.
So I'm just trying to start in a debug mode.
As a next step, I will go to my Eureka dashboard and validate if my cards and loans microservices are
registered successfully or not.
As of now, you can see there is only accounts
microservice.
I'm trying to refresh this page.
As soon as I refresh, you can see we have cards and loans related
microservices also registered themselves with the Eureka Service Discovery agent.
I can also click on this and validate the info details.
They are accurate.
Like at 9000 port, we have deployed cards microservice and we are able to see the cards related information.
Very similarly, let's validate loans microservice information.
So here also this looks good.
So let me close this information.
I hope you are clear.
We are trying to implement this service discovery and service registration along with the load balancing
step by step.
The very first step that we need to make sure is, we should have a separate centralized server which
is responsible for storing all the service registry details and act as a service discovery agent.
That's why we have built the Eureka Server and post that we should make sure all our accounts microservice,
they are registering their details during the startup and that's what we have done by making the changes
inside the respective individual microservices.
Here I'm going to show you a interesting URL of Eureka Server.
So the URL is localhost:8070/eureka/aps.
If you try to access this, you can see you should be able to see all the apps and the instances that
are registered with the Eureka Server.
So under application you can see the application name is loans.
So under this loans, as of now, we have only one instance registered.
If you have multiple instances of loans microservice registered, you will be able to see multiple instances
information.
So as of now we are able to see only one instance information.
So this is the instance ID, this is the hostname, this is the app name, IP address,
what is the status and what is the port number?
And if you can scroll down, there is also some good information on what is the default renewal interval
in seconds and what is the registration time, what is the last renewal timestamp and what is the service
up timestamp?
And very similarly, what is the home page URL, what is the status page URL?
What is the health check?
This way we have lot of information about our instance that is registered with the Eureka Server.
Very similarly, we also have here accounts related information and this application name accounts.
We have one instance registered and the similar lines.
You will also see cards microservice and its instance details.
So if you have multiple instances under a microservice, you should be able to see all of them inside
the response
whenever someone is trying to invoke this URL. Using this URL, only anyone can connect with my Eureka
server and they can try to get the service registration details.
As of now, you can see by default the response is coming in an XML format.
But what if you want in Json format?
So the
Eureka Server supports the Json format also.
So to get the response in a Json format, please take this URL and go to the postman.
So inside the postman I already have the folder with the request name Eureka Apps, so you should be
also have this,
If you have imported my postman collection that I have provided inside the GitHub repo.
So if you click on this request.
So this is the same URL that we tried to invoke before you try to send this request, please make sure
you are creating a new header with the name, accept and inside the value.
Please make sure you are mentioning application slash Json.
So if you try to uncheck this you can see by default I get in an XML format, but if I try to send this
header with the value application slash Json, I am getting all the response in a Json format.
For some reason, if you are looking for only accounts related information, then you can just mention
accounts inside the URL and you will get only accounts related information.
And similarly, if you are looking for parts, then mention the same cards inside the URL, you will
get only cards related information along with the instance details of cards
microservice.
I hope you are seeing and realizing the power of Eureka Server, which is acting as a discovery agent.
So we have only three microservices here.
But think of if you have 100 microservice, how useful this Eureka server for any internal communication
where one microservice is trying to connect with other microservice.
We are not doing any manual job of updating the IP address details into the registry.
All of these details are getting registered automatically during the startup of the microservices.
I hope you are successful at creating an Eureka server and registering all your microservice details
with the Eureka Server during the startup of the microservices.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.