As a next step, let's try to explore more about service discovery and how the client side load balancing
is going to work whenever we are using Eureka Server inside our microservices network.
To show a demo about these concepts, we are going to build a new REST API inside the accounts microservice.
The responsibility of these new REST API is, it has to accumulate account related information, loans
related information and cards related information based upon a given mobile number and it should consolidate
all the response from the other microservices like loans and cards along with the accounts related data.
So all the data of a given customer, it has to respond back to the client whoever is invoking these
new REST API.
So here you can see we have a scenario where my accounts microservice does not have any information
related to cards and loans. So it has to connect with the cards and loans microservice to get that
data.
And that's how we are going to have a scenario where accounts microservice is trying to communicate
with the other microservices internally inside our microservice network.
So to establish the internal communication between the microservices like we discussed previously,
we need to use open feign client library.
So before I try to implement those changes, let me stop all the running instances inside my local system.
Now, here under the start.spring.io, please make sure you have selected Maven.
After that, I'm going to click on this Add dependency and search for open feign.
So you can see there is an starter project with the name OpenFeign.
After selecting this dependency, I'm going to click on this explore button and here we are going to
copy the dependency details.
So let me copy this value. As a next step, I'll open the pom.xml of accounts microservice just after
Netflix Eureka Client,
I'm going to add this dependency and post that I'm going to click on this load Maven changes.
With this, we should have all the open feign related libraries downloaded into the accounts
microservice After making these changes inside the pom.xml let's go to the spring boot main class inside
the accounts microservice. So inside my accounts
microservice the main class is AccountsApplication.
Here I'm going to put an annotation which which is @EnableFeignClients.
So the purpose on why we need to mention this annotation is this will enable the feign clients related
functionality inside my accounts
microservice.
With that my account microservice can connect with other microservices like loans and cards.
So let me save this changes.
Now here in order to connect with the loans and cards microservice in a traditional approach, we will
use some rest template or web client and to those REST template and web client classes are interfaces.
We are going to pass,
what is the URL,
what is the request data,
what is the port number,
what is the exception handling ?
So we need to write all the implementation code or actual logic to invoke the loans and cards
microservice.
But whenever we are using open feign client, we don't have to write the implementation code.
We just have to write that declarative code.
We are already following this kind of approach inside the spring data JPA. For suppose if you go to the
repository package. Here we have accounts repository.
Did I write any implementation code here for to fetch the records based upon the customerId ?
No,
I have written only that declarative code, which means I only created an interface along with the abstract
methods and behind the scenes my spring data JPA framework is going to generate the implementation code
at the runtime.
Very similarly, whenever we are trying to use open feign client, we don't have to write the implementation
code.
We just need to create the interfaces along with the abstract methods.
So let's try to understand how to develop the same. For the same here, just under the services, I'm
going to create a new package with the name
com.eazybytes.accounts.service.client under this client package
I'm going to create a new interface.
So let me create a new interface here.
So the interface name, I'm going to keep it as CardsFeignClient because this interface is going to
help my accounts
microservice, to connect with the cards
microservice. So let me create this new interface.
So now I have an empty interface. To use the open Feign libraries,
we need to make sure we are mentioning an annotation here which is @FeignClient.
To this @FeignClient,
we need to mention a value which is cards because the same value, which is cards we have used to register
with the Eureka Server.
If you can recall inside the Eureka dashboard, all the cards related instances, they will register
with the logical name cards.
So the same cards we need to mention here so that my feign client will connect with the Eureka server
at the runtime and it will try to get all the instance details with the logical name cards.
So that's the purpose of this
annotation and the value that we have mentioned here.
Now, inside this interface, I'm going to create a new abstract method and whatever abstract method
that we are going to create inside this interface, this method signature has to match with the actual
REST API method that we have defined inside the card microservice.
If you go to the cards controller, inside the cards controller, we have a method with the name fetch
card details.
So I need to create the very similar method inside my CardsFeignclient interface.
So let me copy this method details and mention the same here.
But here inside this interface we are not going to write any implementation code.
We are just going to define them as abstract methods.
Once we define these abstract method, we can remove these validations related code because the validations
will be performed at the REST API level but not here.
That's why we don't have to mention the validations.
Now you can see here we are following the same method name like we have inside the CardsController.
The method name
you can choose whatever name inside this FeignClient interface, but please make sure the method signature
like method input parameters, return parameters along with the method access type should be same as
what we have defined inside the actual microservice.
So once we define this here, you can see we don't have the CardsDto inside the accounts microservic.
So let's try to create the CardsDto inside the accounts
microservice. So for the same, I'm going to copy the DTO from the cards
microservice. So if I go to the cards microservice I'll be having a package and the dto package I need
to copy the CardsDto class.
So let me copy the same into the dto package of accounts microservice.
And very similarly, I also need LoansDto because we are going to develop a new interface for
LoansFeignClient as well.
So let me copy the LoansDto
also. So here under the loans project and going into the dto package and inside this DTO package
we have LoansDto.
So let me copy these LoansDto into the AccountsDto package.
So with this we have copied all the required DTOs into the accounts
microservice. Now I'll open the
CardsFeignClient the error should get resolved,
If not, let's try to resolve these by importing these cards.
So with this now we have declared the abstract method.
On top of this method we need to mention the REST API path details that my actual method inside the
CardsController is going to support.
You can see it is going to support get mapping fetch.
So let me copy this value and paste the same inside the CradsFeignClient
.
But apart from this fetch, if you see inside the CardsController, we also have some path which is
specific to entire controller.
The path is /api.
So that's why we need to mention the exact path, which is /api/fetch.
With this we should be good if needed
we can also mention like consumes as application/json.
We are trying to communicate to the FeignClient that these API which we have inside the cards microservice,
it is going to accept that Json input data.
So now if you see this abstract method is matching exactly with what we have defined inside the cards
microservice. So that's the one primary rule that we need to follow.
On top of that, we need to make sure we are mentioning this annotation along with the logical name
that cards microservice is going to register with the Eureka Server.
So behind the scenes, my cards FeignClient will connect with the Eureka Server and try to fetch all
the instances that are registered with the logical name cards.
And once it receives 1 or 2 or any other instance details, it will try to cache those details for 30s,
which is the default period.
And within these 30s it is not going to connect again with the Eureka Server, but instead it is going
to leverage the details present inside the cache.
So based upon the IP details inside the cache, it is going to invoke this API along with the request which
is mobile number.
So behind the scenes, all the implementation code will be generated by the open feign client.
So here you can see we have not written any business logic.
We are just telling to our feign client how to connect to other microservice.
What is the method signature,
what is the request parameter,
what is the request structure,
what is the response structure,
what is the rest API path ?
So if you define those meta details, the remaining magic will be taken care by the feign client.
Now let me try to create a very similar feign client interface for loans microservice API
also. For the same, I'm going to copy these interface, which is CardsFeignClient and paste the same
inside the same package.
And I'm going to rename this to LoansFeignClient.
So let me click on this
ok.
Inside this LoansFeignClient, we need to make sure for this LoansFeignClient we are passing the logical name
of loans microservice the loans microservice logical name that
we are following is loans itself.
So let me save this.
After this, the response, it is going to send LoansDto's.
That's why we need to mention LoansDto inside the return type of the method and the request param it is
going to be the same which is mobile number.
So let's try to confirm the same inside the LoansController which is present inside the loans microservice.
So here if you look for the fetch API inside the fetch API, the method name is fetch loan details and
it is going to accept the request to param, which is mobile number.
So we are trying to pass the same from the Feignclient interface
also, I can also copy this method name and mention the same here.
With this we should be good to leverage these FeignClient interfaces inside our accounts
microservice to interact with the other microservices like loans and cards
microservice.
I hope you are clear with all the steps that we have followed till now. In the next lecture, let's try
to continue this discussion.
Thank you,
Bye.