As of now, we made the required changes inside the accounts microservice to connect with the loans,
microservice and cards microservice.
So we have created these LoansFeignClient and very similarly, we also created CardsFeignClient as well.
Now as a next step, let's try to use them inside our accounts microservice to communicate with
the other microservices and we should accept the response and we should consolidate all the response
from three microservices and send the same to the client application.
Since we want to send the consolidate response from accounts, cards and loans microservice, we need
to make sure we are creating a dto supporting these consolidated information. For the same inside my accounts
microservice I'm going to create a new dto with the name CustomerDetailsDto. So this is going to hold
all the details about a customer like accounts, cards, loans along with their personal details.
So let me create this class.
Instead of typing all the fields, what I can do is, I'll go to the CustomerDto
since all the information that we are going to send inside the CustomerDetailsDto is very
similar to what we have inside these CustomerDto I'm going to copy the content from this class, so
let me take this @Data and @Schema the same I'll try to mention inside the CustomerDetailsDto.
.
So here the schema name, I'll just keep it as customer details and the description
I will change it as schema to hold customer, account, cards and loans information.
So this is the schema that is going to hold all the information related to the customer, accounts, cards
and loans.
First, let me get the details of customer from the CustomerDto.  So I'm going to take all these fields
here and paste the same inside the CustomerDetailsDto. Once we have pasted these details
right now you can see there is customer related information like what is the name, what is the email,
what is the mobile number?
And what are his account details?
Very similarly, we should also pass cards details and loans details .For the same, just like how
we have mentioned the AccountsDto very similarly
I'm going to mention CardsDto and LoansDto. So let me import the LoansDto here and post that I will change
the variable name to LoansDto and here the description
I'm going to keep it as Loans Details of the Customer.
And now I'm going to change this AccountDto
to CardsDto like you can expect the field name I'm trying to change and the description also,
I'll try to change with cards details of the customer.
So with this now we have the CustomerDetailsDto.
is ready and this is going to hold the consolidated data of my customer.
As a next step, I'm going to open the controller package and here I'll create a new controller and
the controller name is going to be CustomerController.
Inside this controller, I'm going to create a new REST API.
First, let me mention RestController.
On top of this, I will try to copy other open API specification related information from AccountsController.
So let me take all these tag information RequestMapping, @Validated and mention the same
inside the new controller that we have created.
So I'm trying to paste here, post that I'm going to update this name and description.
I'll mention the name as REST API for Customers in EasyBank and post that, I'm going to update this
description with a new description.
So the description is going to be REST APIs in EasyBank to fetch customer details and RequestMapping
path API.
It should be fine and produces media type application
Json value should be fine, RestController and @Validated, everything is fine.
Now inside this controller, I'm going to create a method.
The method is public responseEntity().
And to this responseEntity() I'm going to pass CustomerDetailsDto and the method name I'm going to
mention as fetchCustomerDetails() to this method, we are going to accept the mobileNumber of my customer
on top of the mobile number.
We are also going to do some validations like rejects, validations and make sure that mobile number
is a ten digit mobile number.
We already have such validations defined inside the AccountsController under fetch API.
So if you can scroll to the fetch API, we have this information here.
So let me copy this value and mention the same inside the CustomerController.
So now inside this method I can write the business logic, but before that I'm going to mention what
is the REST API path that this method is going to support.
So this method is going to support Http method.
That's why I need to mention get mapping along with the path, which is fetchCustomerDetails.
I'm going to have the API path as fetchCustomerDetails.
So whenever someone is trying to invoke API class, fetchCustomerDetails this method
will get invoked.
So to this method we can also mention open API specification related annotations so we can copy the
same from here which we have inside the AccountsController.
The same I can mention here.
Once we pasted these annotations, we can try to change the summary description like Fetch Customer
Details REST API and here I can mention REST API to fetch Customer details based upon a mobile number
and post that under the API responses we should mention these API response like 200, 500 which we are
going to send in case of success scenario and failure scenario.
Now I need to write the business logic inside this method. To write the business logic,
we are going to leverage the service layer for the same inside the service package,
let me create a new interface just like how we have IAccountsMicroservice.
I'm going to create a new interface with the name ICustomerService inside this interface, I'm going
to create an abstract method which is going to return CustomerDetailsDto and the method name is going
to be fetchCustomerDetails() and this method will accept mobile number as an input.
So this is an abstract method.
I'm going to mention few method Java comments here.
Now, as a next step, I'm going to create an implementation of this interface. For the same, let's
go to the Impl package and here I'm going to create a new Java class with the name CustomerServiceImpl.
Inside this class, we are going to implement the interface, which is a customer service.
So I'll get a compilation error.
So let me click on this and implement methods and, and override this method, which is fetchCustomerDetails().
Inside this method,
as of now you can see I have empty logic before I try to write some logic.
First, let me try to inject all the dependencies into this ServiceImpl class.
So the dependencies that I have here is first, I am going to use AccountsRepository to fetch all the
accounts related information from the database that these accounts microservice is trying to use.
Very similarly, I'm going to require CustomerRepository to fetch all the customer related information
from the database that this accounts microservice is right now using, coming to the loans and cards
related information.
In order to get those details, we need to invoke the other microservices.
So whenever we want to invoke the other microservices, we need to make sure we are using the feign client
related interfaces that we have created.
That's why I'm trying to inject those interfaces to this service class.
So let me mention the object name here.
Post that very similarly,
I'm going to mention LoansFeignClient along with an object name.
So these are the four dependencies that I have mentioned inside my CustomerServiceImpl.
So on top of this class I'm going to mention two annotation, which is @Service and
@AllArgsConstructor.
Since I have mentioned @AllArgsConstructor, my Lombok is going to generate an constructor
with all the fields that we have defined inside the class like AccountsRepository, CustomerRepository,
CardsFeignClient and LoansFieldClient.
So whenever we have only single constructor inside your class, the autowiring is going to happen automatically
without the need of mentioning @Autowire annotation on each of these fields.
So now, as a next step, I need to write some logic inside my fetchCustomerDetails().
We already wrote some business logic to fetch the accounts and customer related information from the
database inside the AccountServiceImpl.
So let me open the same.
And here under the fetch account you can see there is some logic that we can use.
So let me take this code and mention the same inside the new method that we have created.
As of now, you can see from the database we are trying to fetch the customer data based upon the mobile
number that we have received.
In case if we don't have any records, then we are going to throw this an exception.
Very similarly, we are trying to fetch the accounts related information based upon the customerId
that we retrieved from the customer table.
So now as a next step, I need to map this customer data and accounts data to this CustomerDetailsDto.
So as of now we don't have any mapper method that will convert customer and accounts data into the customer
details.
So that's why we need to write a new method inside the CustomerMapper.
Inside this CustomerMapper, I'm going to create a method very similar to mapToCustomer(). So let
me copy this method and rename this to mapToCustomerDetailsDto.
And the return type from this method is going to be CustomerDetailsDto, and the input parameters for
this method will be Customer.
And the second parameter we need to change to CustomerDetailsDto.
And now inside the method we need to map all the data from the customer()
to these CustomerDetailsDto.
For the same, we just need to update these reference inside the method.
With that, we have a method ready which will map all the data from Customer to CustomerDetailsDto.
So I can go to my CustomerServiceImpl and here I'm going to use the customerMapper() method like
customer.mapToCustomerDetailsDto and to this method I'm going to pass the object of customer comma new
object of customer details to the output from this method
I'm going to catch on the left hand side with the return type, which is CustomerDetailsDto and a
variable name CustomerDetailsDto. Now using these CustomerDetailsDto,
I can try to invoke a method which is setAccountsDto() and I can pass the AccountsDto, but in order
to pass the AccountsDto first we need to convert these Accounts to the AccountsDto.
For the same, we can invoke a class which is AccountsMapper.mapToAccountsDto and to this method
we need to pass this accounts, new AccountsDto.
With this we have populated all the customer and accounts related information inside the
CustomerDetailsDto.
Now coming to the interesting part.
We need to populate very similarly loans related and cards related information inside this DTO, but
unfortunately we are not storing that information inside the database of AccountsMicroservice we are
storing inside the other microservices.
That's why we need to leverage the FeignClient interfaces that we have created and using them, we need
to invoke the methods we have defined inside them and post that we need to catch the response back and
populate the same into the CustomerDetailsDto.
So here, let me first try to invoke the loans related microservice. For the same,
we need to use the object that we have injected into this class with the name LoansFeignClient.
Against this object reference, we have a method which is fetchLoanDetails().
So this fetchLoanDetails() method we need to pass the mobile number that we have received and the output
from this method is going to be ResponseEntity of LoansDto.
So let me catch those details on the left hand side with the variable name, which is loansDtoResponseEntity.
.
Here
with this line behind the scenes, my FeignClient will connect with the Eureka Server and try to get
the loans instance details and it will perform some load balancing and invoke the actual microservice
REST API and we'll get the response.
As a next step, I can populate these loans related information into the CustomerDetailsDto.
So from this LoansDtoResponseEntity, I'm going to invoke the get body method.
So with the get body method, we are going to get the object which is LoansDto the same.
We are trying to get into the CustomerDetailsDto very similarly.
We can also do for cards microservice also.
So let me copy the same code.
And instead of loans feign client, we should use cards feign client and we should invoke the method
which is fetchCardDetails().
And here also we need to change to CardsDto and the variable name
also I'm going to change to CardsDtoResponseEntity post that we can set the CardsDto into the
CustomerDetailsDto by using these CardsDtoResponseEntity.
So let me copy this here with this all the information we have populated into the CustomerDetails.
So the same I'm going to return from this method with this, we have completed all the business logic
inside our ServiceImpl.
As a next step, I will go to the CustomerController here
first, I need to make sure that I am injecting the CustomerService implementation into this controller
class.
So the interface that we have for CustomerService is ICustomerService.
So I'll just mention as private final ICustomerService with the variable name ICustomerService.
After defining these variable, I'm going to create an constructor for these class which is CustomerController.
.
So to this constructor I'm going to pass ICustomerService as an input parameter and inside the constructor
I'm going to write the code, which is this.ICustomerService = ICustomerService.
Since there is only one constructor inside this class, we don't have to mention @Autowiring
on top of this constructor.
Now using this ICustomerService, we need to write the business logic inside this method.
The business logic is going to be very simple.
First, by using ICustomerService, I'm going to invoke the method which is fetchCustomerDetails().
And to this method I'm going to pass the mobile number that we are going to receive.
And on the left hand side, I'm going to catch the output with the help of CustomerDetailsDto and with
the variable name customerDetailsDto.
At last I need to return the same to the client application with the help of ResponseEntity using this
ResponseEntity,
I'm going to invoke the status and the status that we are going to send here is HttpStatus.OK.
.
So once we mention this HttpStatus, we are going to invoke the body method.
And to this body method we are going to pass the CustomerDetailsDto object.
With this,
we have made all the required changes.
So let me do a clean build here.
Once the build is completed, we can try to start all our microservices.
First
let me start the config server.
So my config server started.
So let me start Eureka server.
Now, after the Eureka server is started, I'm going to start other microservices like accounts, loans
and cards microservice.
So let me start the accounts
microservice first, followed by cards microservice and at last I'm going to start the loans
microservice I'll go to the Eureka dashboard and make sure all my microservices registered their details
with the Eureka Server.
So here I'm trying to refresh my Eureka dashboard.
You can see all the microservices instances are currently registered with Eureka.
As a next step, I'll go to the postman. Inside the Postman,
first, we need to make sure we are creating the data inside accounts, loans and cards
microservice with the same mobile number. Like you know we are right now using H2 database.
That's why we need to create the data again. For the same, it is going to be super quick and simple.
First, using create account, I will send this request.
Please make sure we are using the same mobile number in all microservices now using the same mobile
number,
I'm going to create a new card followed by new loan using the same mobile number.
Now all these APIs are successful.
As a next step, I'll go to the accounts folder and here you have an request with the name FetchCustomerDetails.
.
You can see this supports Http get method and the path is localhost:8080/API/fetchCustomerDetails
and mobile number is whatever we have used.
Now, if I try to invoke this request behind the scenes, my accounts microservice is going to connect
with the loans and cards microservice and will give me a consolidated response.
Are you ready
here, let me click on this send and hope for the best.
You can see we are getting a successful response and inside the response there is customer related information,
there is accounts information, there is loans, information, and we also have cards information.
If you see the beauty here, we didn't hard code the API or DNS names anywhere inside the accounts microservice.
we just given what is the logical name that other microservices they are going to use to register themselves
with the Eureka Server.
So whenever my accounts microservice is trying to connect with other microservices, it will go and
check with the service Discovery agent, which is Eureka!
Like, Hey, Eureka, please give me the details of loans
microservice. Eureka Server will say, okay buddy, please wait for a few seconds.
Let me check my registry details.
After checking the registry details, my Eureka server is going to provide all the instance details
along with their information to my accounts
microservice. If there are multiple instance details received behind the scenes, my feign client is going
to use the spring cloud load balancer and after performing the load balancing strategy, my feign client
is going to invoke one of the instance of loans or cards microservice.
Behind the scenes there is a lot of work went and all this work is right now being taken care by the
feign client Eureka Server.
We as developers, we wrote some configurations, we wrote some interfaces and methods, and with that
the communication between the microservices is happening perfectly.
I hope you are clear with all the information that we have discussed.
If there is some confusion, don't worry, please take your time.
Try to rewatch the video and try to check all the code changes that we have done and test in your local
and with that it will be super, super clear for you.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.