As of now, we discuss everything about the Eureka Server as a next step,
let's try to generate the Docker images of our microservices along with the config server and Eureka
server.
And once we generate the Docker images, we can update our Docker compose file and validate the service
discovery and registration related changes inside the Docker environment as well.
So for the same first, make sure your Docker server is running inside your local system.
And before I try to start the generating of the Docker images, I need to make sure I'm adding the jib
related plugin details inside the pom.xml of Eureka Server.
So this Eureka server project we have generated inside this section only by default, you can see we
have the plugin details related to the Spring boot maven plugin.
So here we need to add jib related plugin.
For the same you can open the pom.xml of any of the other microservice.
So inside the config server I'm trying to open the same and here I'm trying to copy the plugin details
related to the Google jib.
So let me copy this details and mention the same inside the Eureka server.
After mentioning these plugin details, I'm going to change this tag name from S6 to S8 because right
now we are into the section 8.
I need to update that tag related information inside other microservices also.
So inside my config server I'm trying to update the same.
After loading the maven changes, I'll open the pom.xml inside accounts microservice and update the
tag information here from S6 to S8.
I hope you are clear on why we have S6 here, but not S7 because we copied the code from the section 6
but not the section 7.
So that's why we are seeing the tag name as S6, which we need to update to S8.
Let's do the same for cards microservice also.
So at the end of the file here, we need to update the tag information to S8.
At last, we need to make the similar change inside the loans
microservice also.
So right now I'm into the pom.xml file of loans
microservice and I have made the required changes and loaded the maven changes.
So with this we can do a complete clean build of all the microservices.
Once the build is completed.
Please make sure you are stopping any running instances inside your IntelliJ idea.
As a next step, I'll go to the terminal.
So right now I'm into the section 8
inside my terminal I can navigate first to the config server.
Technically, we don't have to regenerate the docker image of config server because we didn't make any
changes inside the config server.
But like I said before, to be consistent with other Docker images, let's try to generate the Docker
image of config server that is specific to the section 8.
So to generate the Docker image, the command is mvn
compile jib:dockerBuild
with B capital.
So I'm trying to execute this command.
This will generate the new docker image for the config server with the tag name S8.
So it is going to take few seconds here.
So you can see right now the process is completed.
Let me clear the console and navigate back to the parent folder after this.
And now I will try to navigate to the Eureka server. For the Eureka Server
also, I'm going to generate the Docker image for the same
we need to run the same command, which is mvn compile jib:dockerBuild after Eureka Server.
We need to follow the similar process to generate the Docker image for accounts microservice.
So let me generate the accounts Micro service Docker image.
After the accounts microservice, we need to generate the Docker image for loans microservice.
You can generate these Docker images in any order.
The order that you follow here does not matter.
So now the generation of loans microservice docker image is completed.
Let me clean the console and navigate back to the parent folder.
Now I'll navigate into the cards folder and run the command, which is mvn compile jib:dockerBuild.
So this is the last Docker image that we need to generate inside our local system that is specific to
the Section 8.
As a next step, I'll go to the Docker dashboard and try to delete all the images related to the S7.
So all these images we no more needed.
I already pushed them into the Docker hub for your reference.
Since I want to save some space inside my local system, I'm trying to delete these unused images,
so let me click on this delete forever.
So with that, my Docker images related to S7 are deleted.
Now, if you search for S8, you will be able to see all five Docker images that we have generated right
now.
As a next step, I'm going to push all my Docker images into the remote Docker hub.
Like, you know, the command that we need to use here is docker image push docker.io and what is
your Docker account username?
In my case it is easybytes followed by configserver.
And what is a tag name.
Tag name is the S8.
We are going to push our config server Docker image from our local system to the remote hub Docker repository.
Behind the scenes
I'm going to push all my Docker images and come back.
I pushed all my Docker images related to section 8 into my Docker hub successfully.
You can see here right now, inside my Docker hub, we have a new Docker image with the name Eureka
Server.
Very similarly, we have other type of Docker images related to cards, loans, accounts and config
server.
If you try to open any of these under accounts, you should be able to see multiple Docker images with
different tag names like S4, S6, S7 and S8.
With this, we successfully generated the Docker images specific to Section8.
Inside the next lecture, let's try to update that Docker compose file and try to start all the services
with a single Docker compose command.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.