Inside this lecture, let's try to update the Docker compose file so that we can test Eureka related
changes inside that Docker environment.
So inside that Docker compose folder.
First I'm going to open the Docker compose file present inside the default profile.
Here first, we need to delete the Rabbitmq related service because we no more need it.
After this,
I'm also going to remove these depends on under the config server.
Since we don't have any rabbitmq service, we can remove the same followed by.
I'm going to update these image from S6 to S8 and now I'm going to copy this config server service
and paste the same just above the account service.
So this service name, I'm going to keep it as Eureka server.
So once we update the service name, we should also make sure we are mentioning that what is the Docker
image name, which is like eazybytes/eurekaserver:s8 and the container name.
I want to keep it as eurekaserver-ms.
Next, we need to update the port mapping like we know by default
Eureka server is going to start at the port 8070.
That's why I'm going to change this port mapping to 8070. After the port mapping
we should also provide the health check details for the Eureka Server because we want our accounts
microservice, loans microservice and card microservice to get started only after the config server
and Eureka server started successfully.
That's why we need to provide the health check details for the Eureka server as well.
So here the command is going to be same, but we just need to change the port number from 8071 to 8070.
We already mentioned the properties related to the health readiness and liveness inside the eureka server
application.yml file.
With this command, we should be good from health check perspective and after the health check you can
see we are going to extend the commonconfig.yml.
Under this we are going to use the microservice based config.
So let's see what is there inside the microservice based config.
So under the microservice based config we have deploy instructions and network related instructions
and we have an environment variable which is related to Rabbitmq.
We can delete this Rabbitmq related property here.
As a next step, I'll go to the Docker compose file and here I need to mention that depends on.
Using this depends on
I'm going to mention that my Eureka server is going to depend on config server because since my Eureka
server is going to load the properties with the help of config server, we need to make sure we are
mentioning this service as healthy.
After mentioning these depends on details,
I should also provide an environment variable under the Eureka server providing the spring application
name details.
So let me take this value from accounts microservice and paste the same value inside the Eureka Server.
So here you can see I have created a new environment variable and inside this property, which is spring
application name, I'm going to mention my Eureka server name, which is Eureka Server. Using the same
name,
we have created a file name inside the config server.
With this we should be good.
There are no other environment variables that I need to provide for my Eureka server.
It does not depend on any other microservices or database, so we should be good As a next step,
I can look at what details I need to mention
under accounts, loans and cards.
We know our individual microservice.
They need to connect with the Eureka server.
That's why we need to mention an environment variable.
And since the environment variable is going to common for all microservices, we can mention that inside
the commonconfig.yml and at the same time all our individual microservices they are going to depend
on Eureka Server.
And since this depends configuration is also common for all microservice, we can mention that under
the common-config.yml.
So here we have a service name with the name microservice-configserver-config.
Under this service I'm going to add one more depends on details.
Like just like how we have config server.
I'm going to add Eureka server.
So this is the service name that we have created inside the Docker compose file.
And for this service we need to mention the condition as service healthy.
After mentioning these depends on details, we can go to the environment variables just like how we
have spring config import.
We should also mention the URL details of the Eureka server.
The same I'm trying to mention here.
The property name is Eureka_CLIENT_SERVICEURL_DEFAULTZONE and here
we should not mention localhost.
Instead we should mention the service name that we have mentioned inside the Docker compose file.
The service name is Eureka Server followed by what is the port number where it will start 8070 and after
the port we need to mention /eureka.
So with these updates, all the configurations that we
have updated under this service name will be utilized by the accounts, loans and cards micro services.
So as a next step, let's try to update the image related information for accounts from S6 to S8 and
very similar update I want to do for loans microservice, followed by cards microservice.
So with these changes we should be good.
I can quickly try to copy the same docker-compose.yml file into other profiles like prod.
I'm trying to copy these latest docker compose Yaml file and very similarly I'm going to open the profile
and here also I'm going to paste the content from the default profile.
Now very similar thing I'm going to do for commonconfig.yml and paste the same under the prod
and here the spring profiles active.
I'll change from default to prod.
Let me do the same for QA as well.
You might be wondering why I'm trying to duplicate the same kind of compose and common config in different
folders.
Like I said before, this will give you a flexibility in future whenever you want to go with different
different requirements in different environments, then you can update the respective Yaml file.
So with these changes we have updated the Docker compose file. In the next lecture,
let's try to start all the containers with the help of Docker, compose command and try to validate
the Eureka changes that we have developed inside the Docker environment.
Thank you and I'll catch you in the next lecture bye.